<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life of faith Wherein is shewed the general use of faith in all the passages of a Christians life. Together with a discourse of right judgment on Joh.7.24. By H. Lukin.</title>
            <author>Lukin, H. (Henry), 1628-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 256 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 138 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49463</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3477</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213826</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826097</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826097</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30489</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49463)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30489)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1798:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life of faith Wherein is shewed the general use of faith in all the passages of a Christians life. Together with a discourse of right judgment on Joh.7.24. By H. Lukin.</title>
                  <author>Lukin, H. (Henry), 1628-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 170, 1-81, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.H. for John Allen, at the Rising-Sun in St. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Text continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John VII, 24 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30489:1"/>
            <p>THE LIFE OF FAITH.</p>
            <p>Wherein Is ſhewed the general uſe of Faith in all the paſſages of a Chriſtians life.</p>
            <p>Together With a Diſcourſe of right Judgment on <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.24.</p>
            <p>By <hi>H. Lukin.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Now the Juſt ſhall live by Faith. <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Do ye judge uprightly, O ye Sons of men? <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 58.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>John Allen,</hi> as the Riſing-Sun in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:30489:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30489:2"/>
            <head>To all that have obtained precious Faith.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Grace and Peace,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the wiſh of a good man, That he could be the ſame to God that his right hand was to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; my goodneſs extends not unto God, but to the Saints that are upon earth, and to the excellent, in whom is my delight: For theſe would I gladly ſpend and be ſpent, if I might in any thing be a helper of their Faith and
<pb facs="tcp:30489:3"/>
Joy. I thank God I am not yet in <hi>Zacharies</hi> caſe; that I ſhould be fain to write my mind, but when either the hand of violence, or the clods of the Valley ſhall ſtop my mouth, I ſhall be as unable to write as ſpeak; It is but little that I can do by ſpeaking, my words will reach but to few, and where they do reach, I may complain with <hi>Melancthon,</hi> that Old <hi>Adam</hi> is too hard for me: And I am willing to try this way alſo, if by any means I may help forward any in the way to Heaven, and I hope I ſhall the more willingly dye, if I may leave any thing behind me which may be of the leaſt uſe to the Church of God when I ſhall ſleep in the duſt. I confeſs I have not in the publiſhing of this ſmal Treatiſe done as the <hi>Romans</hi> were wont in preferring Laws, conſulted firſt with the Learned, to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what I have written be not alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy contained in ſomwhat that hath been written before, or whether it be not
<pb facs="tcp:30489:3"/>
contrary to the Doctrine formerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, or whether it may be uſeful to the Church; but I remember the Counſel of <hi>Petrarcha, Quia ſimul omnia vel legere, vel audire &amp; meminiſſe non potes, utiliſſimis quidem, &amp; (quando brevitas eſt amica memoriae) breviſſimis quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que te fulcias.</hi> We cannot read or hear every thing, therefore I have choſen to treat of thoſe things that are moſt uſeful, and have handled them very briefly. For the manner of hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling theſe things I lie open to the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of others; he that is afraid of leaves muſt not go to the wood, we ſay, and he that is afraid of mens cenſures muſt not write Books, elſe we had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed more of many learned mens la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. If in any thing I may not be well underſtood by ordinary Readers, I may anſwer as the Proteſtants do to the Papiſts about the perſpicuity of the Scriptures, it is not the manner of delivery, but the thing delivered that
<pb facs="tcp:30489:4"/>
makes it obſcure, and there are other things plain enough for them; to make things obſcure which are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves plain, by great ſwelling words of vanity (beſides the ſinfulneſs of it) is ſuch an unmanly piece of Padantry as I have alwaies abhorred from; yet if at any time I have happened to ſpeak of ſuch things as have been above the reach of ordinary hearers, I have not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted it altogether loſt labor to ſuch, if they have thereby been delivered from the opinion of their own omniſciency, and underſtood thus much by it, that <hi>they did not underſtand all things. I fear God,</hi> who knows with what aim and intention I write and ſpeak every word, and I dare not accept of the ſervice of Fancy, Pride, Vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, or any corrupt Paſſion (which are ready enough to mingle themſelves with whatever we do) in that which I must go to God with in Prayer, to commend to his bleſſing; and now at my parting with you I will give you a
<pb facs="tcp:30489:4"/>
few words of advice, and I beſeech you let my counſel be acceptable to you.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Learn to underſtand the nature of the Covenant of Grace, that you may know upon what terms God and you are agreed; there is no excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therein either againſt infirmities on your part, or againſt afflictions on Gods part; you may break the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God, (not of right, but it may <hi>de facto</hi> ſo fall out) and God may viſit you with a Rod for it, and yet not break his Covenant, <hi>Pſal. 89.30, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is not perfect obedience re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired on your part, (that is, as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation, though perfect obedience is our duty, elſe our moral infirmities were no ſins; <hi>where there is no Law there is no Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion)</hi> neither hath God promiſed worldly happineſs. <hi>Though my houſe be not ſo with God, ſaith</hi> David, <hi>yet he hath made with me an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb facs="tcp:30489:5"/>
Covenant in all things or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and ſure,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>2 Sam. 23.5.</hi> Though my houſe be not ſo with God, that is, either as <hi>ver. 3.</hi> he had not ruled in the fear of God, but had miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried in the buſineſs of <hi>Uriah,</hi> and it is moſt likely in other things, by <hi>Abſaloms</hi> inſinuations, and the effect of them upon the people, <hi>2 Sam. 15.3, &amp;c.</hi> or it had not been as a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning without clouds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as <hi>ver. 4.</hi> but its happineſs had been eclipſed by the buſineſs of <hi>Amnon,</hi> and worſe by that of <hi>Abſolom.</hi> Yet the Covenant of God was ſo ordered in all things, as it remained ſure as to ſpiritual things, which are therefore called, the <hi>ſure mercies of David, Iſa. 55.3.</hi> If theſe things were well underſtood and conſidered, we ſhould not be diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by our infirmities, though we might be humbled for them; as an eminent Saint ſaid on his death bed, he had much peace and quietneſs, not ſo much from a greater meaſure of
<pb facs="tcp:30489:5"/>
Grace than other Chriſtians had, or from any immediate witneſs of the Spirit, but becauſe he had a more clear underſtanding of the Covenant of Grace than many others, having ſtudied it and preached it ſo many years. Again, we ſhall neither charge God fooliſhly in afflictions, as if he did us any wrong in not ſtanding to his Covenant, nor take him for our enemy, as <hi>Job 13.24.</hi> interpreting them as evidences of his wrath, or effects of revenging juſtice. And laſtly, We ſhall not flatter our ſelves with hopes of outward prosperity, nor be troubled with diſappointment when we faile of it, which is an addition to mens miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, when, as one ſaies, expectation takes more upon truſt than enjoyment is able to diſcharge. If we have food and raiment let us be therewith contented, <hi>1 Tim. 6.8.</hi> We indented with God for no more than <hi>Jacob</hi> did, <hi>Gen. 28.20.</hi> as to this life, <hi>Mat. 6.33.</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>31.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb facs="tcp:30489:6"/>
               <hi>2.</hi> Mind your preſent duty, and the work of every day in the day; Every day brings trouble enough with it, as we ſay in our Proverb. There is much talk of the <hi>Turk</hi> and the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and our next neighbour doth us more hurt than both of them; we look with dreadful apprehenſions upon the evils that are at a diſtance, and mind not our preſent dangers which we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in, or the temptations which we are dayly aſſaulted with. Many are like the <hi>Aſtronomers</hi> that look up to the Heavens to foreſee what will after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards come to paſs, and fall into a ditch before their feet. <hi>Corn. Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa de Aſtronomia.</hi> We fear future calamities, and in a moment go down to the grave, <hi>Job 21.13.</hi> We fear what the Sword or ſome other Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may do a great while hence, and a feaver, or any other diſeaſe, which we are dayly lyable to, may do us as much hurt, <hi>Lipſius de conſtantia, l. 2. c. 19.</hi> I confeſs, a prudent foreſight
<pb facs="tcp:30489:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of evill is good, <hi>Prov. 22.3.</hi> but there is no better preparation for it, than to mind our preſent duty; let us keep a pure conſcience, and the teſtimony thereof will be our rejoycing in an evill day, <hi>2 Cor. 1.12.</hi> Let us give all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to make our calling and election ſure, and that will deliver us from the bondage of the fear of death. Let us do good while we have opportunity, and ſo lay up for our ſelves a good foundation againſt the time to come. <hi>1 Tim. 6.18, 19.</hi> If we know not what evill will be on the earth, let us liberally give to others, <hi>Eccleſ. 11.2.</hi> that when the evill comes we may ſay with <hi>Antonius, Hoc habeo quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque dedi, Seneca de Beneficiis, l. 6. c. 3.</hi> what we ſo lay up is in ſafe hands, and will be duly paid again, <hi>Prov. 19.17.</hi> I could tell you of one, who having given ſomewhat to a poor man, and conſidering with himſelf whether he had not injured himſelf by giving beyond his ability, preſently
<pb facs="tcp:30489:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
corrected himſelf with thoſe thoughts, that he had lent it to one that would pay well again, and within an hour had it reſtored above ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, in a way which he never thought of.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Be very carefull to walk blameleſly, and inoffenſively. Chriſtians are truſted with the honour of Religion, as Magistrates, and all in any authority, are with the Dignity and honour of their places, which they are not to betray to ſcorne and contempt, by doing any thing that is baſe or unworthy thereof. But further, by the Profeſſion of Religion we derive upon our ſelves the enmity of the world, <hi>John 15.19. Gal. 4.29.</hi> this is an old grudge, an ancient hatred, <hi>Ezek. 25.15.</hi> therefore we had need to behave our ſelves wiſely, in a perfect way, <hi>Pſal. 101.2.</hi> that we may maintain an aw of us in them, <hi>Mark. 6.20.</hi> and then we may ſay with <hi>Caligula, Oderint dum metuant:</hi> Let them
<pb facs="tcp:30489:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hate us, ſo they fear us. <hi>Zeuxis</hi> painted a Boy holding grapes in his hand, and he had painted the grapes ſo lively, that he deceived the birds, and made them come to eat them; but he was diſpleaſed with himſelf, that he had not painted the Boy ſo lively as to ſcare them away. If we take upon us a form of godlineſs, to contract the hatred of the world, let us be ſure to expreſſe ſo much of the power of it, as to make them fear us. And though this will not alwayes reſtrain the rage of men ſo farre, but they may make bold ſometimes to offend us, yet we ſhall have a witneſſe for us in their own breaſts against themſelves, which will at one time or other be whispering to them as <hi>Pilate</hi>'s Wife to him, <hi>Matth. 27.19. Have nothing to do with ſuch a juſt man;</hi> and will ſooner or later laſh them worſe than the Heathens inexorable <hi>Nemeſis:</hi> but if, by an unworthy carriage, you loſe the repute of holineſſe, and integrity, they will
<pb facs="tcp:30489:8"/>
make bold to do any thing to you, without mercy, and without fear, <hi>Jer. 50.7.</hi> as birds will ſit upon the head of a <hi>Mormoluke,</hi> and pick at the very face of it, when they perceive it is but the image of a man, and not a real living man. Let none be able to finde any occaſion againſt you, unleſſe it be concerning the Law of your God, <hi>Dan. 6.5.</hi> reſolve, if it be poſſible, to cut off occaſion from them that deſire occaſion, <hi>2 Cor. 11.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> Be ſure to follow the work of Mortification: then you will be fit for any condition; the temptations of prosperity will then loſe their force againſt you; you will be as <hi>Barzillai, 2 Sam. 15.35.</hi> all the pleaſures of the Kings Court were no temptation to him, becauſe through age <hi>deſire failed, Eccleſ. 12.5.</hi> So the things of the world loſe their ſavour and reliſh with a mortified Chriſtian; as he replied (when it was told him, If he would pleaſe <hi>Caeſar</hi> he need not live
<pb facs="tcp:30489:8"/>
upon herbs) That he that could live upon herbs need not pleaſe <hi>Caeſar:</hi> He that hath ſo farre mortified his affections, as to be content, as <hi>Epictetus</hi> ſayes, <hi>Enchirid. cap. 21.</hi> to be at Gods finding, as a Gueſt at a table, that takes what is carved for him, and no more, need not fawn upon any man, much leſſe violate his conſcience for the great things of the world. Neither will loſſes or afflictions, on the other hand, be any great trouble to them, as the Martyr ſaid, If you take away my meat, God will take away my ſtomack, and then ſhe ſhould not miſſe her meat: If your honors be taken away, and your pride be taken away firſt; if your earthly mindneſſe and ſenſuality be mortified before you looſe your eſtates and worldly accomodations, you will eaſily bear the loſſe of them, as he that hath a member mortified, feels not what you do to it. Violent affections are alwaies dangerous; as they that <hi>will</hi> be rich, ſo they that <hi>will</hi> be great or
<pb facs="tcp:30489:9"/>
honorable, fall into temptations and ſnares, <hi>&amp;c. 1 Tim. 6.9.</hi> and whatever our hearts cleave to, whenever it is rent from us, it will be as the renting of our fleſh. <hi>Jonah</hi> was <hi>exceeding</hi> glad of his gourde, <hi>Jon. 4.6.</hi> and he was as <hi>exceeding</hi> angry when it withered<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If the Sea grow rough, ſtrike ſail; if times grow troubleſome, ſhrink up and contract your deſires, and then ſay, as <hi>Luther, Miſer ſit, qui miſer eſſe poteſt;</hi> Let him be miſerable that can be miſerable. The ſenſe of loſſes or any afflictions is according to the value which we put upon any thing. Take a <hi>Ruffian,</hi> who as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſayes, <hi>Malit Rempublicam turbari, quam comam, ſollicitior ſit de capitis ſui decore, quam de ſalute;</hi> de <hi>brevitate vitae,</hi> cap. <hi>12. That had rather ſee the Common-wealth in diſorder, than his hair:</hi> that takes more care to have his head handſome, than he doth (as I may truly tranſlate it) of his ſalvation: What an affliction
<pb facs="tcp:30489:9"/>
would it be to ſuch an one to have his hair cut off: <hi>quomodo excandeſcit, ſi quid ex juba ſua decifum eſt:</hi> when another, that mindes conveniency more than ornament, would account himſelf rid of a trouble; as <hi>Seneca,</hi> when he was old deſired to be diſcharged of the burden of his riches, and ſaid, he ſhould not thereby become poor, but ſhould, when he was rid of thoſe things that did blindfold him with their brightneſs, beſtow his time in ſtudy, which he was wont to imploy in his gardens, and poſſeſſions. <hi>Salvian</hi> ſhews excellently, how happy a mortified Christian may be in any condition, however others may through ignorance judge them miſerable, <hi>de Gubernati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Dei, lib. 1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, Brethren be of good comfort, if the world will contribute nothing to your joy, but adde to your affliction, you have a joy which they cannot intermeddle with, <hi>Prov. 14.10.</hi> you need not to be beholding to
<pb facs="tcp:30489:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
them to make you happy, or entreat them to ſpare your joy, which they cannot take from you, <hi>John 16.22.</hi> And if your afflictions encreaſe, though the world, and carnal profeſſors may look upon you with ſcorn, becauſe you are black by the ſun looking upon you, <hi>Cant. 1.6.</hi> with <hi>Obad. 12.</hi> and <hi>Micah 4.11.</hi> yet God hath thoſe comforts in ſtore for you against ſuch a day, which you, it may be, never taſted of yet, <hi>2 Cor. 1.4, 5.</hi> as the experience of many of the Martyrs hath abundantly teſtified. Love as brethren, if the world hate you. Have peace among your ſelves, if you cannot have peace with the world: And ſpeak oft one to another, to comfort, encourage, and provoke each other; and there will come a time, when you ſhall diſcorn betwixt the righteous and the wicked, betwixt him that ſerves God, and him that ſerveth him not. I will conclude with the words of <hi>Polycarp. Leyſerus,</hi> Ep.
<pb facs="tcp:30489:10"/>
               <hi>ded. part. ſecund.</hi> Loc. <hi>Theolog. Chemnitiis;</hi> That, when we ſhall ſee cauſe to take up his complaint, we may alſo make uſe of his counſel; <hi>Orbatur partim Eccleſia viris praeſtantiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimis, &amp; optime de ea meritis: partim hoſtiliter multis in locis fideles Paſtores per impios lupos ex ſtatione ſua extur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur, partim Epicureus ſani Evangelii contemptus cum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terva</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in populo paſſim invaleſcit: ad quae mala accedunt mille injuriae, quibus vigor &amp; alacritas in fidelibus verbi Praeconibus retunditur; odia item &amp; infectationes eorum, qui pro defenſione veritatis in acie non fuerunt poſtremi, idque ab iis qui impigri &amp; vigilantes</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>unà no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſcum eſſe debebant. Haec certè mala Eccleſiam everſura videntur. Humani verò praeſidiis
<pb facs="tcp:30489:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hic vel nihil, vel parum omnino ſupereſt. Quaeramus itaque aliquid ſolatii in mutua animorum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctione: &amp; piis exhortationibus nos mutuò erigamus, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmemus, donec omnibus pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculis inſani maris nobis emetiendi ſuperatis, portum aeternae patriae lae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i ſervati attingamus, Deum ſimul piis &amp; aſſiduis precibus fatigantes, ut magnus ille &amp; fortiſſimus Michael pro populo ſuo pugnet, &amp; naviculam ſuam contra adverſitatum procellas &amp; defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onum voragines tueatur, quo tandem ea ſubducta, ovantes in aeternam patriam ingrediamur.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:30489:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>BOOKS ſold by <hi>John Allen,</hi> at the Sun-riſing in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>CAryl,</hi> on <hi>Job.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Volum. 5. quarto.</item>
                     <item>Volum. 7. quarto.</item>
                     <item>Volum. 9. quarto.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Beza Novum Teſtamentum.</hi> folio.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Allen</hi>'s Scripture Chronology. quart.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Call to the Unconverted. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lukine</hi>'s Practice of Godlineſſs. qu.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Burges</hi> of Orignal ſin. folio.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Davenport</hi> and <hi>Hook</hi> of <hi>New england,</hi> their Catechiſme.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gataker</hi> againſt that wicked Cheat, <hi>Judicial Aſtrology:</hi> proving it to be the Abomination of the Heathens, and that it ought not to be tolerated in a Chriſtian Commonwealth. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 47.12. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.2.</item>
               <item>The Faith and Order practiſed in the Congregational Churches in <hi>England,</hi> agreed and conſented unto by their Elders and Meſſengers, at their Meeting in the <hi>Savoy. October</hi> 12. 1658.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cotton</hi> on the Covenant. Octavo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The heart of New-England rent at the Blasphemies of the preſent Generation:</hi> Or,
<pb facs="tcp:30489:12"/>
A brief Tract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re concerning the Doctrine of the Quakers, demonſtrating the deſtructive nature thereof, to Religion, the Churches, and the State; with conſideration of the Remedy againſt it, occaſional ſatisfaction to Objections, and confirmation of the contrary Truth, by <hi>John Norton,</hi> Teacher of the Church of Chriſt, at <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Quakers folly made manifeſt to all men,</hi> in a publick diſpute at <hi>Sandwich</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> between three <hi>Quakers</hi> and Mr. <hi>T. Danſon Miniſter;</hi> to which is added a Narrative of their wicked abominable practiſes, by the ſame Author.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Miniſters Maintenance by Tithes, Infant Baptiſm, Humane Learning, and the Sword of the Magiſtrate,</hi> clearly maintained by the Word of God, by <hi>Immanuel Bourne,</hi> Miniſter of Gods Word at <hi>Waltham</hi> in <hi>Leiceſter-ſhire;</hi> with a ſober Anſwer to <hi>Anthony Pierſons</hi> great Caſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ythes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Judicial Aſtrology</hi> totally routed and their pretence to Scripture, Reaſon, and Experience anſwered, by <hi>J. A.</hi> Publiſhed for publick good.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30489:12"/>
            <head>THE Life of Faith.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The worth or excellency of every thing is according to its uſefulneſs. <hi>Hab. 2.4. Rom. 1.17. Gal. 3.11. Heb. 10.38.</hi> conſidered, and their mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enquired into, how places of the Old Teſtament are cited in the new. The Life of every true Believer is an everlaſting life, what living by Faith doth import.</head>
               <p>THe nature of Faith I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready endeavoured to explain in a ſmall Treatiſe formerly publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. I have now taken in hand
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30489:13"/>
to ſhew the uſe of it, for it is this wherein every thing attains its per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; and as habits are ſaid to be perfected in their acts, for which they are: ſo faith may (in a good ſenſe) be ſaid to be perfected in works, becauſe of the univerſal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence that it hath into the whole courſe of our lives; and for this cauſe it is called <hi>Pretious Faith,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1. the value of every thing being anſwerable to the uſefulneſs of it. For divers Ages before the time of <hi>Socrates,</hi> moſt men were led by Fancy rather than Reaſon: As a Learned man hath obſerved (<hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaubon</hi> of <hi>Enthuſiaſme,</hi> p. 4.) and the only happineſs of thoſe Ages was to be exempted from Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, for there muſt needs be a good agreement, where no reaſon is uſed to examine or diſprove: b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Socrates</hi> taught them the uſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by organizing (as one expreſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it) and, as it were, enſouling the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30489:13"/>
body of Philoſophy, reducing the Principles thereof to ſuch order, as they might be uſeful and practica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; for which he was judged by the Oracle to be the wiſeſt of men; but here is a point of higher wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; the Spirit of God in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures hath taught us the uſe of Faith, whereby we live a life as far excelling the life of Reaſon, as the life of Reaſon excels the life of Senſe; and how much faith doth conduce to this life we ſhall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, by a due weighing thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture where the Juſt are ſaid to <hi>live by Faith:</hi> And the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral caſes wherein the Holy Ghoſt uſes this expreſſion: We firſt meet with it, <hi>Hab.</hi> 4.2. where ſome refer Faith to the ſubject, reading the words, The Juſt by Faith ſhall live: others to the predicate, according to the ordinary reading, and this indeed ſeems more genuine, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever if we ſhould take the firſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30489:14"/>
reading, the ſence will not differ. There had been little queſtion made about the meaning of this place, but that the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.11. ſeems to apply it to another end, than was inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Prophet: making uſe thereof to prove juſtification by Faith without the Works of the Law. Some ſuppoſe the Prophet intends this chiefly of Juſtification, and not of any deliverance from the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> inſerting it as a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion not properly belonging to the Argument in hand: it being the manner of the Prophets, upon occaſion of particular deliverances more remarkable than ordinary, either related, or foretold; to riſe higher, and proceed further, to that more general deliverance of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and ſpiritual reſtauration and enlargement of the Church by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. (ſee <hi>Gataker</hi> on <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.1.) others think he ſpeaks chiefly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30489:14"/>
of the deliverance of the Jews from the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> and that till it was accompliſhed they ſhould ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port themſelves by Faith, and than the Apoſtle might notwithſtanding apply it to the buſineſs of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe theſe temporal deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances were types of ſpiritual, and it is the ſame Faith whereby we truſt God both for ſpiritual and temporal mercies; and if faith in God for temporal deliverances be ſo acceptable to him, then alſo will faith in him for everlaſting ſalvation be as pleaſing in his ſight. So <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrezat</hi> on <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38. Others judge that the Prophet ſpeaks in a more large and comprehenſive ſence, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding thereby whatſoever may be comprehended under life; and indeed whatever was the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Prophet in that place, the word may be extended to ſuch a latitude of ſignification, as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from the uſe which the Apoſtle
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30489:15"/>
makes of it in the New Teſtament, for it is plain that the Apoſtles did not only multiply inferences from particular places of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and apply one place to diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent purpoſes (as we may ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.26, 28.) but they altered pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which they cited; the former they might do as men endued with reaſon, whoſe work it is to multiply concluſions from a few Principles; the Law of Nature, and the whole body of moral Philoſophy (as ſome think) being hereby made up of a few <hi>common Notions:</hi> The latter they might do as Apoſtles inſpired by the Holy Ghoſt: ſo that they might not only cite Scripture, but make and interpret Scripture, wherefore ſometimes they give not the words, but the ſence of the Prophets. What the Prophet calls his glory, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.9. the Apoſtle calls tongue, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.26. What the Prophet calls opening the ear,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30489:15"/>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.6. the Apoſtle interprets preparing a body, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.5. So likewiſe, compare <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.4. with <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38. Sometimes they leave out ſomething which is not to the preſent purpoſe; compare <hi>Deu.</hi> 24.1. with <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.31. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.5. with <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.24. Sometimes there is an addition of ſomething for il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtration; compare <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.13. with <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.10. Sometimes ſome ſmall mutations: See more of this in <hi>Tarnovins</hi> on <hi>Amos</hi> 5.27. In theſe places, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.11. it is evident the Apoſtle ſpeaks of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. (where he doth not in formal words indeed quote the place, but hath clear re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to it) he ſpeaks of Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; and <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38. he ſpeaks of Chriſtians ſupporting, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting themſelves by faith in trials and afflictions, till the time appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for their deliverance; which ſeems alſo to be the chief intent of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30489:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the Prophet <hi>Habakkuk,</hi> and all theſe are comprehended in the word <hi>Life;</hi> for all men are by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture dead in Law, that is, bound over to eternal death, condemned already, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.18. ſome under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the threatning thus, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. Now in Juſtification this ſentence is repealed, and man is inveſted with a new right to everlaſting life, wherefore it is called, Juſtification to life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18. and we need not diſtinguiſh this from everlaſting life, for the life which a Beleever is reſtored to, is an everlaſting life, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.36. and 5.24. Though the Acts of this life may be for a time obſtructed, yet it can never be wholly extinguiſhed, as Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> hath determined in his <hi>Remains, p.</hi> 108. whoſe judgement (it may be) will be more regarded by ſome than the judgement of many other learned men who have fully proved it. And Sanctification is ordinarily
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30489:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
underſtood by life. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1. ſpeaks of initial Sanctification or Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.18. the Gentiles before faith are ſaid to be alienated from the life of God; by this life we are alive to God, fitted for communion with him, as we are by Reaſon made capable of converſe with men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.11. but yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by life we are not to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand life ſimply and nakedly <hi>in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracto,</hi> but an happy comfortable life; <hi>Vivere non eſt vita ſed valere,</hi> a ſickly life is not worthy the name of life, ſo a diſconſolate life is the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.4. Yea, <hi>Paul,</hi> by reaſon of his afflictions, ſaith, he was in deaths oft, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23. So our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.15. A mans life conſiſteth not in the abundance of the things which he poſſeſſeth, that is, they do not make a mans life comfortable. So ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.8. Now we <hi>live</hi> if you ſtand faſt in the Lord, ſo
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30489:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
he might have done if they had not ſtood faſt; but he means, this would be a reviving, or a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to him, to ſee their ſtedfaſtneſs and perſeverance, as he expreſſeth himſelf more fully, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.19. A Beleever may not only make a ſhift to get to heaven by Faith, but may maintain himſelf comfortably in an evil World. <hi>So that to live by Faith imports thus much, We are by faith not only acquitted from the guilt of ſin, and entitled to everlaſting life: but are enabled to hold on chearfully, and comfortably in an holy courſe, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all temptations and troubles which we meet with in this evil world.</hi> Neither let any think that hereby too much is aſcribed to Faith, ſince Chriſt is our life, <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.25. Chap. 14.6. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.4. for though we ſpeak herein ſomewhat improperly, or <hi>Metonymically:</hi> yet it is according to the ordinary manner of ſpeech; for when we ſay, A man lives by his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:30489:17"/>
or by his wits, every body un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands it of what he gets by theſe: So to live by faith, is to live by what we have coming in by faith, either morally, or by reall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of our Union with Chriſt, what it is not, <hi>viz.</hi> Eſſential, Perſonal, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal, a meer Union of affections: <hi>Joh. 17.21.</hi> and <hi>Gal. 2.20.</hi> vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated: the effects of this Union ſhewed by divers ſimilitudes; how this Union is by Faith; of the legal Union betwixt Chriſt and the Elect before Faith, by ſome aſſerted; the relation betwixt Chriſt and his Elect as the neceſſary foundation of his ſatisfaction.</head>
               <p>IT being ſo that Chriſt is the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal and fountain of a Beleevers
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30489:18"/>
life, I muſt begin the proof of what I have taken in hand to clear, with the Union which is betwixt Chriſt and beleevers, this being the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Communion with him. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.20. our Saviour tells his Diſciples, that after his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when they ſhould receive a more full meaſure of the Spirit, they ſhould know two great myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, his Union with the Father, and his Union with them, whereby they did, as it were, mutually poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs each other; of this Union we read further, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.21, 23. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12.</p>
               <p>Now, if any ask me what this Union is, I muſt tell them, I know not; <hi>Chriſtianus ad multa respon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere poteſt Ignoro,</hi> ſaith <hi>Austin,</hi> If I ſhould ſay, it is a myſtical uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I do in effect ſay, it is ſuch an Union as I do not underſtand, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.32. yet as they ſay, we may know God <hi>per viam remotionis vel
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30489:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
negationis, &amp; per viam cauſalitatis:</hi> So I may tell you what this Union is not, and what the effects of it are.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is not an eſſential Union, as ſome have boldly affirmed; for this would infer an equality of power, holineſs, wiſdom, &amp;c. that is, make the creature not only perfect, in holineſs, but omnipotent, omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcient; the infiniteneſs and perfection of all excellencies being of the Eſſence of the Godhead.</p>
               <p>And for that place, <hi>John</hi> 17.21. it is forced to ſerve two <hi>Hypotheſes.</hi> Some thence deny the Deity of Chriſt, becauſe it is but ſuch an Union that is between the Father and the Son, as is betwixt Chriſt and believers. Others would thence infer an eſſential Union betwixt Chriſt and Believers, becauſe it is ſuch an Union as is betwixt the Father and the Son. But the place will ſerve neither of their purpoſes, ſignifying, as <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.48. only ſome
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30489:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
kinde of ſimilitude, no equality, as <hi>Glaſſius</hi> hath fully proved, <hi>Gram. ſacr.</hi> 501. &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This Union is not a perſonal Union, as ſome ſtrangely ſpeak, (ſee <hi>W. Dell.</hi> on <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20.) The whole proceſs of the laſt Judgment (as ſet down <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.31, &amp;c.) fully proves, that Chriſt and Believers remain diſtinct perſons, and that place, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. is not to be underſtood literally, for then there were a plain contradiction in it. But Chriſt is ſaid to live in us, becauſe he makes us live, as will appear by comparing <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. with <hi>Galat.</hi> 4.6. in one place the ſpirit is ſaid to cry, in another place to make us cry. <hi>Nos clamamus, ſed ille clamaredictus eſt, qui facit ut nos cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin de correp. &amp; Grat.</hi> c. 15. And the Apoſtle ſpeaks in that place, as in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10. but as one afraid of ſeeming to aſſume to himſelf, and derogate
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:30489:19"/>
from the Grace of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is not a corporeal Union, as the Papiſts would prove from <hi>John</hi> 6.56. that place is interpreted literally, only to ſerve their <hi>hypotheſis</hi> of tranſubſtantiation.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is not a meer Union of affections, ſuch as was in the primitive Chriſtians, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32. or in the ten Kings, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.13. though there is ſuch an union of affections, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.5. yet this is but the effect of a nearer Union, which (though we fully underſtand not its nature) is ſet forth to us by ſeveral ſimilitudes, as of a vine and its branches, <hi>John</hi> 15.1. &amp;c. Of an head and members, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11. Of an husband and wife, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.32. all which ſhew the effects of this union, denoting the influence of divine power and vertue, which believers have from Jeſus Chriſt: the ſympathy that he hath with them: their ſubjection to his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30489:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
guidance, and direction: the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection which they have, and freedome from the Law by Jeſus Chriſt: as a woman under the covert of her husband: But of theſe things in their place.</p>
               <p>I now come to ſhew how this Union is made up by Faith; which I prove,</p>
               <p>Firſt, from 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. where being in the Faith, and Chriſt being in them, are made indifferently a proof of Chriſt ſpeaking in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, Of the ſenſe and contexture of that place, See the <hi>Animadverſions</hi> of Sr. <hi>Norton Knatchbull.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Chriſt dwells in the heart by faith,</hi> Epheſ. 3.17. he ſtands and knocks, and Faith is the opening to him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.20. when <hi>Lydia</hi> believed her heart was opened.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By Faith we are eſpouſed to Jeſus Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. As the marriage Union is made by the conſent of both parties, ſo is this
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:30489:20"/>
Union betwixt Chriſt and the ſoul; Chriſt hath given his conſent by the offer and promiſe of the Goſpel, and the ſoul conſents, when by faith it accepts this offer, and layes hold on this Promiſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. By faith we are made the ſons of God, <hi>John</hi> 1.12. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26. and conſequently Partakers of the ſpirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. Some indeed ſpeak of an Union betwixt Chriſt and the elect before Faith, by his Incarnation, which they call a legal Union, or a ſtipulatory Union, ſuch as is betwixt a Debtor and his Surety, which they make neceſſary to his ſatisfaction, ſince, as they ſay, <hi>unitas praeſtantis eſt fundamentum proprietatis ad officium praeſtitum:</hi> others again load this with dreadfull conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, making it the foundation of <hi>Antinomianiſme,</hi> the ruine of Chriſtian Religion, leaving no room for Remiſſion of ſinnes. I dare not peremptorily define in ſuch a caſe,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:30489:21"/>
yet it ſeems to me at preſent, that there muſt be ſome relation betwixt Chriſt &amp; his elect, whereby his ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction becomes available for them, &amp; whereby he may obtain for them ſpiritual bleſſings wherwith they are bleſt in him, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.3. amongſt which faith is to be certainly reckoned. But the forementioned conſequences of the former Doctrine, (as underſtood by them that maintain it) I cannot ſo clearly apprehend. If we have recourſe to the civil Law for the proof of them, which tells us, that every obligation is taken away by the payment of the debt; that tells us alſo, that <hi>vicarius paena corporalis</hi> cannot properly pay the debt: for in ſuch a caſe, that holds, <hi>dum alius ſolvit, aliud etiam ſolvitur.</hi> And if it be ſaid, it is the ſame <hi>in ſenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> civili,</hi> though not in <hi>ſenſu phyſico;</hi> I anſwer, in ſtrictneſs <hi>noxa ſequitur caput,</hi> and <hi>aliud pro alio invito creditori, ſolvi non poteſt, Myn ſinger,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:30489:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Inſtitut. Tit.</hi> 30. ſo that God did, in diſpenſing with the perſon, <hi>uti ſuo jure,</hi> and by an act of ſupream Dominion ſubſtitute Chriſt in our ſtead; wherefore it was free for him to appoint himſelf upon what termes the Obligation ſhould be taken away: and here was room enough left for Remiſſion. I will but refer to <hi>Grotius, de ſatisfac. c.</hi> 6. where he ſets down what the true notion of remiſſion is, and ſhews that there is properly Remiſſion, where an act of the rector or Creditor doth inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vene, to make a ſolution valid: ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedently to which act, ſuch a ſolution may be admitted or refuſed: and that ſuch an act doth here intervene is evident, which ſeems to be a <hi>diſpenſation,</hi> unleſs we will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>interpretation</hi> in as large a ſenſe as <hi>Suarez,</hi> l. 6. <hi>de legibus,</hi> cap. 1. S. 3. And further, <hi>Grotius</hi> doth in the ſame place yield, that <hi>ſolution ejuſdem</hi> doth not <hi>ipſo facto liberare:</hi> unleſs
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:30489:22"/>
it be with this intention, <hi>ut reus liberetur.</hi> So that whatever Chriſt paid, it might be that the ſinner might be freed, at ſuch a time, or on ſuch termes as ſhould be agreed on between the Father and the Son. Whereas ſome ſay, what Chriſt did or ſuffer'd, was as a Mediator, this will not prove, that he was not <hi>ſponſor:</hi> the ſame perſon may be Mediator and Surety, as the learned <hi>Parker</hi> hath proved by the examples of <hi>Judah, Gen.</hi> 43.8, 9. and <hi>Paul, Philem.</hi> 9.18. <hi>de deſcenſu,</hi> lib. 3. <hi>Sec.</hi> 95. We ſhould as carefully avoid <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> in this caſe, as <hi>Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mianiſm. Aquinas,</hi> p. 3. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 49. <hi>Art.</hi> 1. c. goeth as far as any man, for he ſaith plainly, that the Redemption of Chriſt becomes available to the Remiſſion of our ſinnes, as he is our head, and we his members, as the hand may do ſomething to ſatisfie for the fault which hath been committed by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:30489:22"/>
the foot: becauſe <hi>actiones ſunt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitorum.</hi> I have ſometime won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, how this place of <hi>Aquinas</hi> eſcaped Mr. <hi>Wottons</hi> cenſure, (<hi>de Reconciliatione,</hi> P. 1. l. 2. cap. 10. N. 3. &amp; cap. 16. N. 9. where he cites it) conſidering how he diſputes <hi>P.</hi> 2. <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>C.</hi> 16. &amp;c. But to leave this digreſſion; Whatever the Relation was betwixt Chriſt and his Elect, as the foundation of his Satisfaction, yet that which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Scripture may moſt properly be called our Union with him, is not before we believe, when we become actual partakers of the benefits of his death, as will more fully appear in the following Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:30489:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> We are juſtified by Faith, not before faith. Why ſuch as are juſtified are afflicted, and their happineſs deferred? How faith juſtifies? How imputed for righteouſneſs? Sanctification our formal happineſs. The fruit of the ſpirit, received by faith; yet in the Ordinances. <hi>John 7, 38, 39. Hoſ. 14.6. Pſal. 92.13.</hi> expounded.</head>
               <p>HAving thus laid the foundation, I will now proceed to ſhew you, what Communion a Believer hath with Jeſus Chriſt, by vertue of this Union: and</p>
               <p>Firſt, They partake of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and ſo are freed from the ſentence of death, which before they lay under. The Scripture abounds with the proof of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:30489:23"/>
this, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.43. <hi>cap.</hi> 13.39. and, whatever attempts have been made upon theſe places to diſable them for the proof of Juſtification by Faith, yet that place of the Apoſtle, <hi>Galat.</hi> 2.16. is beyond all exception, <hi>Knowing,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that a man is not juſtified by the works of the Law, but by the faith of Jeſus Chriſt, even we have believed in Jeſus Chriſt, that we might be juſtified by the faith of Chriſt:</hi> they believed to the end they might be juſtified: now the end is not before the means, unleſs in intention. As for thoſe who have ſo earneſtly contended for Juſtification before Faith, they ſeem to do it out of a good intent, leſt we ſhould derogate from the Merit of Chriſt, the juſtice of God, or the comfort of the Saints. But they are afraid, where no fear is: for yielding the certainty of Gods Election, and the efficacy of Chriſts death, whereby the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:30489:24"/>
Salvation of the Elect becomes ſure in it ſelf, <hi>certitudine objectivâ,</hi> yea ſuppoſing the greateſt redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancy of merit in the ſufferings of Chriſt, all this doth not amount to juſtification. And I would deſire thoſe who labour ſo earneſtly in this buſineſs, to conſider theſe few things;</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Elect are kept long out of heaven after the ſatisfaction made by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They lie under many evils while they are in this world: theſe things ſenſe will not ſuffer us to deny.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is equally injuſt, to inflict upon any what is not due to them, and to detain from them what is their due: and whether is it harder to ſay, that we are not juſtified till we believe, notwithſtanding the ſatisfaction which Chriſt hath made for us? or that we are juſtified, and yet left under the power of Satan,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:30489:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the curſe of the Law, dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes? wherefore they take not a right courſe to vindicate the juſtice of God: but the matter ſeems to be thus, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the purpoſe of God towards ſinners hath been, and whatever intrinſick value may be in the obedience of Jeſus Chriſt, yet his merit was not abſolute, but founded upon an act of Grace, God conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending to accept of the ſatisfaction of our Surety, where he might have required the Debt of us: wherefore it was free for him to appoint, upon what termes, and at what time, theſe for whom Chriſt died ſhould be made partakers of the benefit of his death, and under what diſcipline they ſhould be exerciſed till they partake thereof, eſpecially ſeeing the condition he requires of them, derogates nothing from his Grace, being his own gift, having ſuch an aptitude in it ſelf, for that to which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:30489:25"/>
it is appointed, and not contributing the leaſt mite to the ſatisfaction for our ſin, and when the deferring of our happineſs, and the afflictions we ſuffer in the mean time, are both for our advantage, and work together for our good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. For the Queſtion about the intereſt of Faith in our juſtification, whether it juſtifie as an <hi>inſtrument,</hi> or as a <hi>condition,</hi> I think it deſerves not half the words that have been uſed about it, they are both of them School-termes, and not found in the Scripture, and ſhould not therefore diſturb the peace of the Church, eſpecially ſeeing both parties at variance are agreed in the thing, but not in the formal notion, under which they do conceive of it; and I think both ſides are ſo far agreed, that Faith may be called an <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> allowing much impropriety of ſpeech, and that it may be called a <hi>condition,</hi> while we thereby do not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:30489:25"/>
ſuppoſe any ſuch thing as merit. As guilt doth immediately reſult from the act of ſin, by vertue of the threatning, ſo doth righteouſneſs from faith by vertue of the promiſe, as the Law is the ſtrength of ſin, whereby it bindes over the ſinner to puniſhment, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.56. So the Goſpel is the ſtrength of faith, by vertue of which the ſinner is acquitted. Yet I would not be underſtood, as if I aſcribed the ſame cauſality to faith in juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to ſin in condemnation. And where Faith is ſaid to be counted or imputed for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, we need not thereby underſtand that we are juſtified for our faith, or that it is the matter of our juſtification, but our faith is reckoned or imputed to us, that is, God doth reckon us believers, and deal with us as ſuch, that is, juſtifie us according to his own gracious appointment in the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:30489:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>For ſo that is ſaid to be imputed to us, which is really inherent in us, as ſin is ſaid to be imputed to a perſon when he is reckoned or accounted a ſinner, and dealt with as a ſinner, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.19. But now our juſtification is but in order to our ſanctification, for hereby we live to God, and converſe with him. This is our formal happineſs, I mean Sanctification taken paſſively, and <hi>in actu ſecundo,</hi> and according to the degree thereof is the degree of our happineſs. When we ſhall know God perfectly, we ſhall love him perfectly, and then our joy and happineſs ſhall be perfected, And if we could ſuppoſe a man to be juſtified and not ſanctified, it would be, but as if a man ſhould have his debt paid, and be left in priſon. Its true, ſuch an one might be exempted from the puniſhment of ſenſe, and ſo, in as good a condition as a beaſt; but it would
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:30489:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
not exempt him from the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of loſſe. Juſtification qualifies us for heaven <hi>morally,</hi> but Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation <hi>naturally.</hi> A fool may have a right to an eſtate, if he be lawfully begotten, but he cannot enjoy it without the uſe of reaſon: So if we ſhould be ſuppoſed to have a right to happineſs by juſtification, we could not enjoy it without ſanctification. Therefore they ſpeak ignorantly, who ſo much cry up Juſtification, and ſpeak ſo ſlightly of Sanctification. Chriſt bleſſeth us in turning us away from our iniquities, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.26. Now the Author hereof is the Holy Ghoſt, who is the quickening Spirit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.63. the ſpirit of life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. in him, we live and move ſpiritually. As he divides his gifts to every one as he pleaſeth, ſo likewiſe his graces: they are his fruits, <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.22. the conſtant being of our Graces de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon his perpetual in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:30489:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
dwelling, <hi>John</hi> 14.16. the livelineſs thereof, and our comfort, on his arbitrary influence, which he gives out, or withholds at his pleaſure, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.11. This is as the dew, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.5. which deſcends inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly, <hi>John</hi> 14.17. the dew ſweetly refreſhes, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.12. ſo doth the Spirit, <hi>John</hi> 14.16. the dew makes fruitfull, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.39. ſo the Spirit makes us grow as the Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies for fruitfulneſs, fragrancy, beauty: like the Cedars for duration, and firm rooting; which —<hi>quantum vertico ad auras aetherias, tantum radice ad tartara tendunt: vide Rivet in locum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now it is by Faith that we receive the Spirit, <hi>John</hi> 7.38, 39. it is by the Spirit indeed that we are inabled to believe, Fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h being reckoned among the fruits of it, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. but then we receive greater meaſures of the ſpirit by faith. Put water into a pump, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:30489:27"/>
you may bring up more, while there is any in the well: So let the Spirit be put within us, whereby we may believe, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27. and Faith will continually draw further degrees from the fountain: It is as the attractive power, or magnetical vertue in plants, whereby they ſuck juice and moiſture from the root, which makes them thrive and proſper. And for the more full clearing hereof, I will ſhew you how Faith doth improve all thoſe Ordinances, which are the breaſts of conſolation, from whence the chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dren of God do ſuck, and are ſatisfied with the bleſſings of the Goſpel, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.11. <hi>Thoſe that are planted in the houſe of the Lord, ſhall flouriſh in the courts of our God,</hi> Pſal. 92.13. It is in the Church that the Ordinances of God are diſpenſed. Neither yet do all flouriſh that are there, but ſuch as are planted there. You may ſee
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:30489:28"/>
many dead ſticks and boughs in a Garden, which are only for the ſupport and defence of ſome choice plants or flowers: ſo there are many amongſt believers that make the ſame common profeſſion with them, which are but for their defence and ſecurity. If there were none that profeſſed Religion, but ſuch as are found and ſincere believers, how ſoon would they become a prey to Adverſaries. But they are thoſe that are planted or ingrafted, that bear fruit, <hi>John</hi> 15.4. Now there are three Ordinances whereby a Chriſtians ſpiritual life is maintained, and which do all become effectual thereto by faith, and theſe are <hi>Prayer, hearing the Word, and the Lords Supper.</hi> Indeed though Baptiſme is ordinarily ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, when perſons are not capable of exerciſing Faith, yet there is ſome uſe to be made of it: But I ſhall not treat
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:30489:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
diſtinctly of it here, but leave the Reader to infer by propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from what is ſaid of the Lords Supper, how it is to be improved, there being much ſaid about it, in a few words, in the larger <hi>Catechiſme</hi> of the late <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> and there being a Treatiſe written of it by Maſter <hi>Simon Ford.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:30489:29"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> The uſe of Prayer, though we pray by the Spirit, yet we are to pray for the Spirit, <hi>Mat. 7.11.</hi> and <hi>Luk. 11.13.</hi> compared; an unbeleever cannot pray acceptably, nor in the name of Chriſt, yet is not therefore diſcharged of his duty; by faith we pray with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, boldneſs, importunity, <hi>Mat. 15.22, &amp;c.</hi> explained; by Faith we wait for a return of Prayer; helps to Faith in Prayer, <hi>Pſa. 9.10. 2 Pet. 1.4. Iſa. 30.18.</hi> illuſtrated<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what Faith is required in Prayer, or what it is to pray in Faith, <hi>Jam. 1.6, &amp;c.</hi> opened; the ends of Prayer.</head>
               <p>PRayer is as the Merchants Ship, it fetches in all a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſtore, even temporal bleſſings, if they be really bleſſings, are brought in by Prayer; indeed,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:30489:29"/>
ſometimes men have them without asking, but they had better aske them without having: for it is by Prayer that they are ſanctified to us, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. And we are to pray, not that we may incline God to give, but becauſe he is enclined and hath promiſed to give, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.27. And though we pray by the Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15, 27. yet we muſt pray alſo for the Spirit, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.13. He is given to us as a Spirit of Supplication, and thereby we obtain him to work effectually in us to all thoſe ends and purpoſes for which Chriſt ſent him into the World, to be <hi>Vicari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Domini,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> calls him, <hi>De velandis virgin,</hi> Cap. 1. To ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply his abſence while he is gone to appear in heaven for us. The words of Chriſt are variouſly related, by <hi>Luke</hi> and <hi>Matthew. Luke</hi> relates them, <hi>How much more ſhall your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father give the holy Spirit to them that aske him.</hi> Matthew, <hi>How
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:30489:30"/>
much more ſhall your Father which is in heaven give good things to them that aske him,</hi> Mat. 7.11. Of the Evangeliſts citing the words of our Saviour, we may make the ſame judgment which was made, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. of the Apoſtles citing the words of the Prophets. If the words of Chriſt were as they are related by <hi>Matthew,</hi> then <hi>Luke</hi> makes a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular inference from a general, or at leaſt from an indefinite promiſe. If God will give good things to thoſe that ask him, ſurely he will give his Spirit, elſe we may ſay as <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 15.2. <hi>Lord God what wilt thou give me?</hi> Nothing can be good to us without the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; if thoſe which <hi>Luke</hi> ſets down were Chriſts words, then <hi>Matthew</hi> doth make the Spirit to be all good things in effect; the promiſe of the Spirit being the great Promiſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, as the Promiſe of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> was under the Law:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:30489:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and the Spirit being all in all, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>Application,</hi> as Chriſt is all in all, in reſpect of <hi>impetration, Col.</hi> 3.11. Or elſe he doth from the promiſe of the Spirit infer, That God would give all good things, as Chriſt argues, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33. and the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. He that gives the greater will not deny the leſs.</p>
               <p>Now, we can do nothing in Prayer without Faith, which muſt qualifie us for it both habitually and actually.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Habitually,</hi> for <hi>without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God. Heb.</hi> 11.6. It muſt be the effectual fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent prayer of a <hi>righteous</hi> man that availes, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.16. for ſuch a man only can pray in the name of Chriſt; If a man ſhould come to deſire a favour of you in the name or for the ſake of ſuch a friend whom you much reſpect, and whoſe name will prevail much with you, would you
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:30489:31"/>
not aske him preſently, What re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation he hath to ſuch a man that he uſeth his name? So many come to God in the name of Jeſus Chriſt, And God may ſay to them, and Why in the name of Chriſt? What are you to Chriſt? Or, What rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion have you to him? Or, ſuppoſe, in the former caſe, your friend, whoſe name another makes uſe of, ſhould be near you at ſuch a time, and you go to him, and aske him if he know that man that makes uſe of his name, and he ſhould tell you, he is one that he hath nothing to do with, one that hath done him much injury, and from whom he never received the leaſt reſpect or civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; What anſwer might ſuch a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner expect? So let us ſuppoſe our ſelves to hear God asking Jeſus Chriſt, when an Unbeleever comes to pray in his name, if he belong to him, or have any thing to do with him: and Chriſt anſwering, That
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:30489:31"/>
he hath nothing to do with him, and is one that deſpiſes his authority, and contemns his grace, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proacheth his name, and makes light of him; What can we think it would availe ſuch an one to pray in the name of Chriſt? Yet an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleevers incapacity of praying ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptably doth not give him a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge from his duty, for if wicked men were bound to do nothing but what they can do as they ought, they ſhould have no ſins of omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but however I ſhould in <hi>Theſi</hi> ſay it is the duty of an Unbeliever to pray, yet in <hi>hypotheſi</hi> if ſuch an one ſhould come to aske mine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, I would deal with him as with one who hath an erring conſcience, I would not adviſe him to do any thing againſt his conſcience, or to do his duty perſiſting in his errour, but rather to lay aſide his errour, by rightly informing his conſcience, that ſo he might do that which is
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:30489:32"/>
lawful in a lawful manner.</p>
               <p>So I would not adviſe ſuch an one to pray, perſiſting in his unbelief; but to believe, that ſo he might pray acceptably. It is true, God doth ſomtimes out of the exupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his bounty hear wicked men, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.29. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.4. But though he beſtows com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon favours on good and bad, yet it is upon the righteous (who are ſo by Faith) that he beſtows them with a ſpecial love, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.8.</p>
               <p>But Secondly, Faith qualifieth us <hi>actually</hi> for prayer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As it diſpoſeth us to an holy awe and reverence of God. He that will ſerve God <hi>acceptably,</hi> muſt ſerve him with <hi>reverence and godly fear. Heb.</hi> 12.28. God diſdains ſuch ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as men would be aſhamed to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to their Prince, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.8. And it is more tolerable to erre by ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition in the Worſhip of God, than on the other hand, by rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:30489:32"/>
and prophaneneſs. Now Faith ſets the ſoul as under the eye of God, ſees <hi>him</hi> (who to ſenſe) <hi>is inviſible,</hi> Heb. 11.27. It being <hi>the evidence of things not ſeen.</hi> So that by Faith the ſoul doth as really ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend God preſent, as if he were incarnat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, or had aſſumed an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſhape; and there is nothing more effectual to beget in the ſoul a due reverence of God, ſince the preſence of Angels in our Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies requires ſuch a <hi>decorum</hi> in the exerciſes which we there perform, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.10.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By Faith we come <hi>boldly</hi> to God in prayer, though Faith pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent rudeneſs, yet it comes with an holy boldneſs, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.12. it is by Faith, as the Apoſtle there ſhews, that we have acceſs with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, there uſed, ſignifies freedom of ſpeech, when a man ſpeaks his whole mind freely, when a man can come
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:30489:33"/>
boldly to God and challenge his Promiſe, urge upon him, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaies of his Mother <hi>Monica,</hi> his own hand-writing, as <hi>David</hi> doth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.49. <hi>Remember thy word unto thy ſervant, upon which thou haſt cauſed me to hope;</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.1. he challenges God in his faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and righteouſneſs to anſwer him, though he dare not deal with God upon terms of ſtrict juſtice, as he ſhews, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. yet he pleads that iuſtice which is founded upon his mercy, and his promiſe made thereby.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Faith encourages the ſoul to perſeverance and importunity in Prayer; there is an holy impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to be uſed in Prayer, ſo the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, uſed <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.8. doth properly import; a clear inſtance of this we have in that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.22. She comes to Chriſt, and propounds her caſe to him, and at firſt he gives her no
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:30489:33"/>
anſwer. Sometimes a Beleever may pray and have no audience, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 22.2. yet Chriſts ſilence would not make her ſilent, but ſhe cries after him, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. It ſeems the Diſciples were weary of her im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, and <hi>Auſtin,</hi> by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this place with <hi>Mar.</hi> 7.24. ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, that ſhe followed Chriſt from one place to another, though he endeavoured to avoid her; then Chriſt doth in effect give her a flat denial, ſignifying to her, that ſhe was none of thoſe to whom he was ſent, for the time of the full cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Gentiles was nor yet come. So God doth ſometimes deny the prayers of his People, as he tels them plainly, <hi>Judg.</hi> 10.13. <hi>He would deliver them no more;</hi> yet neither delaies nor denial would beat her off, but ſhe ſtill continues her ſuit; then Chriſt gives her a very rough anſwer: doth in effect call her a dog, <hi>ver.</hi> 26. Sometimes God ſeems
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:30489:34"/>
to be <hi>angry even againſt the prayer of his People, Pſal.</hi> 80.4. The more they pray, the more their affliction en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth, and things ſeem to grow worſe and worſe with them; but yet ſhe is not diſcouraged hereby, but retorts Chriſts words upon himſelf, arguing from thence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, If ſhe were a dog, yet there was ſomething due to her as a dog: the dogs eating of the crumbs which fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from their Maſters table<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as <hi>David</hi> ſeems to retort ſuch an argument upon God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.11. making that which might ſeem to make his ſin leſs capable of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, an argument to prevail with God for the pardon of them; the greater they were the more need he had of pardon, and the more glory God would have in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of them; this is an excellent point of skill in prayer, yea, not only in wreſtling with God, but in wreſtling with <hi>Satan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:30489:34"/>Now obſerve Chriſts anſwer to this woman, <hi>O woman great is thy faith, be it unto thee even as thou wilt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is firſt, Chriſts teſtimony concerning her, her faith was great, he imputes her importunity and perſeverance to her faith.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Here is Chriſts grant to her, even what ſhe would; by which Chriſt ſhews how pleaſing ſuch importunity is to him, and what a grateful violence, as <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> calls it, <hi>Apol.</hi> c. 39. is thereby offered to him. The ſame impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity we may obſerve in <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 32.24. and in <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 32.10. and the like ſucceſs thereof in them both.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Faith waits for the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of Prayer, as <hi>David</hi> when he had directed his Prayer to God, looked up, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.3. as one that having put in a Petition, waits to ſee what anſwer he ſhall have, or
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:30489:35"/>
what becomes of it. A ſurly beggar loſes many Almes becauſe be will not wait; like that wicked King, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.33. This was the frequent ſin of the Jews, who, impatient of delayes, were wont to betake themſelves to forraign aid, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.1, &amp;c. 31.1, &amp;c. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.1. though God had told them, that <hi>in quietneſs and confidence ſhould be their ſtrength,</hi> Iſa. 30.15. quiet and confident dependance upon God ſhould be their beſt ſecurity: And when <hi>young men</hi> (that are ſtrongeſt, and moſt confident in their ſtrength) <hi>ſhall utterly fall, they that wait on the Lord ſhall renew their ſtrength, they ſhall mount up with wings as Eagles, they ſhall run and not be weary, they ſhall walk and not faint,</hi> Iſa. 40.30, 31. they ſhall hold out to the laſt, and overcome all difficulties, as if they had wings to fly over them. God is ſo well pleaſed with thoſe that wait on him, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 147.11.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:30489:35"/>
that he will not fail them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.3. We may ſay of God, as <hi>Seneca</hi> of a friend, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 3. <hi>Fidelem ſi putaveris, facies;</hi> the Proverb is true here, <hi>He that truſts much, obliges much,</hi> ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.40. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.3. Now that this is the fruit of Faith, is evident from the whole current of that place, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.2, 3, 4. <hi>He that believes makes not haſte,</hi> he doth not through the diſtruſt of Gods Promiſe, (though the performance of it be deferred) betake himſelf to the uſe of any unlawfull means for his own help, (which was before obſerved to be the common ſin of the Jews) <hi>Eſai.</hi> 28.16. but waits for the God of his Salvation, becauſe he knowes his God will hear him, <hi>Micah</hi> 7.7.</p>
               <p>Now becauſe the work of Faith lies much in trading to heaven in Prayer, I ſhall here add ſome helps to faith therein.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Let us look to the command
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:30489:36"/>
of God. It is not in vain that he hath ſaid, Seek ye my face, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.19. When Chriſt called the blinde man, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.49. they bad him be of good comfort, ſuppoſing he intended ſome good towards him, elſe he would not have called him. Commands may ſometimes be of greater uſe than Promiſes, and more effectual for ſilencing doubts and diſcouragements; ſome I believe have found them ſo. We may diſpute our intereſt in a Promiſe, or plead (in a miſtaken humility) our own unworthineſs againſt what we look upon only as a priviledg; but Commands are not to be diſputed, but obeyed. And if we ſhould fear Gods being angry with our Prayers, and that he ſhould ſay as <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7.10. <hi>Wherefore lieſt thou thus upon thy face?</hi> we might take the boldneſs to anſwer, as <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 27.8. <hi>Thou haſt ſaid, Seek ye my face, therefore thy face Lord will I
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:30489:36"/>
ſeek:</hi> And beſides the general com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Prayer, Chriſt hath let words fall from him to invite our importunity, intimating his readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to yield thereto, and how well pleaſed he is therewith, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.8. <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Let us acquaint our ſelves more with the nature of God, &amp; this will be a great encouragement to Faith as one obſerves well, (<hi>Arrowſmith Chain of Principles, p.</hi> 39.) Faith may lay hold on an Attribute when it cannot cloſe with a Promiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.10. <hi>They that know thy name will put their truſt in thee. Name</hi> here may have reference to <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> thoſe Attributes there mentioned being an encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to confidence; or it may have reference to <hi>Exod.</hi> 6.3. the name <hi>Jehovah</hi> importing the conſtancy and faithfulneſs of God in fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his Promiſes, ſee <hi>Rivet</hi> on the place. But moſt probably it is
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:30489:37"/>
redundant here; and the words intend no more, but, they that know <hi>thee</hi> will put their truſt in thee.</p>
               <p>Inſtances of the like redundance we have in thoſe expreſſions, <hi>The Name of the God of Jacob defend thee, Pſal.</hi> 20.1. <hi>To ſeek Gods Name, Pſal.</hi> 83.16. <hi>To love his Name, Iſa.</hi> 56.6. <hi>To fear his Name, Iſa.</hi> 59.19. to praiſe his name, call upon his name, ſwear by his name, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the ſence of the place will be the ſame: Thoſe that know God, that is, how faithful, how good, how wiſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he is, will put their truſt in him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.18. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſhews the bleſſedneſs of thoſe that wait for God, becauſe</p>
               <p>Firſt, God is a good God; while the ſinner waits for mercy, God waits that he may be gracious, <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius videtur Deo veniam peccatori dediſſe quam illi accepiſſe, Bern. de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior. dom. c.</hi> 37. the time ſeems longer to him than it doth to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:30489:37"/>Secondly, He is a God of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, one that doth all things with wiſdome, and moderation, and ſo will take the fitteſt ſeaſon when he may ſhew mercy to our greateſt advantage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Martha</hi> thought it fell out very unhappily that Chriſt was not with her at her bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hers death, <hi>Jo.</hi> 11.21 but Chriſt was glad that he was not there, for he intended a farther mercy than the life of <hi>Lazarus, viz.</hi> the confirming the faith of others by the miracle which he had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to work, <hi>ver.</hi> 15. We are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ready for mercy, but God in his wiſdom ſeeth meet many times to defer it, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.6.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Let us ſtudy the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that ſo we may have them in readineſs to urge upon God as the matter ſhall require in particular caſes, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. the Promiſes are exceeding great and precious; they are great in reſpect of the things
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:30489:38"/>
promiſed, and exceeding precious in themſelves, it being a great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to have a promiſe from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; Many that intend us good, will not come under the bonds of a promiſe, they love not to be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, but would have us ſtand to their courteſie: But God hath not been ſo reſerved, but hath made himſelf a debter by his promiſe, if not to us, yet to his own truth and faithfulneſs; that requiring that what he had promiſed ſhould be fulfilled: So that we know what we have to truſt to; times and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons indeed for their accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he hath kept in his own pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but the things themſelves he hath, as it were, put out of his power, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.7. They are precious in reſpect of their ſutableneſs to every condition or degree of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers; There is no duty a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian can be called to, no temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or affliction which he can be
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:30489:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
exerciſed with, but he may find a Promiſe ſuited to it; Yea, no Chriſtian, of the loweſt ſtature, but may find Promiſes within his reach, though ſome may be above him; a man on the ground cannot reach the top of a tree, but he may get hold of the lower boughs, and ſo riſe by degrees till he come to the top. It may be thou canſt not reach ſuch Promiſes as <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.26. or <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.21. but thou mayeſt reach ſuch as thoſe <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.3, 4, 6. Yea, let me adde farther, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith of Books <hi>de Trinit. l.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. It is expedient that divers men write of the ſame thing in different ſtyles, that ſo what they cannot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand in one they may appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend in another, that ſo the truth may come to all: to one after this manner, to another after that (the common Apology for multiplying Books on the ſame ſubject) ſo I may ſay of the Promiſes; God hath
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:30489:39"/>
promiſed the ſame things under ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral notions, and expreſſed them by ſeveral <hi>ſimilitudes,</hi> whereby he conveys them to the ſoul (as cordial powders are conveyed in ſome wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the ſtomach) and when a ſoul cannot receive comfort by one Promiſe, it doth by another, though they are Promiſes of the ſame thing, but under different notions and expreſſions, or to the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whoſe condition is expreſſed by ſeveral Metaphors. Some may perhaps receive comfort from <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.6. which dare not apply <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.19. though it would be eaſie to ſhew, that whoever hungers and thirſts after righteouſneſs hath a broken and contrite heart. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. is as full a Promiſe as <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.37. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as full as either of them: Yet it may be ſome ſouls may take more comfort from <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.37. becauſe that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that Chriſt will in no wiſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:30489:39"/>
caſt out ſuch as come to him, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers directly to their ſcruple, and juſt meets with that doubt which runs moſt in their minds, (that Chriſt would ſurely reject them if they ſhould come) as if God had intended that Promiſe purpoſely for them.</p>
               <p>But further, theſe Promiſes are precious in reſpect of their firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and certainty, which God hath given us aſſurance of by all thoſe waies which are in uſe among men for the confirmation of any Grant, Covenant, Promiſe; being as a Teſtament confirmed by the death of the Teſtator, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.17. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. A Covenant ſealed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. A Promiſe confirmed by an Oath, which is the utmoſt aſſurance that any man can give or require, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This God doth not that his counſel may be immutable, but that he may <hi>declare</hi> it to be ſo to us, by that which is the moſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:30489:40"/>
ſolemn way of confirmation amongſt men. <hi>O beatos nos quorum causâ Deus jurat. O miſerrimos ſi nec juranti Domino credimus, Tert. de Poenit. cap.</hi> 4. How happy are we that God ſhould ſwear for our ſakes! And what wretches are we if we believe him not upon his oath.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Let us labour to clear our own intereſt in the Promiſe, that we may with the more bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs put in our claim, crying, <hi>Abba Father, Rom.</hi> 8.15. coming with as much confidence to God as a child to a Father, though we may pray indeed without <hi>aſſurance</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: if we come not to God as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he is our Father, we may come to him that he may be our Father. The Promiſe indeed is not univerſal, but the call or invitation is univerſal, and the Promiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes abſolute upon our accepting of Gods invitation, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:30489:40"/>
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. If any ſhall ſay, the invitation is not to all, but only to ſuch as are <hi>thirſty</hi> and <hi>weary.</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, theſe are no limitations of Gods grace, but it would be in vain to invite any others; and thoſe are not <hi>moral</hi> qualifications to make Chriſt willing to accept of us, but <hi>natural</hi> qualifications to make us willing to accept of him. But that you may ſee what Faith it is which is required in Prayer, I will make a ſhort <hi>Digreſſion</hi> to conſider more diſtinctly what it is to pray in Faith: and this may be taken ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther improperly, or properly; we may be ſaid to pray in faith more improperly,</p>
               <p>Firſt, When we pray with this confidence, that our Prayer is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the will of God, (<hi>viz.</hi> that it is according to the will of God that we ſhould ſo pray, though not that our Prayer ſhould be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted;) it may be our duty to pray
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:30489:41"/>
for that which it is not the pleaſure of God to beſtow, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. it is evident by the Context, that the Apoſtle ſpeaks of what a man doth without a perſwaſion of the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of it; for the Will of God muſt be both the <hi>Rule</hi> of our duty, and the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of our obedience; ſo that whatſoever we do without this perſwaſion, though it may be <hi>materially</hi> good, it is <hi>formally</hi> evill, becauſe it is not in obedience to Gods Will.</p>
               <p>Secondly, When we pray in truth and ſincerity, ſo Faith is taken, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.3. and <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.6. the Apoſtle ſeems to ſpeak of ſuch a Faith as doth effectually determine the Will to the free choice and conſtant proſecution of that which is good; and that you may not think this a ſingular notion, ſee the ſence of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral very judicious and godly men, Dr. <hi>Jackson</hi> of <hi>Faith, pag.</hi> 108. Dr. <hi>Preſton on the Attributes of God,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:30489:41"/>
pag.</hi> 11, 12. Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. <hi>p.</hi> 317. Mr. <hi>Capel of Tentations, part.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 46. The double-minded man ſaith, he is not he who is in the right vvay, and labours under ſome doubting, but he that hangs betvvixt tvvo vvaies and knovvs not which to chuſe, whether God or <hi>Baal.</hi>] There are many which pray from their memories, uttering ſuch expreſſions as they have heard or read, or from their fancies and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions (for therein Mr <hi>Saltmarſh</hi> is right, that all extemporary prayers are not from the Spirit, as ſome miſtake.) Others go further, and pray from conſcience, for ſuch things as they are convinced they ought to pray for, yet theſe pray not ſincerely from the heart and affections, and ſo they do not as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.4. <hi>Seek</hi> after that which they deſire of the Lord; they pray, but are afraid to be heard, loath that God ſhould take
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:30489:42"/>
them at their word, or ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to their prayers. This was <hi>Auſtine</hi> caſe <hi>Confeſſ. L.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. he prayed, <hi>Da mihi caſtitatem &amp; continentiam, ſed noli modo. Timebam enim ne me cito exaudines.</hi> Lord, give me cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity and continency, but not yet. I was afraid (ſaith he) leſt thou ſhouldſt hear me preſently, and cure that diſeaſe of luſt which I had rather ſhould be fulfilled than mortified. So doubtleſs there are many which pray for that humility which would ſpoil their pride and gallantry; for that fear of God, ſelf-denial, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly-mindedneſs, which would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt their ſenſual pleaſures, or hinder their thriving in the world by unlawful means: and it is to be feared, would be loath to part with thoſe ſins which an anſwer of ſuch prayers would force them to part with. How many pray, that <hi>Gods name may be hallowed,</hi> and are moſt ready to blaſpheme his name? That
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:30489:42"/>
his <hi>Kingdom may come,</hi> and oppoſe his Kingdom? That his <hi>will may be done,</hi> that will neither do it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, nor ſuffer thoſe to live qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly that deſire to do it? That <hi>God would not lead them into temptation,</hi> and yet daily run upon temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and would account it a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be kept from them? Thus do men compaſs God about with lies and deceit, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.12. pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to pray for thoſe things which they hate or fear.</p>
               <p>But more properly we may be ſaid to pray in faith, when we pray,</p>
               <p>Firſt, With a more general per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion either of the power of God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.28, 29. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. I am perſwaded he is <hi>able</hi> to keep that which I have committed to him, or of his faithfulneſs, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.11. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13. <hi>If we believe not, he is faithful, he cannot deny himſelf;</hi> which words we are not
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:30489:43"/>
to underſtand, as if God notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the unbelief of men would perform to them his mercy promiſed, or as if unbelief could not deprive us of it; but whether we believe or no that ſhall not make the faith of God of none effect, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.3. Gods Promiſe ſhall be made good (according to the true tenour and import of it) to thoſe that by faith lay hold thereon, though we ſhould by our unbelief exclude our ſelves from the benefit of it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, When we pray with a particular perſwaſion that we ſhall receive the mercies which we pray for.</p>
               <p>Now, the chief queſtion is about this, How far we may pray with ſuch a faith?</p>
               <p>And for anſwer hereof we muſt conſider, that our prayers are either for ſpiritual mercies or for tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. Again, ſpiritual mercies are
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:30489:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
either ſuch as are neceſſary to the being of grace, or for the well-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it; that which is neceſſary to the being of Chriſtianity is aſſiſting and perſevering Grace, and of the receiving of this our aſſurance is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the aſſurance which we have of our own ſincerity. For that of God to the Apoſtle, <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee,</hi> is equivalent to a Promiſe, and is as applicable to every Believer as thoſe words of God to <hi>Joſhua,</hi> which the Apoſtle applies to all, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. and that the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. doth not ſpeak of the ſufficiency of grace, as diſtinguiſhed from the efficacy of it, ſee <hi>Rhetorforti exercitat.</hi> 428. and that <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. is true as well of ſpirituals as of temporals, that being the chief end why we ſhould deſire of God not to fail us nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake us, that he may encline our hearts to walk in all his waies, and keep his Commandments,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:30489:44"/>
1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.57, 58. but for ſuch grace as is neceſſary only to keep us from particular infirmities, or for our comfort, or for the livelineſs of our graces; this is not promiſed ſo abſolutely, but after the manner of temporal mercies, for which we cannot ordinarily pray, with a particular aſſurance of being heard; all the Faith we can exerciſe in ſuch caſes, is only on the power, faithfulneſs, and goodneſs of God in generall, and that he will not <hi>deſpiſe</hi> our Prayers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.17. but accept them graciouſly, and anſwer them in ſuch kinde, manner, time, and meaſure, as ſeems good to his grace and wiſdome; and accordingly are all ſuch Promiſes to be underſtood. Indeed ſomtimes God doth make an extraordinary impreſſion of confidence upon the hearts of his people in their prayers for temporal mercies, as in <hi>Luther,</hi> when he prayed for his friend
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:30489:44"/>
                  <hi>Myconius:</hi> and <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt for Sr. <hi>John Cheek, Fullers</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtory, <hi>Lib.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> We are commanded to believe, that we ſhall receive whatſoever things we deſire when we pray, <hi>Mark</hi> 11.24. and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we ask in prayer, believing, we ſhall receive, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.22.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. It is evident in both theſe places, by the context, that our Saviour ſpeaks of that Faith of miracles, which was in the primitive Church, and peculiar to thoſe times.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If this were univerſally true, many would never die, nor ever want any thing: for though they ſhould not, poſſibly, pray thus for themſelves, yet others might pray thus for them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They had not an abſolute power of receiving whatſoever they asked in prayer, but this Faith was from an extraordinary impreſs upon the ſoul, which had not any particular
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:30489:45"/>
Promiſe for its foundation, but only the power of God, &amp; an immediate perſwaſion of his willingneſs, God preparing the heart to ſeek, where he had an intent to lend his ear to hear, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.17. Indeed, as one boaſted that he could make an engine which would remove the whole earth, if he had ſome place elſe to fix his engine upon: ſo Faith would remove the world, if it had a promiſe to ſtand firm upon. If it be ſaid, we ſhould pray for nothing but what we have a promiſe for, I deny it. There are (as Mr. <hi>Hooker, Eccleſ. pol. l.</hi> 5. <hi>Sect.</hi> 48. hath rightly obſerved) two uſes of Prayer, It ſerves as a means to procure thoſe things which God hath promiſed to grant when we ask: and as a mean alſo to expreſs our lawfull deſires towards that which whether we ſhall have or no we know not, till we ſee the event. Yea, I may add further, we may
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:30489:45"/>
therein repreſent our deſires (with a ſubmiſſion to the will of God) of thoſe things which we know we ſhall not have: It was plainly our Saviours caſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.39. though he knew it was not poſſible that the cup ſhould paſſe from him, and that he was come to that hour, for this end; that he might drink it, <hi>John</hi> 12.27.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:30489:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The Gospel the Word of Life. Of Hearing and Reading the Word. The Word is effectuall by Faith. How variouſly Faith acts upon the ſeveral parts of the Word. Upon the Hiſtory and Doctrine thereof. <hi>Hebr. 11.3.</hi> illustrated. Upon the Commands. The <hi>Socinians</hi> notion of Faith cenſured. <hi>1 Theſ. 2.13.</hi> explained. The Acts of Faith on the Promiſes. <hi>Rom. 4.17,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>2 Pet. 1.4.</hi> opened. How the Promiſes to Grace, and the Promiſes <hi>of</hi> Grace conduce to Sanctification. How Faith acts on the Threatnings. <hi>Heb. 11.7.</hi> cleared. The Uſe of Threatnings to Believers. <hi>Rom. 8.13.</hi> interpreted. How the Word is a means of Faith though it be made effectuall by Faith.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:30489:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>THe next means of Spiritual Life is, Hearing the Word of God. This is called <hi>the Word of Life,</hi> Acts 5.20. Phil. 2.15. and Life is promiſed to the Hearing of the Word, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3. <hi>John</hi> 5.25. it is clear he ſpeaks thereof ſpiritual Life, becauſe he ſaith the time is already come; and in the <hi>verſe</hi> before he had been ſpeaking of Everlaſting Life, which is begun in Regeneration. This Word is both the ſeed whereby we are begotten again, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. and the food whereby we are nouriſhed when we are borne, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.2. the end of the Miniſtry being to perfect the <hi>number</hi> of the Saints by converſion, and their <hi>graces by</hi> Edification, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12. I will not examine, whether this word be the inſtrument of the Spirit, or whether they have their different wayes of working, the one <hi>morally,</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:30489:47"/>
by perſwaſion, the other, <hi>phyſically,</hi> by real influence: but this is ſure, there is a Spirit of life accompanies the diſpenſation of the Word, which quickens dead ſoules, as a ſpirit of life entered into the Prophet, and ſet him upon his feet, when God ſpake to him, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 2.2. and as there went a divine power along with the word of Chriſt, when he bade <hi>Lazarus</hi> come out of his grave, which raiſed him out of it: So while <hi>Paul</hi> preached, the heart of <hi>Lydia</hi> was opened, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14. And for this cauſe the miniſtration of the Goſpel is called the miniſtration of the ſpirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.8. Not that the ſpirit doth accompany the Word allwayes, ſo as to make it effectual: it did not ſo when Chriſt himſelf preached, <hi>John</hi> 12.37. nor when <hi>Paul</hi> preached (whom <hi>Auſtine</hi> deſired ſo much to hear) then ſome believ'd, and ſome believed not, <hi>Act.</hi> 28.24,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:30489:47"/>
but it works in ſubordination to Gods Election, bringing home all ſuch as are ordained to eternal life, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.48.</p>
               <p>Now by Hearing the Word, I mean with Dr. <hi>Ames, Quaelibet praeceptio ſermonum Dei, ſive praedicatione, ſive electione, ſive alia quaecunque ratione communicentur:</hi> receiving the Word by preaching, or reading, or any other way. Such words of <hi>ſenſe</hi> ſignifying any way of perceiving a thing, wherefore ſeeing is applyed to ſounds, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.18. <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.12. The Word of God was wont to be read formerly both publiquely and privately. Of the publike reading of it we may ſee <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8.3. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.27. <hi>chap.</hi> 15.21. they read part of it in the Synagogue every Sabbath day: and that they read it privately, is plain from our Saviour's appealing ſo oft to their own reading, <hi>Have you never read,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.3, 5. <hi>chap.</hi> 19.4.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:30489:48"/>
21.16.22.31. and from their ſearching the Scriptures, <hi>John</hi> 5.39. whether we underſtand that <hi>indicatively,</hi> affirming what they did, or <hi>imparatively,</hi> commanding what they ſhould do; they were thereby inabled to judge the better of what they heard, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.11. but this was not enough, but they muſt have an Interpreter, that they might underſtand what they read, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.30. They not only read diſtinctly in the Law, but <hi>gave the ſenſe, and cauſed the people to underſtand it,</hi> Nehem. 8.7, 8. yea, they applyed it by exhortation, <hi>&amp;c. Acts</hi> 13.15. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18. And if it be ſaid, However this is neceſſary, that the Scripture ſhould be explained and applyed, yet Preaching is not now neceſſary, becauſe we have expoſitions, and Sermons, now to read in greater plenty than formerly, when there were no books but ſuch as men wrote out: I
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:30489:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
anſwer, Would to God men would read them more, and that they would but ſpend their ſpare hours therein, which they ſpend idly, or ſinfully: but let not this make us leſs eſteem the hearing of the word preached: for though reading may conduce more to the information of the judgment, yet Preaching with a lively voice doth more excite the affections; and further, the ſucceſſe of the Goſpel, is according as the Lord gives to every man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. and experience hath told us, with what ſucceſſe God hath bleſſed the preaching of the Goſpel. See the Letter of Archb. <hi>Grindall</hi> to Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in <hi>Fullers</hi> Hiſtory, <hi>B.</hi> 9: <hi>p.</hi> 124, 125. Though I had rather men ſhould be inſtructed by the <hi>Homilies,</hi> which were formerly read in the Church, than by many mens Sermons: And I believe God hath bleſſed them to the good of ſoules, where there hath
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:30489:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
been want of able and godly Preachers, yet God forbid, that theſe ſhould ever thruſt out Preaching, where ſuch Preachers are not wanting. He that deſires to be more fully ſatisfied concerning theſe things, may peruſe Maſter <hi>Hooker</hi>'s <hi>Eccl. Polit.</hi> l. 5. S. 21, 22. and Mr. <hi>Hieron</hi>'s <hi>Preachers Plea,</hi> where theſe things are ſolidly and ſoberly debated.</p>
               <p>I come now to ſhew how it is by Faith that the Word becomes effectual to our ſpiritual life. The Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.2. tells us, that the Word preached did not profit the Iſraelites, becauſe it was not mixed with Faith in them that heard it. As to make the ſeed fruitfull in the earth, there is required ſome moiſture whereby it may be as it were incorporated with the earth, and receive of the vertue and fatneſs of it: for it will not grow, if it lie under a dry and hard clod:
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:30489:49"/>
ſo Faith is neceſſary for ingrafting the Word into the ſoul; wherefore it is the power of God to the Salvation of every one which believeth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. And for the clear proof hereof I ſhall ſhew you how variouſly Faith acteth upon the ſeverall parts of the Word of God.</p>
               <p>There are in the Word, 1. ſome things affirmed; and that either Doctrinally, or Hiſtorically, theſe Faith aſſents to.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Some things are commanded: theſe Faith ſubmits to.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Theſe Commands are enforced by Promiſes: theſe Faith embraces and relies upon.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Theſe Commands are alſo enforced by threatnings: theſe Faith ſtands in awe of.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Faith aſſents to the truth of whatſoever the Word of God affirmes, <hi>John</hi> 3.33. <hi>He that believes ſets to his ſeal that God is true.</hi> And 1. in the Hiſtoricall part of the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:30489:50"/>
Word, particularly concerning the Creation it is ſaid, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. by <hi>Faith we believe that the worlds were created by the Word of God,</hi> &amp;c. If it be objected, That this is a thing may be known and demonſtrated by reaſon, and therefore is not an object of Faith. I anſwer, Firſt, it is not to be taken for granted, that the ſame thing cannot be the object both of Faith, and Knowledge, <hi>vide Baronium de fide, Art.</hi> 4.2. Though the Creation ſhould be demonſtrated by reaſon, yet that it was made by the Word of God, and that it was not made of things that do appear is the object of Faith, as appears by the ſtrange conceits which many of the wiſeſt Philoſophers had of it.</p>
               <p>So for the Doctrines of the Scripture, as, of the Trinity, and perſonal Union of the two Natures of Chriſt, imputed righteouſneſs, the Reſurrection, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Faith believe;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:30489:50"/>
with reaſon againſt reaſon; as it is ſaid, to believe the Promiſe in hope againſt hope: that is, though reaſon be not able to comprehend how theſe things ſhould be, at leaſt ſome of them, yet, that they are, we have reaſon enough to believe, becauſe God that cannot lie hath ſaid it; and though we know not how they ſhould be, God doth; and this would be greater arrogancy in us to deny, than if ſome rude ignorant fellow ſhould face down a Mathematician, that a ſtarr is no bigger than the palme of his hand, or the Sun than his cart-wheel; or, if there be any <hi>Antipodes,</hi> they muſt needs go with their heads down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Now the Word is of great uſe to us in reſpect of theſe things which Faith believes. The Apoſtle being to ſhew the great uſe and vertue of faith, begins with this act of it, whereby we believe the Creation of the world, ſuppoſing
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:30489:51"/>
that nothing will be too hard for a believers faith, ſeeing (as <hi>Amyrald</hi> in his Paraphraſe on the place obſerves) although the things that we believe do not yet appear, this hinders not, but we may have full aſſurance of their future exiſtence, ſeeing the ſame power of God which created the world of nothing, may give beeing to whatſoever we believe, when it ſeems good to him: and we ſhall obſerve that frequently in Scripture, God doth ſupport the Faith of his people with this conſideration, of his creating heaven and earth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.28. and 51.13. and herewith <hi>David</hi> ſtrengthens his confidence, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 121.2. <hi>My help ſtands in the name of the Lord that hath made heaven and earth:</hi> as if he had ſaid, I will never diſtruſt his power, for deliverance or protection, who could erect ſuch a ſtately Fabrick from nothing. And there are other hiſtorical paſſages of Scripture alſo,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:30489:51"/>
which may be of like uſe unto us, both for encouragement, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.17. and caution, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11. yea, and for confirming our Faith in the <hi>Meſſiah, John</hi> 20.31. that Hiſtory of the acts and Sermons of Chriſt, being written by <hi>John,</hi> in his old age, for the confirming of the Deity of Chriſt, againſt thoſe which then begun to deny it, at the requeſt of the Biſhops of <hi>Aſia,</hi> which is the reaſon why he diſputes more clearly of the Deity of Chriſt, than any of the other Evangeliſts, and records divers of his miracles, which ſerve for the confirmation thereof, that the reſt do omit, And for thoſe points of Doctrine which Faith aſſents to, and are not otherwiſe demonſtrable by reaſon, they are generally reckoned amongſt thoſe Fundamentalls, the belief of which is neceſſary to Salvation. But herein the uſe of Faith in this particular doth further appear: when
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:30489:52"/>
men do not believe ſuch things as theſe, it brings them to flat Atheiſme at laſt; for they firſt queſtion, and by degrees deny the Authority of the Scriptures, when they ſee the improbability or rather impoſſibility (as ſeems to their reaſon) of many things, both in the Doctrine and Hiſtory of it, as in Philoſophy, becauſe ſome cannot conceive how ſuch a vaſt body as it is demonſtrable that the Sun is, ſhould move ſo many thouſand miles in an hour, as it is neceſſary it muſt, if we ſuppoſe that it move at all, venture rather to deny the received opinion of its motion, and entertain that <hi>paradox</hi> of the motion of the earth.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Faith ſubmits to the commands of the Word, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. we ſhall finde many eminent acts of Obedience aſcribed to Faith, as <hi>ver.</hi> 8. <hi>By faith Abraham, when he was called to go out into a place which
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:30489:52"/>
he ſhould afterwards receive for an inheritance, obeyed, and he went out, not knowing whither he went.</hi> It was an hard tryall, for, as the Proverb is, <hi>patriae fumus igne alien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> luculentior,</hi> the ſmoak of our own Country is as good as the fire of another: and he was to go he knew not whither; for God only bade him go into a country that he would ſhew him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.33. So that command which was yet more hard, of offering up his ſon, he ſubmitted to by faith, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. he was to offer up his <hi>ſon,</hi> which was againſt nature, yea his only begotten ſon, (that is of his wife) and the ſon of the <hi>promiſe,</hi> in whom his ſeed was to be called. So <hi>ver.</hi> 29. <hi>By faith they paſſed through the red ſea,</hi> when it was very unlikely the unruly ſurges of it ſhould keep their place while they went ſo many miles. <hi>ver.</hi> 30. <hi>By faith they compaſſed the walls of Jericho ſeven dayes together, with
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:30489:53"/>
ramms hornes,</hi> a very ridiculous thing in the eyes of men. Now Faith doth thus ſubmit to the commands of God, becauſe we are thereby brought into covenant with God, and conſequently ſubject our ſelves to his authority, as a wife by taking another to be her husband, doth oblige her ſelf to thoſe duties which do immediately reſult from ſuch a relation, and to that ſubjection which is due from a wife to an husband: So by taking God to be our God, and Chriſt to be our husband, we are <hi>ipſo jure</hi> obliged to ſubmit to all his commands. <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.17. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.32. We are indeed obliged to this ſubjection before we believe, but by faith we own our obligation, and do actually and profeſſedly make a recognition thereof: So that we may ſay as <hi>Salvian. de guberunt. Dei, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Fides eſt fidelis Deo eſse, hoc eſt,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:30489:53"/>
fideliter Dei mandata ſervare.</hi> Faith is to be faithful to God, that is, faithfully to keep his commands; yet I am far from thinking with <hi>Socinus, Defenſ.</hi> 108. that <hi>fides in Chriſtum &amp; iſta opera ſunt re ipſa idem;</hi> and that a faith of ſuch a lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, is the matter of our Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and holds the ſame place in the Covenant of Grace which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect obedience ſhould have done in the Covenant of Works; theſe are not Faith <hi>formally,</hi> but only <hi>effectivè</hi> true Faith neceſſarily producing theſe, (<hi>Vide Streſonis meditat. de fide, ſect.</hi> 34, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Faith receives the Word as the Word of God. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. in which place we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve three things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The power of the Word, it wrought <hi>effectually.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The perſons in whom it had this efficacy, they were ſuch as did <hi>believe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:30489:54"/>3. The reaſon of it, they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it not as the word of Man, but as the Word of God; which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies two things:</p>
               <p>Firſt, Their receiving it <hi>Qua Verbum Dei,</hi> or under that notion, conſidered as the Word of God, or believing it to be ſo; whether it be ſtrictly and properly the object of Faith <hi>that the Scriptures are the Word of God,</hi> I will not ſtand here to diſpute, or determine; and how the preaching of men may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived as the Word of God; you may ſee in the fore-mentioned Treatiſe of Mr. <hi>Hieron, We are to prove all things, that we may hold faſt that which is good,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.21. and that we may do ſo we are to ſearch the Scriptures, to ſee how that which we hear doth accord there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.11. and what is rightly deduced or inferred from the Word is of the ſame authority with the Scriptures,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:30489:54"/>
as <hi>Daille</hi> and <hi>Vedelius</hi> have ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently proved againſt the new <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodiſts</hi> in <hi>France</hi> (as they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) who by denying this did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake quite to overthrow the Doctrine of the Proteſtants; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the ſucceſs of ſuch an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking would have been, their boaſts may ſerve for a caution to thoſe who decry conſequences; but I hope men are not ſo zealous now againſt them as they ſometime were, elſe I ſhould before this time have taught that ſmall Treatiſe of <hi>Daille</hi> to ſpeak <hi>Engliſh:</hi> wherein he uſeth his wonted candor and clearneſs.</p>
               <p>Secondly, To receive the Word as the Word of God, is to receive it as becomes the Word of God, that is, as the Word of ſuch a God who is ſo wiſe, ſo juſt and faithful, ſo good, ſo holy, that all his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands muſt needs be <hi>holy, and juſt, and good, Rom.</hi> 7.12. and ſo not to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:30489:55"/>
be diſputed, but obeyed, for by Faith we believe the nature of God as well as his beeing. Now Faith is in this reſpect of ſingular uſe in the whole courſe of our lives; how oft do men ſtand and diſpute the commands of God till they reaſon themſelves out of their duty in things that are againſt carnal rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and carnal intereſt, things which are of meer poſitive inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not of any natural moral right: but Faith conſiders not any thing againſt a Command, as it is ſaid, <hi>Abraham</hi> did not againſt the Promiſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.19. If Chriſt bid <hi>Peter</hi> caſt in his net, though he have toiled long in vain, he will do it at his command, <hi>Luk.</hi> 5.5. If a Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhould be enjoyned ſuch things as the Prophets were oft enjoyned, as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 4.8, 12. (unleſs, as ſome think, theſe things were only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to them in viſions, and they were not really to do them,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:30489:55"/>
ſee <hi>Smith his ſelect diſcourſes of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie,</hi>) he would not ſtick at them, but do all things without murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or diſputing, even ſuch things as are moſt againſt intereſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.8. yea, againſt natural affection, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.17. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.18.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Faith doth embrace the Promiſes, (that is, lay hold on them, thankfully accept them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.6.) and relie upon them for the performance of the mercy promiſed. <hi>Abraham</hi> being ſtrong in the Faith, gave glory to God, and againſt <hi>humane</hi> hope believed in <hi>divine</hi> hope, not regarding any thing which might be objected againſt the Promiſe of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.17, <hi>&amp;c. Let God be true and every man a lyar,</hi> yea, every thing a lyar, ſenſe and reaſon; he conſidered not any thing that they could plead againſt a Promiſe. How happy might a Chriſtian be if he could live by faith in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar?
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:30489:56"/>
Truſting God upon his bare word, when there is nothing elſe to vouch him, when we have neither ſence nor reaſon to ſecond our Faith. But the Promiſes have a more peculiar influence into our ſpiritual life, by them we are made <hi>partakers of the divine nature,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. that is, are made <hi>godly,</hi> like to God in holy diſpoſitions, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations; and the Promiſes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce hereto both <hi>morally,</hi> and (as I may ſpeak) <hi>inſtrumentally.</hi> There are Promiſes <hi>to</hi> Grace, theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote it, as we are thereby encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to the exerciſe of Grace, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58. and to preſs on to the perfection of Grace, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. For ſupernatural habits are ſtrengthened and confirmed by exerciſe and renewed acts, though we ſhould ſay they are not acquired thereby. But there are Promiſes <hi>of</hi> Grace. Whether the Promiſes of the firſt Grace be mad <hi>to,</hi> or may
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:30489:56"/>
be pleaded <hi>by</hi> any particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or whether they may be made only to the Church in general, as the Promiſes in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning the calling of the Gentiles, I ſhall not take upon me to define. But certainly there are Promiſes of following Grace to be pleaded by particular, perſons in Prayer, as was ſhewed in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Chapter; and this pleading of Promiſes in Prayer is, as M. <hi>Dod</hi> would ſay, like putting of bonds in ſuite: Thus the Promiſes are means or inſtruments for conveying of Grace to us.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, There are <hi>Threatnings</hi> in the Word of God, and theſe Faith makes the ſoul ſtand in awe of, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.161. Certainly, <hi>Davids</hi> heart ſtood in awe of the Word of God, becauſe he believed it; as the <hi>Ninevites</hi> took warning at the preaching of <hi>Jonah,</hi> and proclaimed a faſt, becauſe they believed God,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:30489:57"/>
                  <hi>Jonah</hi> 3.5. But the cleareſt proof hereof is, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.7. by Faith <hi>Noah</hi> being warned of God of things not ſeen as yet, moved with fear, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared an Arke, to the ſaving of his houſe: In theſe words we have the faith of <hi>Noah</hi> commended from the warning he took at the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of God concerning the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal deluge which was to come upon the World; he believing this threatning, his fear put him upon the uſe of ſuch means as might prevent the evill which he feared, (the beſt uſe of that paſſion) and moſt that it is good for) and we ſee the iſſue of it, he ſaved himſelf and his houſe; like a prudent man, he foreſaw the evill and hid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.3.</p>
               <p>Now, let us ſee the power of <hi>Noahs</hi> faith in this, and how much reaſon he had to object againſt what he did.</p>
               <p>Firſt, He was warned of things
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:30489:57"/>
which did not appear, that which was threatned was yet many years to come, ſo that he might ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry probably die before that time, and be paſt need of an Arke; and what he was commanded was ſuch an unlikely thing to be performed that it was enough to diſcourage his attempt; he was to take two of all Creatures but ſuch as lived in the water, and ſeven of ſuch as were clean beaſts, and food for all theſe; it was ſeven months after the flood began, ere the tops of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains were ſeen, and it is likely long after that before the earth brought forth food fit for them; and it muſt be an huge Veſſel to hold ſo many Creatures, and food for them for ſo long a time. And when he had made the Ark, how ſhould he get theſe Creatures together? Or, how ſhould he rule them when he had them together? And he might think that the undertaking of ſuch
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:30489:58"/>
a work would expoſe him to the ſcorn of others, and if he let it alone he might eſcape as well as others, yea, better perhaps, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving warning he might remove his habitation near ſome high moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain before the flood came; but all theſe objections notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he went on with his work, and we ſee what was the iſſue of it. Oh how would men tremble at the Word of God, if they did certainly believe the threatnings of it! And what is it that hardens men in their wickedneſs but ſuch carnal reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings as <hi>Noah</hi> had in ſtore to have brought out againſt the warning of God. Tell men of the judgement to come, enough to make an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then tremble, <hi>Act.</hi> 24.25. when he was a Judge on the Bench, and his Preacher a Priſoner at the Bar; Tell them of that horrour which will ſo amaze men at the laſt day, as to make them call for the rocks
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:30489:58"/>
to cover them, or the mountains to fall on them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.16. they either ſay with the Prophets hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 12.27. <hi>The Viſion is for many daies to come, and he propheſies of times afar off;</hi> He tells us of things to come a long while hence, and it will be time enough to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for them afterwards; or elſe they ſay with thoſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.19. they ſhall have peace though they walk in the imagination of their own heart; or they ſhall eſcape as well as others, or they ſhall be heard at the laſt day for their impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity (for ſo ſhall many ſeek to enter into the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) or if they ſhould ſet upon the work of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance they muſt leave their old waies, and their old company, and ſo expoſe themſelves to their ſcorns; theſe are ſuch reaſonings as Faith in <hi>Noah</hi> overcame; and it might be well for godly men to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:30489:59"/>
improve the threatning of the Word more to the reſtraining of their corrupt luſts and affections. How ſhould ſuch places, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. be as the Sword which the Angel held before <hi>Balaam</hi> when he followed the wages of unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.23. If any ſhall to that place object, that believers cannot die. I am ſure that place will prove then, that believers can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not live after the fleſh, and that if we live after the fleſh we are no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers; it proves the connexion betwixt the means and the end, betwixt dying and living after the fleſh; and let not any think theſe are too low motives for Chriſtians to be acted by: God thought them not unmeet for <hi>Adam</hi> to make uſe of in innocency, he had an intimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dating threatning, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. Chriſt preſſed ſuch upon his Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.29. God hath ſet our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions one over againſt another,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:30489:59"/>
as 'tis ſaid of proſperity and adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.14. and happy is he that finds no need of fear to reſtrain the violence of his other affections. I ſhall conclude this Chapter with the anſwer of an objection; ſome may ſay, How can Faith be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for making the Word thus effectual, when Faith it ſelf comes by hearing, and is ordinarily wrought by the Word, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17. To this I anſwer: Firſt, That as God at the Creation did not hold to the ordinary Method which he hath kept ſince, but created the Light before the Sun, though ſince the Sun hath been created it hath been the Fountain of Light: So though ordinarily the VVord is made effectual by Faith, it is not neceſſary God ſhould obſerve the ſame Method in the firſt working of Grace which he doth in carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it on, But ſecondly, Though Faith come by hearing, yet there is
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:30489:60"/>
a Faith concomitant with that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, elſe the Word would not at all profit: The Word brings that evidence along with it which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets the faith whereby it becomes effectuall: it is obvious to every ones conception, that if a man come to deal with me about any thing, all he can ſay doth nothing at all move me, unleſs I give cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to what he ſaith, and yet he may uſe thoſe Arguments or Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences which may make me believe him; and in eating, certainly our food doth ordinarily encreaſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and ſo natural heat, before the ſeveral concoctions be performed, and it is by that natural heat that the ſeveral concoctions are perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, whereby our food doth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nouriſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:30489:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The ſeveral uſes of the Lords Supper exciting Grace in us; conveying Grace to us; ſealing the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; by Faith only we have a right thereto, and make right uſe thereof; in the Controverſies about the Sacraments, the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not ſo much about mens title thereto, but our judgement of their title; the Judgment of the Church of <hi>England</hi> herein; whether thoſe who doubt of their ſincerity may come to the Lords Supper; how we are to deal with ſuch; the ground of many mens deſire to come thereto.</head>
               <p>I Come now to ſpeak of the Lords Supper, and that you may ſee how this is a means for the ſtrengthening and encreaſe of Grace, that ſo we may <hi>have life, and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:30489:61"/>
have it in abundance, Joh.</hi> 10.10. I will ſhew you the uſe of this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. And</p>
               <p>Firſt, It is a ſign to repreſent ſpiritual things to us, we do herein ſee <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, as it were, evidently ſet forth and crucified among us, Gal.</hi> 3.1. we therein <hi>ſhew forth the Lords death till he come,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. and therefore are to do it in <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of him, verſ.</hi> 25. that is, to perpetuate or continue the memory of his Death and Sufferings in the Church to the end of the World; and hereby it becomes a means for the exciting of Grace, and an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the exerciſe of it, the eye affecting the heart, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.51. Here we have occaſion for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of <hi>Repentance,</hi> while we ſee the body of Chriſt broken, and his bloud powred forth; <hi>He was woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for our tranſgreſſions, and bruiſed for our iniquities, Iſa.</hi> 53.5. we are many times it is likely filled with
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:30489:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>
indignation againſt the Jews, when we read how they dealt with him; but we are therein, at Dr. <hi>Stoughton</hi> ſaies, like the fooliſh <hi>Athenians,</hi> who when they had killed an Oxe, an innocent Creature in Sacrifice, acquitted the Prieſt, but condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Sword that gave the dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtroke of murder; for we did more to the crucifying of him than <hi>Pilate,</hi> or the Jews, or the chief Prieſts, ſo that we ſhould father be moved with indignation againſt our ſelvs, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11. <hi>When we look on him whom we have pierced, Zach.</hi> 12.10. <hi>And be in bitterneſs.</hi> There we may ſee more of the evill of ſin by what God inflicted on his own Son, than if we could look into hell and ſee the preparations which are made for the puniſhment of it. Again, we have here an encouragement to <hi>Faith</hi> while we ſee the love of God in giving his Son, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16. The love of Chriſt in giving himſelf,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:30489:62"/>
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. The expiation which was made by his Bloud that clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth us from all ſin, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. We have here alſo occaſion for the exerciſe of our <hi>love</hi> both to God and man, while we behold the love which God hath towards us, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.11.19. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.32. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.32. Our <hi>patience,</hi> while we ſee how Chriſt endured the Croſs, and deſpiſed the ſhame, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. Our <hi>joy</hi> and deſire, while we ſee the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations that God hath made for us, repreſented to us under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Supper, friendſhip and communion being moſt ſhewn in eating and drinking, and meat and drink is more neceſſary to us than the Objects of any other ſence; See <hi>Vines on the Lords Supper, p.</hi> 97, &amp;c. But there is a further uſe of this Ordinance, and that is to offer ſpirituall things and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate them to us; wherefore it is called, The Communion of the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:30489:62"/>
Body and Bloud of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. God doth therein really offer to us Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo all his benefits, as in Marriage, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the perſon we are entitled to the Eſtate; and <hi>his fleſh is meat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and his bloud drink indeed, Joh.</hi> 6.55. whereby our ſpiritual life comes to be preſerved and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; and as our food is turned into our ſubſtance: So there is the neareſt communion betwixt Chriſt and us in this Ordinance, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this is comprehended the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling uſe of it; God doth hereby ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely confirm the Covenant of Grace in general, and likewiſe in particular, to every one ſo far as their faith doth act upon the things ſignified, as their ſence doth upon the outward ſigns. See this plainly handled in Mr. <hi>Marſhal</hi>'s defence of Infant-Baptiſm, 117, 201. but accurately in Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> againſt <hi>Blake, Sect.</hi> 64.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:30489:63"/>Now, Faith is abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the right receiving of the Lords Supper; and obſerve this, That though there are many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes about the qualifications of ſuch as are to be admitted thereto, the queſtion is not concerning the ground of <hi>their title,</hi> but <hi>our judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> Not what it is that gives them a right to it, or fits them for it, but what is a ſufficient ground for us to judge them to be ſuch as have a right to it, and are fit for it. Some ſuppoſing a meer verbal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion to be enough; others requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a credible profeſſion, or ſuch a profeſſion as we may in prudence and charity judge to be real and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere; which ſeems very reaſonable, profeſſion not being required for it ſelf, but as a ſign of the thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed. See Mr. <hi>Baxters Diſputations of right to the Sacraments, p.</hi> 6. &amp;c. and of <hi>Confirmation, p.</hi> 41, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but that Faith is neceſſary to the right
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:30489:63"/>
uſe of it hath been the conſtant Judgement of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> both in its former and latter conſtitution; and that not only a <hi>dogmatical</hi> faith, but <hi>a lively Faith in the mercy of God through Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> See not only the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> and <hi>Catechiſm</hi> of the late <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> but the <hi>Articles</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> agreed upon 1562. <hi>Art.</hi> 29. The <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Ireland, Art.</hi> 96. The <hi>Catechiſme</hi> in the <hi>Book of Common-Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if any ſhould object, that the Catechiſme only ſaies, that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers are to examine themſelves about their faith.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, the duty of examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not required for it ſelf, but as a means to know whether we have this faith; becauſe, as the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Articles expreſs it, without this we cannot partake of Chriſt, but eat and drink to our own condemnation.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:30489:64"/>I forbear to cite the Teſtimony of other Churches or Authors, which would be both tedious and needleſs, the thing being evident in it ſelf; For conſider the Lords Supper, as it repreſents to us ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual things, and we cannot without faith diſcern the Lords Body; and though it may be diſcerned <hi>ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively</hi> by a bare hiſtorical faith, the fruit of tradition and common knowledge, yet we cannot diſcern it <hi>practically,</hi> ſo as to have the heart affected therewith, but by a lively faith, which is the ſubſtance of what is paſt, as well as of what is hoped for; that is, we do by Faith as really apprehend or diſcern the Body and Bloud of Chriſt, as if we had ſeen him upon the Croſs; and it is by faith alone that we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate to our ſelves what Chriſt hath done and ſuffered, which is neceſſary to a due affecting of the heart therewith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:30489:64"/>
But conſider the Sacrament as it offers and ſeal ſpiritual things to us, and it is certainly of no uſe to us without Faith. For as it is the eye of the ſoul whereby we ſee Chriſt, ſo the hand whereby we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him, and the mouth whereby we feed on him; and a dead man may as ſoon feed upon a banquet ſet before him, as an unbeliever on the Body and Bloud of Chriſt. Yea, though this ſhould be granted to be a converting Ordinance, yet a concomitant faith is abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to our receiving it with any benefit to our ſelves, which is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for my purpoſe to prove how neceſſary Faith is for the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all means for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and encreaſe of our ſpiritual life; and conſidering this as a ſeal, it is wholly uſeleſs to unbelievers, the Seal confirming no more than is in the Covenants, and they are wholly void and of none effect to
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:30489:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>
thoſe who fail of performing what is required of them therein.</p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude this with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering a queſtion which may ariſe from what I have before laid down. If Faith be ſo neceſſary to a right receiving of the Sacrament, how can thoſe adventure to come thereto who doubt whether they have true faith or no?</p>
               <p>This queſtion hath already been diſcuſſed by others, as Mr. <hi>Baxter on the Sacraments,</hi> p. 191, &amp;c. <hi>Mr. Ford in his Treatiſe of the ſpirit of bondage and adoption,</hi> 308. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall be more brief in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of it: And firſt in <hi>Theſt</hi> I may anſwer with Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> that we muſt in ſuch caſes as theſe follow the ſmalleſt prevalent perſwaſion of our Judgement, though far ſhort of full aſſurance; and as he truly ſaith, if we muſt act only upon certainty, we muſt ſleep out moſt of our lives: for beſides the caſes
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:30489:65"/>
wherein he inſtanceth that we muſt forbear giving thanks for ſpiritual mercies, as Juſtification, Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Adoption, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> till we have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained full aſſurance; it would be deſtructive to humane Society, and diſcharge children of their duty to their Parents, and in ſome caſes, and in ſome ſuppoſitions which are by many made, all Inferiours from ſubjection to their Superiours; in this caſe I may ſay with the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.21, <hi>If our heart condemn us not, then have we confidence towards God.</hi> Though we have not ſuch a full perſwaſion as doth exempt us from all doubting, if upon a due examination of our ſelves our heart do not accuſe us of hypocriſie, we may come with boldneſs to this heavenly banquet. But now in <hi>Hypotheſi</hi> if one ſhould come to me, and make it a caſe, whether he ſhould come to the Lords Supper or no: I would know of him the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:30489:66"/>
ground of his queſtion, if it be any deſire that he hath to come to this Ordinance, If it be not, I ſhall not trouble my ſelf to ſatisfie his curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity; but if he do truly deſire to come thereto, this may help to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer his queſtion. I do not think indeed that every deſire of coming thereto is an evidence of what may entitle a man to it, or fit him for it, for then we ſhould have many more Believers amongſt us than I can yet hope that we have; and it is this which hath cauſed ſo many violent intruders, and put Miniſters to ſo much trouble to keep thoſe who are unfit from theſe holy things. Doubtleſs, this deſire in many proceeds partly from mens impatience of having their faith or ſincerity queſtioned, though they are more unwilling to be Believers indeed; And partly, from thoſe Popiſh Principles which are ſo deeply rooted in many, of the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:30489:66"/>
neceſſity and efficacy of the Sacraments, as if there could be no Salvation without them, and no fear of miſſing ſalvation if we receive them. But I here ſpeak of a true, ſincere, well-grounded deſire; wherefore I would know of ſuch, what is the ground of their deſire to come to the Lords Supper; and if it be that they might partake of Jeſus Chriſt and his benefits, and a greater meaſure of his grace, whereby they may be enabled to walk more worthy of their holy vocation, this is ſufficient ground for a judgement of charity in thoſe who admit then, and of confidence in themſelves that they may come with boldneſſe thereto: and if they ſhould ſtill tell me they dare not come, and fear they have no right thereto; I ſhould no more regard what they ſay, than if a man ſhould ſeriouſly tell me that he would fain utter his minde to me but he
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:30489:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>
cannot ſpeak. And if they ſhould further object, that they fear, though their heart do not at preſent condemn them, yet they may be as the ſtony ground, and in time of temptation fall away, and ſo diſcover, that their Faith was not true: I ſhould adviſe ſuch to come to Chriſt in this Ordinance, as the <hi>Campani</hi> of old applied themſelves to the <hi>Romans,</hi> when they were oppreſſed by the <hi>Samnites Liv. li.</hi> 7. their <hi>Envoie</hi> which they ſent to them after a long ſpeech, uſeth theſe words, <hi>Quandoquidem noſtra tueri adverſus vim atque injuriam juſtâ vi non vultis, veſtra certa defendetis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Although you will not by lawfull power defend what belongs to us, againſt injury and violence, you will certainly defend what is your own; therefore we yield up the people of</hi> Campania, <hi>the City of</hi> Capua, <hi>our fields, Temples, and all belonging to us to your juriſdiction or
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:30489:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>
dominion; ſo that whatſoever we ſuffer for the future, we ſhall ſuffer as your ſubjects.</hi> So if we fear being overcome by the aſſaults of our ſpiritual adverſaries, let us apply our ſelves to Jeſus Chriſt, and go and renew our Covenant with him, reſigning up our ſelves, ſouls, bodies, and all the faculties and members thereof, to be kept by his power to ſalvation, that we may be able to claim his aid, and challenge his aſſiſtance, as he hath a ſpecial inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt in us, <hi>John</hi> 10.12. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. 9. and pray, as <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 119.94. <hi>I am thine Lord, ſave me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:30489:68"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> What our ſpiritual Adverſaries are. How our Luſts do tempt us. <hi>James 1.14.</hi> explained. The Diſadvantage of Believers in their ſpirituall combate, by reaſon of their own luſts, ſhewed by many ſimilitudes out of <hi>Pariſienſis.</hi> The uſe of Faith in purifying the heart. <hi>1 John 3.2, 3,</hi> cleared.</head>
               <p>IF we conſider the forementioned ſervices as part of that homage which we owe to our Creator, (acknowledging the dependance which we have on him, in directing all our prayers and ſupplications to him, the authority which he hath over us as our Lawgiver, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.12. by ſitting down at his feet, to receive of his words, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.3. the obligations that are upon us to him for the great things Chriſt
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:30489:68"/>
hath done and ſuffer'd for us, by celebrating the Memorial of his Paſſion, in the Lords Supper) Faith quits it ſelf ſufficiently in a right performance of theſe Duties. But conſidering them as means of grace, for the getting and encreaſe thereof, ſo what Faith doth therein is but in order to the overcoming of temptations, and bearing afflictions, wherein the grace which we get thereby is very much exerciſed. So that in ſpeaking of theſe things, I muſt neceſſarily refer to many things ſpoken of in the foregoing Chapters, though I ſhall not repeat them: and in treating of thoſe temptations which faith is of ſuch uſe to overcome, I ſhall ſhew you whence they proceed, and how we do by faith overcome them.</p>
               <p>Now theſe Temptations do proceed from the <hi>fleſh,</hi> from the <hi>world,</hi> and from the <hi>Devil.</hi> Theſe
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:30489:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>
are ordinarily reckoned our three ſpiritual adverſaries, and though they do all of them many times conſpire in the ſame temptation, yet I muſt treat of them diſtinctly.</p>
               <p>For the Firſt, The Apoſtle tells us, that <hi>fleſhly luſts war againſt the ſoul,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.11. <hi>And every man is tempted, when he is drawn aſide of his own luſt and inticed,</hi> James 1.14. where we have the two wayes whereby luſt prevails, either the <hi>impetus</hi> and violence of it, whereby it hurrieth a man into ſin, as the horſe his rider into the battle, <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.6. caſting reaſon down from its ſeat where it ſhould hold the reines of our affections, ſo that neither fear, ſhame, admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of others, checks of conſcience, our own Principles, Profeſſions, former reſolutions, will reſtrain them, but they break all bands, &amp; caſt away all cords, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2.3.</p>
               <p>Secondly, They entice and allure the will to conſent, by pretending
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:30489:69"/>
the great pleaſure and ſatisfaction in fulfilling them, the conſiſtency thereof with Salvation, purpoſe of repentance, probability of pardon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by reaſon hereof we fight with our other adverſaries at a great diſadvantage, as <hi>Pariſienſis de Tent. &amp; reſiſt. cap.</hi> 2. hath by many apt ſimilitudes excellently ſhewed, as Of a Kingdome divided againſt it ſelf, having a party within it ready to joyn, as occaſion ſerves, with a forrain adverſary. Of a Souldier that rides on a reſtive or unruly horſe, that runs backwards, or runs away with him, when he ſhould charge his enemy. To a ſtrong man ſtanding to fight on a ſlippery place, where he is not able to hold his feet to put forth his ſtrength. To a Souldier in a houſe or caſtle, that hath many breaches or open places where an enemy may ſhoot in at him. To a Souldier that bares an heavy burthen which
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:30489:70"/>
loads him, and preſſes him down, when he ſhould fight. To an houſe, whoſe lower part is of ſome combuſtible dry matter, and ready to take fire: ſo our hearts are ready, as occaſion ſerves, to comply with Satan, and betray us into his ſnares; our affections unruly, our ſenſes as ſo many windows or Avenues, through which Satan may caſt in his darts: our corruptions as a burden that keeps us down, as the remainders of an evil diſeaſe, that enfeebles us, ſo as we fail when we ſhould put forth our ſtrength againſt our ſpiritual adverſaries: our hearts as tinder, or gun-powder, apt to be ſet on fire by every ſpark of temptation.</p>
               <p>Now Faith is of great uſe to us in this reſpect, Purifying the heart from theſe corrupt luſts, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9. And this it doth,</p>
               <p n="1">1. As it unites us to Jeſus Chriſt, whereby we are made partakers of
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:30489:70"/>
the Divine Nature, which is continually luſting and ſtriving againſt our corrupt nature, weakening it by degrees: <hi>The ſpirit luſts against the fleſh, as the fleſh luſts against the ſpirit,</hi> Gal. 5.17. This is in the ſoul as the expulſive faculty, which is ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient to the nutritive faculty, expelling ſuch things as are noxious to nature.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By Faith we receive the ſpirit of Jeſus Chriſt: This may ſeem to be the ſame with the former, but they differ, as the habits of grace from aſſiſting grace, or <hi>auxilium habituale &amp; actuale,</hi> of which ſee <hi>Alvarez de auxiliis divin. grat. Disp.</hi> 82. <hi>N.</hi> 10. as the Fable is of <hi>Hercules,</hi> that he cleanſed the ſtable of <hi>Augea,</hi> wherein thouſands of oxen had lyen for many years, by turning a river through it: ſo this ſinke of our hearts is cleanſed by the ſpirit,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:30489:71"/>
which as a fountain opened for ſin, and for uncleanneſſe, doth continually flow in a believers ſoul, compare <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.1. with <hi>John</hi> 7.38, 39.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Faith purifieth the heart, as it improves thoſe Ordinances which are means for the purifying of it, as the Word, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.9. <hi>John</hi> 15.3. Prayer, <hi>Exek.</hi> 36.26, 27, 37. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 51.10. &amp;c. How Faith improves theſe I have ſhewed in the former Chapters.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Faith doth this morally, by improving ſuch Arguments as may perſwade us hereto, 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 7.1. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2, 3. Faith and Hope run parallel, faith believing the promiſe, hope expecting the thing promiſed, and we can hope for nothing but what we believe the Promiſe of. Now, whoever hopes to be like Chriſt hereafter, will certainly purifie himſelf, that he may, in ſome meaſure, be like him here,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:30489:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that being our ſtate of perfection, and there being in every thing a naturall tendency and reaching forth to its perfection, and the ſpirit doth not work in us as phyſick, but there muſt be a ſubordinate concurrence of our wills therewith: the Apoſtle, on the ſame ground, preſſeth to mortification, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.4, 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:30489:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> What a dangerous temptation the world is, What it is to overcome the world. The Story of <hi>Conſtantius</hi> his Courtiers. The Parable of the thorny ground. <hi>Luke 8.14.</hi> opened. How Faith overcomes the world. <hi>Heb. 11.24,</hi> &amp;c. illuſtrated. <hi>Matth. 6.30,</hi> &amp;c. cleared. How Faith overcomes by looking to the recompence of reward. How it diſcovers the vanity of the world, <hi>1 Cor. 7.29,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>THe world in our ſpiritual conflict is as the <hi>Midianitiſh</hi> women which cauſed the Children of Iſrael to ſin, <hi>Numb.</hi> 31.16. according to the wicked counſel of <hi>Balaam,</hi> ſpoken of <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.14. the ſtory of which we may read, <hi>Num.</hi> 25. and more fully in <hi>Joſ. de Ant. Jud. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 6. And though the neceſſaries of this
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:30489:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
life ſometimes prove a temptation to many, yet the chief baits of the world are the ſuperfluities of it, as riches, pleaſures, honors, and preferments. Now as the Moraliſt ſaith of vices, we conflict with them, not that we may wholly overcome them, but that we may not be overcome by them: So if we can maintain our ground ſo farr againſt the world, that it doth not intangle and overcome us, it is a good degree of victory, though we be ſometimes ſolicited by the allurements of it. And we thus overcome the world.</p>
               <p n="1">1. When we do not uſe any unlawfull means for the attainment of the things of it. This was it which that good man feared, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.9. that being preſſed with poverty and want, he ſhould be tempted for the ſupply of his neceſſities to take ſome ſinfull courſe, and ſo make his Profeſſion
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:30489:73"/>
of the name of God to become vain.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When we do not for the things of the world caſt off the Profeſſion of Religion; like the Courtiers of <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> whoſe Story is worth ſetting down: The Chriſtians were ſometimes in great eſteem with the heathen Emperours, becauſe by means of their Prayers they ſometimes obtained great victories, and had wonderfull ſucceſſe, whereof there is a memorable inſtance in the Letter of <hi>Aurelius,</hi> which he ſent to the Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> the copy of which is to be read in the <hi>Magdeburgenſes Cent.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. ſo that <hi>Conſtantius</hi> had a minde to know whether there were any true Chriſtians in his Court; and to that end made a Decree, that whoſoever would ſacrifice to their Idols ſhould be preferred in his Court: but thoſe that would not muſt depart, and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:30489:73"/>
be thankfull that they might depart without puniſhment: Hereupon many did renounce their profeſſion, others reſolutely maintained it, and would not by any means be prevailed with to worſhip their falſe Gods. <hi>Constantius,</hi> when he had hereby made tryall who were ſincere in their Profeſſion, and would rather loſe their honors and Preferments than quit it, theſe he highly honoured and advanced, but the other he ſeverely reproved, and baniſhed them from his Court, as being unfit to be truſted by men, who would not be faithfull to God, <hi>Euſebius, de vita Constantini, &amp; Hiſtor. Trip. L.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7. So the <hi>young man,</hi> Matt. 19.22. left Chriſt, being overcome with the love of riches: and thoſe <hi>John</hi> 12.42. had ſome convictions that Chriſt was the Meſſiah, but durſt not make confeſſion to Salvation, becauſe they loved the praiſe of men more
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:30489:74"/>
than the praiſe of God; as many doubtleſs are ready to ſay with <hi>Balaam, Numb.</hi> 23.10. <hi>Let me die the death of the righteous,</hi> being convinced they are in the right way, yet think if they ſhould live their life, and betake themſelves to a ſtrict courſe of holineſs, they ſhould be accounted ſome ſilly ſneaksbies, or dull <hi>hypocondriaques,</hi> men of no port or breeding, among the <hi>eſprits forts,</hi> or brave gallants of the time; and they will loſe heaven rather than runne the hazzard of ſuch an imputation.</p>
               <p>But yet there is a 3. way, farr more dangerous, whereby the world prevails againſt multitudes, and this is intimated in the Parable of the thorny ground, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.14. thoſe do not fall away, as they <hi>v.</hi> 13. but hold on in a Profeſſion of Religion; but it comes to nothing at laſt, they bring forth no fruit to perfection, being choked with cares, and riches,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:30489:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and pleaſures of the world, they deceive themſelves by thinking to ſerve both God and <hi>mammon,</hi> to keep up a Profeſſion of Religion, which will conſiſt with their luſts &amp; carnal intereſts. Now theſe things hinder the growth of the Word, as thornes hinder the growth of the corne, 1. by drawing away the heart of the earth, whereby the corne ſhould thrive and grow, 2. by overtopping the corne, and keeping it down. While theſe ſhould be meditating in the Word of God day and night, having their thoughts much exerciſed therein. that ſo they may be <hi>as a tree planted by the rivers of water, bringing forth fruit in due ſeaſon,</hi> Pſal. 1.2, 3. they have their thoughts wholly taken up with diſtracting cares about the neceſſaries of this life, what they ſhall eat, and what they ſhall drink, and wherewith they ſhall be cloathed, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.31. Or if their
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:30489:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>
abundance ſet them above this temptation, then riches or pleaſures ingroſs their thoughts; they are either projecting, how for the future to make proviſion for the fleſh, to fulfill the luſts of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.14. how to compaſs ſuch a place, or purchaſe, where to meet with ſuch company to enjoy their pleaſure, how to morrow may be as this day, and much more abundant, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.12. or elſe they are acting over their former ſinne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in their imagination, that they may again enjoy the pleaſure thereof by rumination, pleaſing themſelves with the remembrance of what they did in the dayes of old, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 23.19. at ſuch a time, in ſuch a place, in ſuch company, which is worſe than the firſt commiſſion of it, being in effect a juſtifying of their former ſin, and wiſhing they had an opportunity to commit it again upon ſecond thoughts, (which
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:30489:75"/>
ſhould be wiſer than former) every one knowes beſt himſelf how much of his ſolitary time is thus taken up; and ſuch thoughts as theſe prey upon the vitalls of Chriſtianity, as the diſeaſe called the <hi>wolfe</hi> preys upon the body. Or elſe, as the thornes overtop the corne; theſe make a profeſſion of Religion, and bear Chriſt fair in hand, while they can make his intereſt and theirs agree; but if they have an opportunity for ſatisfying their luſts: Chriſt muſt be ſerved as the man, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.8. he muſt take the loweſt room, to give place to another, and make way for their luſts. This was <hi>Herod's</hi> caſe, who heard <hi>John</hi> gladly, and did many things which he taught, but he muſt enjoy his pleaſure whatever <hi>John</hi> ſaid, <hi>Mark</hi> 6.17, 20. This is the ruine of thouſands of ſoules, <hi>who have a form of godlineſs, but are lovers of pleaſures,</hi> or elſe lovers of riches,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:30489:76"/>
and honors, <hi>more than lovers of God,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.4, 5. Now it is by Faith that we overcome theſe, <hi>This is the victory that overcomes the world, even our faith,</hi> 1 John 5.4. a clear proof hereof we have in <hi>Moſes, Hebr.</hi> 11.24. in whom God would let us ſee the victory of Faith as clearly as we did in <hi>Solomon</hi> the vanity of the world. Obſerve in this place the ſtrength of <hi>Moſes</hi> tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, his abſolute conqueſt, and the means whereby he overcame: to enforce the Temptation he had on one hand, the offer of being accounted the ſon of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s daughter, there was honor, <hi>ver.</hi> 24.2. the pleaſures of ſin, <hi>verſe</hi> 25.3. the Treaſures of <hi>Egypt, verſe</hi> 26. and if upon refuſall of theſe he might have lived quietly, and enjoyed a competent eſtate, the temptation had been ſmall in compariſon: but on the other hand he was preſented with reproaches,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:30489:76"/>
afflictions, and <hi>the wrath of the King,</hi> which <hi>is as the roaring of a lion,</hi> Prov. 19.12. yet <hi>Moſes</hi> choſe theſe rather than the former: Many make a vertue of neceſſity, and deſpiſe thoſe things which they have no hopes or means to attain: but in ſuch a caſe there is no temptation. <hi>Moſes</hi> had his choice of theſe, and we ſee what it was, that he preferred to all theſe offers of the world, not the glory which ſhall hereafter be revealed in us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18. but the <hi>reproach</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 26. And the time when he did this is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, it was not when he was young and unable to judge of the worth of theſe things, but when he was come to years, even when he was forty years old, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.23. neither was he then likely to be perſwaded to it by his mother: and all this he did by faith, <hi>ver.</hi> 24.</p>
               <p>Now Faith overcomes theſe temptations:</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:30489:77"/>1. As it relies firmly on the Promiſe and Providence of God. This will keep us from anxious cares, or the uſe of unlawfull means for the neceſſaries of this life. There is a known Story of a Good Man, who being in a ſtrait for mony, told his wife, he had a Bond lying by him, and now all failed he would go put that in ſuit, and this was the Promiſe of God, that <hi>he would never fail him, nor forſake him,</hi> Heb. 13.5. And ſuch a promiſe is better ſecurity to Faith than if we had the beſt eſtate in the Land morgaged to us. Though a man ſhould ſay to his ſoul, with him, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.19. <hi>Thou haſt goods laid up for many years. Riches may take to themſelves wings, and fly as an eagle towards the heavens,</hi> Prov. 23.5. quite out of ſight, and never to be recalled; but whoever wants, <hi>he that ſeeks the Lord ſhall want no good thing,</hi> that is, nothing that is <hi>formally</hi>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:30489:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>
good for him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.10. It is better to be at Gods finding, than to live upon a ſtock in our own hands. One would have thought <hi>Elijah</hi> had been well provided of water, if he had been as ſure of meat, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17. he ſate by a brook, but his meat was to be brought him by ravens, no very truſty ſervants; but the brook failed, when we do non read the ravens failed him: he had a ſupply of water according to the ordinary courſe of nature, his meat in a ſpeciall way of Providence. And Faith will likewiſe rely upon Providence as well as upon a Promiſe. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.30, &amp;c. we have</p>
               <p n="1">1. The ſin which Chriſt reproves, that was over ſolicitous care about the things of the world</p>
               <p n="2">2. The cauſe of theſe diſtracting cares, that was, The weakneſſe of their Faith, <hi>ver.</hi> 30.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Arguments which he uſeth for the ſtrengthening of their
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:30489:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>
faith; and amongſt many others, one is taken from Gods generall Providence, for all creatures, <hi>verſ.</hi> 28. another, from his ſpeciall providence for his own children, <hi>ver.</hi> 32.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Faith overcomes the world, as it hath reſpect to the Recompenſe of Reward, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.26, 27. For firſt, we thereby ſee the excellency of ſpirituall things, which doth much abate our eſteem of the world, and conſequently the force of the temptation. Theſe things having no glory in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that glory which excells, as the Apoſtle ſaith in another caſe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10. ſo faith diſdains the offers of the world in compariſon with Chriſt; as a Merchant would the offer of ſome contemptible thing for an exceeding rich jewell. So whatever the Devil can offer the ſoul in <hi>lieu</hi> of heaven, though he ſhould make the offer which he
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:30489:78"/>
did to Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.8, 9. The Believer would by faith diſdain to hear him, or to look to him, and be filled with indignation againſt him, as offering him incomparably leſſe, yea nothing in compariſon with that which he would bereave him of. <hi>Super omnem estimationem &amp; cogitationem, &amp; cogitatum minus quam decens ſit, &amp; nihil prorſus comparatione illius: Gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. Pariſienſ. de Tentat. &amp; reſiſt. prope finem.</hi> Away fawning pleaſures, that would bereave me of thoſe pleaſures which are at Gods right hand for evermore: begone deceitfull and vaniſhing honors, which would beguile me of that glory of which I can never be diveſted, from which I ſhall never be degraded. <hi>Valeat vita, pereat pecunia,</hi> &amp;c. Farewell riches, farewell life, if I cannot enjoy you without the loſſe of Eternal life, of a Kingdome that hath no end, an Inheritance that
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:30489:79"/>
fadeth not away. But further, Faith having reſpect to the recompence of reward, can by patience wait for it: <hi>Omne peccatum impatientiae aſcribendum:</hi> Every ſin is to be aſcribed to impatience, ſaith <hi>Tertullian de patientia, c.</hi> 5. When men like the Prodigal, muſt have their portions preſently, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.12. muſt have their good things in this life, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.25. cannot be content to be guided by Gods counſel <hi>here,</hi> and brought to glory <hi>hereafter,</hi> as <hi>Aſaph, Pſalm</hi> 37.24. Faith can ſtay, <hi>being the ſubstance of things hoped for,</hi> Heb. 11.1. reſting as quietly in expectation thereof, in confidence of Gods faithfullneſs, as if they had already a reall ſubſiſtence.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Faith overcomes the world, as we thereby diſcover the vanity of it. Faith eaſily ſees through the world, and ſo eaſily contemns it, ſees the bottome of
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:30489:79"/>
theſe things, as the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſſadour did the bottome of the <hi>Venetians</hi> coffers, when they ſhewed him their Treaſure. Senſe is blinde, and cannot ſee afarre off, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7. But Faith is a perſpective which makes things at a diſtance ſeem as at hand. <hi>Pariſienſis de Tent. L.</hi> 4. tells us a Story of a young man of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> that alwayes carried about with him the skull of a very beautifull woman, whom he had known in her life time, ('tis likely) that when at any time he found himſelf enticed by the beauty of any, he might look upon that skull, and deſpiſe it, conſidering what that will be brought to, in a ſhort time, which he is now ſo apt to doat upon: and as <hi>Gregory, Qualis erat mortua caro quae viva concupiſcitur.</hi> Faith needs not ſuch helps, but can look upon all the glory of the world, and weep over it, as <hi>Xerxes</hi> over his Army of ſo many hundred
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:30489:80" rendition="simple:additions"/>
thouſands: Or, as Chriſt on the buildings of the Temple, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Diſciples were ſo much taken, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.1. thinking how ſoon we ſhall <hi>deſpiſe</hi> or <hi>lament</hi> the ruines of what men now ſo much admire. The Apoſtle, upon this ground. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.29. bids, that <hi>thoſe who have wives ſhould be as if they had none; and they that weep as though they wept not; and they that rejoyce as if they rejoyced not; and they that buy, as if they poſseſſed not; and they that uſe this world as not abuſing it, for the faſhion of this world paſſeth away.</hi> No more effectuall Conſideration, to moderate our affections to the things of the world, and ſo prevent the abuſe thereof, than that of the vain appearance of happineſs which is in them, and their tranſient nature: Neither the comforts which we rejoyce in, nor the croſſes which we weep for, will be of any long continuance: <hi>Ce n'est qu'une
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:30489:80" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ombre paſſagere qui s'en va &amp; une vaine apparence du bien, Amyrald in loc.</hi> A flitting ſhadow quickly gon, A vain ſhew or appearance of happineſſe. <hi>Seneca</hi> hath a paſſage, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 110, which may ſerve for good gloſs upon this place, <hi>Quid miratis? Pompa est: ostenduntur istae res, non poſſidentur: dum placent, tranſeunt.</hi> When I behold (ſaith he) a brave houſe, a gallant train, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſay with my ſelf, <hi>Why doeſt thou wonder?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>all theſe things are meer</hi> pageantry, <hi>a ſhew which is gone while we pleaſe our ſelves with it.</hi> He could ſee thus farr by reaſon; but a Believer may much more clearly diſcerne theſe things by the eye of Faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:30489:81"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> The power of Satan to tempt, by working both upon the mind and affections, <hi>Epheſ. 6.16.</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened; how Faith overcomes his temptations; <hi>1 Pet. 1.5</hi> opened; <hi>Luk. 11.21, 22. illuſtrated;</hi> the general uſe of Faith in respect of all the pieces of our ſpiritual Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; <hi>Epheſ. 6.</hi> from <hi>verſ. 14.</hi> to <hi>verſ. 19.</hi> explained.</head>
               <p>SAtan is the chief enemy we have to conflict with, and when he deſired to <hi>have Peter,</hi> that is, to have him in his power, as <hi>Job</hi> 2.6. Chriſt prayed for him that his faith might not fail, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.31, 32. ſuppoſing he might be able to abide the encounter while his Faith held out. The influence of Angels both good and bad is certainly as the influence of the heavenly Bodies,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:30489:81"/>
very ſtrong, though we are little ſenſible thereof. The devill is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, he works powerfully or effectually in the children of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.2. he can doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs by the ſtirring of <hi>Phantaſms,</hi> and moving the <hi>ſpirits,</hi> work much both upon the <hi>judgement</hi> and <hi>affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> and theſe have alſo a mutual influence upon each other. He could put it into the heart of <hi>Judas</hi> to betray his Maſter, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.2. He could fill the heart of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> to lye to the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.3. He can take advantage of a ſinners grief and trouble to ſwallow him up of ſorrow, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7, 11. He can take away the Word out of mens hearts (by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting their minds to ſome other thing) leſt it ſhould ſettle in their hearts, and they be thereby perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to believe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.12. He can repreſent things to the mind by ſtirring of <hi>Phantaſmes</hi> when they
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:30489:82"/>
are not repreſented to the outward ſenſe; and he is ſo cunning, he knows how to apply <hi>actives</hi> to <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſives,</hi> how to fit and ſuite tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to mens tempers and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as <hi>Judas</hi> being a thief, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.6. that is, a covetous wretch, he could ſuggeſt to him the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of betraying his Maſter; and then <hi>Satan,</hi> when Objects are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented either to the <hi>ſenſes</hi> or <hi>ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination,</hi> can ſtir the <hi>ſpirits,</hi> and work upon thoſe humours which may exceedingly encreaſe thoſe paſſions, which ſuch Objects are proper to, and this is as ſpreading the ſails when the ſhip is carried by wind and tide; and hence is that violence of luſt which is ſpoken of formerly, <hi>Chapter</hi> 7. the Proverb being true here, that he muſt needs go whom the devill drives. And hence are thoſe dreadful temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to <hi>Despair,</hi> the devill holding mens minds intent chiefly upon
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:30489:82"/>
ſuch things as may encreaſe their fears, and thereby diverting them from ſuch things as might give them ſome hopes; and then work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the melancholick humours of the body, which have ſtrange operations on the mind to beget moſt ſad and diſmal apprehenſions, therefore it is no marvel if he can ſwallow us up of ſorrow. He that pleaſes to ſatisfie himſelf more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly about theſe things may conſult <hi>Voetius de natura &amp; operationibus daemonum,</hi> 960, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now Faith quenches all the fiery darts of Satan, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.16. In which place the Apoſtle alludes to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of thoſe who uſed impoyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Arrows or ſhafts in their fights, which <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>Job</hi> 6.4. the venome of which doth exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly burn and torment the fleſh where they ſtick. Whatever the temptations of Satan be they are very troubleſome to the ſoul, but
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:30489:83"/>
Faith doth either as a Shield keep them off, or as a ſoveraign Balſome allay the heat of their poyſon, it either prevents or cures them.</p>
               <p>Now Faith overcomes theſe temptations.</p>
               <p>Firſt, As we thereby have Union and Communion with Jeſus Chriſt, of which I have before ſpoken, we are kept by the power of God through <hi>Faith</hi> to ſalvation, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. It is the power of God which keeps us, but this it doth by Fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h, both as by Faith we derive a divine power to our ſouls, and as the power of God ſtrengthens our Faith. Chriſt by Faith dwels in the heart, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. and then we have one ſtronger in us than he that is in the World, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.4. who takes his armour from him and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides the ſpoyl, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.21, 22. takes from him thoſe things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he fortified himſelf, and ſerves
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:30489:83"/>
himſelf of them, as a Conquerour enriches himſelf with the ſpoyl, and arms himſelf with the weapons of his enemy. Satan ſometimes ſerved himſelf of our Wiſdom, Reaſon, Thoughts, Affections, which Chriſt brings into captivity to his own obedience, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4, 5. Our members, which were weapons of ſin to unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, are made Inſtruments of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs unto holineſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.19. Our goods, or riches, which were fuel to our Luſts, are now conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Gods uſe; and by Faith we have recourſe to Jeſus Chriſt for dayly ſupplies of Grace, whereby we are enabled to ſtand out againſt all the powers of hell, and through which we are more than Conquerours, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.30.</p>
               <p>Secondly, By Faith we over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the temptations of Satan, as we ſet to our Seals that God is
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:30489:84"/>
true, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.33. Man fell at firſt by believing the devill rather than God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.3, &amp;c. and we muſt now ſtand by believing God rather than the devill. How effectual would this be againſt temptations to Atheiſm, Blaſphemy, Unbelief, Deſpair, if we could keep cloſe to the Word of God? And when we find in our ſelves any temptations to unworthy thoughts of God, to diſtruſt his Promiſes, or argue againſt the comforts of his Word, let us preſently ſuſpect the hand of Satan, as <hi>David</hi> ſuſpected the hand of <hi>Joab,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.19. God is true, and cannot lye, but the devil is a lyar, and the father of it, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.44.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it is by Faith that we make uſe of all our ſpiritual armour; ſo that ſome from thoſe words, <hi>above all, Epheſ.</hi> 6.16. do infer the uſefulneſs of Faith for the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all other parts of our ſpiritual armour, and therefore is to be taken
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:30489:84"/>
upon them all, and not the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence thereof above them.</p>
               <p>But to come to the particular parts of this armour. As</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Truth,</hi> if we take it with reference to the mind or judgment, and thereby underſtand ſoundneſs of Doctrine, which indeed is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for keeping together the reſt of our ſpiritual armour, this is evidently a fruit of Faith, as appears by what hath before been ſpoken of Faiths aſſent to the Doctrine of the Goſpel; and the Apoſtle, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.14. ſhews why he kept cloſe to the Truth, though it was branded with the name of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, to the Doctrine of the Reſurrection, which was accounted ſuch a <hi>Paradox</hi> by the Philoſophers of <hi>Athens, Act.</hi> 17.18. He believed God with an implicite faith, in whatſoever was written in the Scriptures. Or if we take Truth as it reſpects the heart, or for <hi>ſincerity,</hi>
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:30489:85"/>
which indeed adds worth to all other Graces, they being as Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, exceeding precious if true, good for little if falſe, and this is the fruit of Faith, as Faith purifies the heart, and as by faith we ſet God before us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.27. there being no greater motive to ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty than a ſence of the preſence of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. So for <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> if we underſtand it of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted righteouſneſs of Chriſt for Juſtification, this is a Breſt-plate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enſing the heart and conſcience againſt the darts of Satan, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33. though we have many wounds in other parts of the body, if the heart be found we may recover, but a ſtab there kills. So if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience be untouched, we may be able to ſuſtain other infirmities, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.14. And this I have before proved to be the fruit of Faith, and ſhewed how Faith improves it in urging the Promiſes; if we hereby
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:30489:85"/>
underſtand inherent righteouſneſs, this is alſo a Breſt-plate, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 25.20. <hi>Pro.</hi> 13.6. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Nil conſcire ſibi,</hi> &amp;c. is as a brazen wall to a man, <hi>Hor. Epiſt.</hi> So <hi>Job, cap.</hi> 31. ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made a large profeſſion of his own integrity, <hi>ver.</hi> 35. faith, if his Adverſary ſhould write a book againſt him, he would bind it to him as a Crown, and he would go boldly to him and not be afraid to declare to him the number of his ſteps, that is, to give him a particular account of his whole life. And this I have alſo proved to be a fruit of Faith. And whatever is meant by the <hi>ſhoes</hi> of the preparation of the Goſpel, if it be ſuch furniture as the Goſpel prepares, this is of no uſe to us without Faith, as I have before ſhewed, <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. where I have alſo ſaid enough to prove that it is by Faith that we weild the Sword of the Spirit, which our Saviour made ſo much uſe of in his encounter with
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:30489:86"/>
Satan, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. That by the Helmet of Salvation is meant <hi>hope,</hi> is plain from 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.8. and whether it be called an Helmet becauſe it chiefly preſerves the head, ſecuring us againſt errour, as one thinks, <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pler on Jude</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 11. Or take it in a larger ſence, I have before ſhewed, that Hope neceſſarily ſuppoſes Faith, the work of Hope being to expect the accompliſhment of the Promiſe which Faith believes. And Prayer, which the Apoſtle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends as a general means for the uſe of our ſpiritual armour, cannot be rightly performed without Faith, ſo that our ſpirituall combate may well be called, <hi>The fight of Faith,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.12. ſeeing it is by Faith that it is wholly managed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:30489:86"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> The evil effects of ſore afflictions, where Faith doth not help to bear them; Faith looks to the Author, cauſe, ends of affliction; Good thoughts of God a great help to bear affliction; Three ends thereof, <hi>Deut. 8.16.</hi> Why outward troubles are oft ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with inward; Faith ſees all in God in affliction; Aſſurance not neceſſary to comfort; Believers more then Conquerours in affliction; <hi>Col. 1.11.</hi> opened; Recumbency the moſt noble Act of Faith; The advantage of Believers above others in affliction; The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>ALthough afflictions are in a proper ſence called temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet it will be requiſite to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them by themſelves, and to ſhew the uſe of Faith therein both for <hi>bearing</hi> them, and <hi>improving</hi>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:30489:87"/>
them. Afflictions if they be ſore and heavy, are as I have before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, a ſhadow of death, by reaſon whereof a Chriſtian is many times ready to faint, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.5. yea, to charge God fooliſhly, as if he would at laſt caſt us off, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 27.1. yea, as if he had already caſt us off, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.32. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.14. yea, as if he took pleaſure, or it did him good to grieve and afflict his own children, <hi>Job</hi> 10.3. and (which is more ſad) when they preſs hard, our feet are ready ſomtimes to ſlip, &amp; we almoſt repent of our repentance, and think we have cleanſed our hearts in vain, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.2, 13. So that God is fain to take off his rod leſt we ſhould be tempted to put forth our hand to iniquity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.3. But though we be as dying, yet by Faith behold we live, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Faith looks to the <hi>Author</hi> of our affliction, ſeeth the inviſible hand which inflicts and moderates
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:30489:87"/>
them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.27. while Sence looks only at the Inſtrument there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Now this doth much quiet the ſoul under affliction, as <hi>Eli</hi> ſaid, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.18. <hi>It is the Lord, let him do what ſeemeth him good.</hi> And <hi>Job,</hi> though the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beans</hi> had ſpoyled him, and taken away his goods, aſcribes it to <hi>God,</hi> as the righteous permitter and wiſe orderer of it, <hi>Job</hi> 1.21. When <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tila,</hi> King of the <hi>Hunns,</hi> came into <hi>France, Lupus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Troyes,</hi> met him, and asked him, who he was that ſo ſpoyled and made ſuch devaſtations in the earth? He anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Dei ſe eſſe flagellum,</hi> He was the Scourge of God; Whereupon <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> commanded the City Gates to be opened to him, and welcomed him with theſe words, <hi>Fauſte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grediatur flagellum Dei, Magdeburg. Cent.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. While the rod is in Gods hand there is no danger, he is a wiſe God and cannot be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen;
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:30489:88" rendition="simple:additions"/>
a ſtrong mighty God, who can rule the rod in his own hand, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.15. A righteous God, and can do us no wrong, <hi>Jer.</hi> 12.1. and will not give man advantage againſt him ſo as to enter in o judgement with him, <hi>Job</hi> 34.22. He is a good God, who doth not afflict willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor grieve the children of men, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.33. and ſo will be ſure to lay on no more than need requires, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.6.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Faith looks to the <hi>cauſe</hi> of our affliction; Sence is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to quarrel with God, as if he took pleaſure to afflict, <hi>Job</hi> 10.3. as if he took us for his enemies, and ſet us up for his mark to ſpend all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of his diſpleaſure upon us, <hi>Job</hi> 13.24. &amp; <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.12. but by Faith we may ſee through theſe clouds, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.17. and ſtay our ſelves on God, though we walk in darkneſs and ſee no light, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.10. <hi>Job,</hi> when he had recovered himſelf,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:30489:88"/>
and had found his faith, would not let his hold go of God though he ſhould kill him, <hi>Job</hi> 13.15. Yea, Faith can ſee love and faithfulneſs in the greateſt afflictions, becauſe it judges not by Sence, meaſures not happineſs by preſent enjoyments, and ſo makes not things before us an evidence of love or hatred, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.2. but reckons of things according to the tendency of them to the promoting our everlaſting happineſs; wherefore <hi>David</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges that it was in <hi>faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> that God had afflicted him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.75. God was therein <hi>faithful</hi> to the intereſt of his ſoul.</p>
               <p>Now this doth much caſe the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of affliction, we can eaſily bear that which we know is done out of love; the <hi>wounds</hi> of a friend are better than the <hi>kiſſes</hi> of an enemy, <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.6. We are impatient of an <hi>enemy</hi> beſieging us in a City, or
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:30489:89"/>
impriſoning us in a Caſtle, when we can well enough be content our <hi>Phyſician</hi> ſhould confine us to a Chamber, becauſe we know he doth it out of his love and care. If ever we would comfortably bear afflictions let us maintain good thoughts of God, and not make the ſevereſt interprerations of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences, or entertain any evill ſurmiſes or jealouſies of him; we ſhould indeed be ſo ſenſible of his Fatherly diſpleaſure as not to <hi>deſpiſe</hi> his chaſtening, but not queſtion his Fatherly care ſo as to <hi>faint</hi> when we are rebuked of him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.5.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, By Faith we look to the <hi>end</hi> of our afflictions, there are three ends of them which are ſet down together, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.16. The firſt is to <hi>humble</hi> us, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.6. this they do as they bring our ſin to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.21. as they let us ſee our dependance on God, and how obnoxious we are to him,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:30489:89"/>
how much we are at his mercy. The ſecond is to <hi>prove</hi> us, <hi>Job</hi> 23.10. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.6. and I have elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where ſhewed what an excellent fruit of affliction this is. The third is to <hi>do us good</hi> in the latter end, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.11. By experience we may know this afterwards, as <hi>David</hi> could ſay, It was good for him that he was afflicted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.71. But Faith rejoyces in this before hand, being the ſubſtance of things hoped for; and as the <hi>Levites</hi> praiſed the Lord before the victory, in confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of his faithfulneſs in making good his Promiſe; 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.21. ſo a Believer can rejoyce in tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, in <hi>hope</hi> of the happy iſſue thereof, as it is ſaid Mr. <hi>Dod</hi> did once in a very great affliction, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knew God would do him good by it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Faith takes Gods bare word, when a man hath nothing elſe to truſt to; and indeed this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:30489:90"/>
moſt properly Faith, otherwiſe we deal with God as we do with one whom we count a knave, whom we dare not truſt any further than we can ſee him; let Faith have but a Promiſe and it will be too hard for ſenſe or reaſon, becauſe it knows it is impoſſible for God to lie, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe is impoſſible to him but what is againſt his Nature or Word. <hi>Abraham</hi> believed this, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.19. Therefore he obeyed, knowing that if there was no other way to fulfill the Promiſe, God could do it by raiſing the dead; and this is to be obſerved, that when God will do any notable thing for any of his people, he firſt doth, as it were, ſentence to death all means condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing thereto, that ſo they may <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him that raiſeth the dead,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9. Thus he dealt with <hi>Abraham,</hi> with <hi>Joſeph,</hi> with the <hi>Iſraelites in bringing them out of Aegypt.</hi> And if Chriſtians did but
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:30489:90"/>
duly conſider this, it would free them from many ſad doubts and fears concerning their own condition: Many when they read the many Promiſes in Scripture to the children of God, and compare their own condition therewith, are ready to ſay, as <hi>Linacer,</hi> when he read the fifth Chapter of <hi>Matthew,</hi> Either this is not the word of Chriſt, or theſe are not the people of Chriſt; ſo either theſe Promiſes are not true, or we have no right in theſe Promiſes; and out of modeſty they rather chooſe to affirm the latter, and ſo caſt away their confidence, reaſoning concerning themſelves, as <hi>Job</hi>'s friends did concerning him, <hi>Job</hi> 4.7. God never caſt off a righteous perſon, but he had caſt off <hi>Job,</hi> wherefore <hi>Job</hi> was not a righteous perſon, but an hypocrite: and this is one cauſe why inward troubles do ſo
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:30489:91"/>
oft accompany outward troubles: as in <hi>David, Pſalm</hi> 6.2, 3. his body and ſoul were ſore vexed together. When men are in great ſtraits and afflictions, they think theſe things cannot ſtand with the Promiſes of God concerning his <hi>preſence</hi> with his people, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.1, &amp;c. <hi>his protection and proviſion, Pſal.</hi> 84.11. wherefore ſure they are none of his people. Do but obſerve how Chriſt rebukes his Diſciples, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.25. for being afraid, though they were in ſuch great danger, and he imputes this to the defect of their faith.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Faith ſees all in God in time of affliction, as it ſees God in all in time of proſperity: Thus <hi>Habakkuk</hi> lived by the ſame faith, <hi>chap.</hi> 3.17, 18. which he preached, <hi>cha.</hi> 2.4. Thus <hi>David</hi> had reckoned the protection of God as a garriſon, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.21. though ſome think he means <hi>Keilab,</hi> by that ſtrong city,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:30489:91"/>
yet others think, he means nothing but Gods Salvation, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.1. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.16. eſpecially comparing it with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.5. which he wrote when he fled for his life; and yet, how doth he there profeſs his own ſecurity, in confidence of Gods Salvation, <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.7. and it holdes as well for any other mercy, as for protection; for God, in promiſing to be <hi>a God</hi> to his people, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. doth in effect promiſe, that his power, wiſdome, goodneſs, or any other of his Attributes ſhall not be wanting to them when they may be improved for their Good. And where we ſee not the power of God put forth at any time for our help, and ſupply, in what we deſire or need, let us account that there the wiſdome and goodneſſe of God are ours, in denying us what he knowes would not be good for us, and what is better for us to want than have. <hi>Amemus unum bonum, in
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:30489:92"/>
quo ſunt omnia bona, &amp; ſufficit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>August. Med.</hi> Many obſerve a difference in the words of <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 33.9, 11. though they are tranſlated alike, <hi>Eſau</hi> ſayes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> but <hi>Jacob</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a wicked man, like <hi>Eſau,</hi> may have <hi>much;</hi> but a godly man, like <hi>Jacob</hi> hath <hi>all:</hi> For, as <hi>Austine</hi> ſaith, he <hi>hath all, that hath God, who hath all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any ſhall ſay, Indeed we might glory in tribulation, if we were aſſured that God is ours: But how can we ſee all in God, when we doubt of our intereſt in him? and, as the Apoſtle ſaith, that all men have not faith; ſo we may ſay, all Believers have not aſſurance. To this I anſwer, That full aſſurance is not allwayes neceſſary to our joy and comfort, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe did certainly live comfortably, and rejoyce in his condition, yet he was not ſure he ſhould abide therein, and not fall
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:30489:92" rendition="simple:additions"/>
from it; there was not <hi>certitudo rei,</hi> or aſſurance of the thing it ſelf, therefore <hi>he</hi> could not be ſure of it. And a child may comfort himſelf in hopes of his Fathers eſtate, though he know not but his Father may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inherit him. And if any reply, that <hi>Adam</hi> might be taken up with the happineſs of his preſent condition, and ſo not need to look forward for comfort, as Believers are fain to do, and that <hi>Adam</hi> had not ſo much cauſe to ſuſpect his condition, as a believer hath. I add, a Merchant rejoyceth much in expectation of his Ship coming home, richly laden, yet he knowes it is ſubject to great hazards at ſea, and I deſire this may be diligently heeded; Faith of <hi>recumbency</hi> (as it is commonly called) is the moſt proper and moſt noble act of faith, (though I am farr from thinking that the concluſion is not <hi>de fide,</hi> where both the premiſes are not ſo, &amp; ſo that aſſurance is not
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:30489:93" rendition="simple:additions"/>
faith) <hi>v. Daille la foi fondee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>partie</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 12. For as Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Thomas, Joh.</hi> 20.29. <hi>Bleſſed are they that have not ſeen and yet have believed:</hi> bleſſed are they who though they are not aſſured either by any mediate or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate teſtimony of the Spirit, yet dare rely (<hi>ſtrongly ſtrongly ſtrongly,</hi> as an eminent dying Saint once ſaid) upon the Promiſe of Jeſus Chriſt, that he will in no wiſe caſt out thoſe that come to him; for as thoſe are commanded to rejoyce that <hi>ſeek</hi> the Lord, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 105.3. though they have not yet <hi>found</hi> him, becauſe he hath not ſaid to any in <hi>vain ſeek ye my face,</hi> ſo may thoſe rejoyce that thus caſt themſelves upon Jeſus Chriſt, though he have not yet ſaid to them, <hi>I am thy Salvation,</hi> Pſal. 35.3. and he takes pleaſure in thoſe <hi>who ſo hope in his mercy,</hi> Pſal. 147.11.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, By Faith we receive ſtrength from Jeſus Chriſt for bearing of affliction. I have ſhewed
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:30489:93"/>
before how we have Union and Communion with Jeſus Chriſt, and through him we are able to do all things, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13. he ſpeaks not there of active obedience only, as a learned man hath obſerved <hi>Hales Romains,</hi> 125. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> there is as much as <hi>vales,</hi> or <hi>poſſum,</hi> which is as well <hi>to ſuffer,</hi> as <hi>to do;</hi> and it is clear from the context, that he ſpeaks there <hi>chiefly</hi> of ſuffering. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.11. There is a gradation, <hi>ſtrengthened with all might according to his glorious power, unto all patience, with long-ſuffering, and joyfulneſs.</hi> The power of God doth not only ſtrengthen us to patience, but to all patience; we may have patience in ſome afflictions, not in others; thoſe may bear loſſes perhaps, that cannot bear affronts or diſgrace; and not only to patience, but long-ſuffering: this reſpects the length of our ſufferings, as the other did the weight of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:30489:94"/>
Some can endure a ſharp brunt, but tire under a long affliction. But he goeth further to joyfulneſs, thoſe may endure an heavy affliction, and endure it long too, which yet go drooping and heavily under it: but by Faith in the power of Chriſt we may bear long and heavy afflictions with joy: <hi>Thus we are more than conquerors, through him that loved us,</hi> Rom. 8.37. we conquer afflictions, when they do not conquer us, but we are more than conquerors when we can rejoyce in them.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Faith looks to the recompence of reward, as I before ſhewed the efficacy of it in this reſpect, to overcome <hi>temptations,</hi> ſo we ſhall now ſee how effectual it is to enable us to bear <hi>afflictions:</hi> Though our outward man periſh, our inward man is renewed day by day, ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16. Afflictions did abound, yet they gained ſpirituall ſtrength to go
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:30489:94"/>
on more cheerfully, inſtead of fainting or drawing back, and the reaſon hereof was, they looked not on the things which were ſeen, but on the things which were not ſeen, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. which is the work of faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. As <hi>Columbus,</hi> when he firſt went to diſcover <hi>America,</hi> ventured a tedious and long voyage over the main <hi>Ocean,</hi> upon this confidence, that he ſhould there diſcover another part of the world, which had formerly been unknown to us, when the <hi>Spaniards</hi> that went with him were ready to mutiny, becauſe they had not ſo much judgment as to be perſwaded of any ſuch fruit of their travel. Or as <hi>Moſes</hi> had much adoe to get an unbelieving multitude along with him through the wilderneſſe, but they were oft murmuring, rebelling, turning back in their hearts unto <hi>Egypt.</hi> So have I ſeen thoſe who have
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:30489:95"/>
been unequally yoaked, and have had ſome heavy burden of affliction lying on them, the one hath born it cheerfully and comfortably, the other hath been an hindrance, and no help, continually murmuring and complaining. In ſuch caſes the vertue of faith doth moſt evidently appear; and though there are not many amongſt us, where the Goſpel is preached, ſuch infidels as to deny the Recompenſe of reward, yet it is only the exerciſe of a true and lively Faith, which can lift up the ſoul under affliction, that being the very <hi>ſubstance of the thing hoped for, and the evidence of things not ſeen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For a Concluſion of the whole matter let me borrow the words of a learned man, Dr. <hi>Arrowſmith, Tact. Sacr. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>ſ.</hi> 13. <hi>O quan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> memorem fides virtutum nobiliſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> &amp;c. How ſhall I make mention
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:30489:95" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of thee <hi>O Faith,</hi> the moſt noble of all Vertues? What ſhall I ſay of thee? Thou art the Hinge on which the Gate of heaven turns, the Bucket by which we draw the water of life, the Wedding Ring whereby the Soul is married to Jeſus Chriſt, the Receptacle of the Bloud of Chriſt, the only Condition of the New Covenant, and the chief part of the New Creature; they that by thee attain to a recumbency are ſafe, they that attain to aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance are <hi>joyful.</hi> Thou art the Eye, the Hand, the Mouth, yea, the All of our Souls. Yea, I may add, Faith is in <hi>Grace</hi> as the Philoſophers Stone in <hi>Nature,</hi> as a <hi>Catholicon</hi> or vniverſal ſoveraign remedy for all diſeaſes. It is in the Soul as the Lungs in the Body, the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of breathing, whereby <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis ſpiritus</hi> (as <hi>Fernelius</hi> ſaith <hi>tanquam patulo alitur &amp; fovetur;</hi> we are continually thereby taking
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:30489:96" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in, and giving out: Either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving from Jeſus Chriſt, or laying out for him. Wherefore with all our getting, as the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſaith of Wiſdome, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.7. let us get Faith, and pray, that God will <hi>fulfil the work of Faith with power in us,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.11. When Chriſt teaches his Diſciples the exerciſe of <hi>Love,</hi> they pray for the encreaſe of <hi>Faith, Luk.</hi> 17.5. Whatever we are called to in this World, let us pray <hi>Lord encreaſe our Faith;</hi> hereby we ſhall be able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our <hi>Duties,</hi> to exerciſe our <hi>Graces,</hi> to overcome our <hi>Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> to bear our <hi>Afflictions,</hi> to hold up in <hi>Deſertions;</hi> yea, <hi>all things are poſſible to him that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth, Mark</hi> 9.23. <hi>Search and examine your ſelves whether you be in the Faith or no,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. No Faith no Life; and be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in the uſe of all means
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:30489:96" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for the ſtrengthening of Faith, attend Ordinances, treaſure up Experiences, conſult the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of others, be diligent in ſecret duties, take heed of an evill heart of unbelief, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.12. This work is to be followed well, for we are ſlow of heart to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, Satan is a great enemy to Faith, and there are not in us the ſeeds of Faith as of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>Sibbs Souls Conflict.</hi> Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially let us be diligent in the <hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>exerciſe</hi> of Faith; I have ſhewed the uſe of it <hi>in actu ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nato,</hi> but let us learn the uſe of it in our dayly practice; <hi>David</hi> in his greateſt grief, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.18. took care to have the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> taught the uſe of the Bow; it is not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving good weapons in the War, that will do us any good without the uſe thereof: and Faith in the habit, not exerciſed, is but as
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:30489:97"/>
the Sword in the Scabbard. <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine, De aſcenſion. in Deum propè finem.</hi> The Apoſtles had Faith, <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.25. but they had it to ſeek when they ſhould uſe it, and ſo were at preſent as if they had none; as he that hath much and doth not <hi>enjoy</hi> it, is as if he <hi>poſſeſſed</hi> it not. Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver condition you are in, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you are about, ſtir up Faith, for it hath ſome work to do therein; <hi>Every thing is beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in its ſeaſon, Eccleſ.</hi> 3.11. and this is the ſeaſon of Faith, as Chriſt ſaid of the poor, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.8. I may ſay of ſome other Graces, we ſhall alwaies have uſe for them in heaven, not of Faith; <hi>here</hi> we live by Faith, <hi>there</hi> by ſight.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30489:97"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE OF <hi>Right Judgement,</hi> on</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOHN 7.24.</hi>
                  </bibl> Judge not according to the appearance, but judge righteous judgement.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur bleſſed Saviour, having healed a man on the Sabbath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, the Jewes were ſo enraged thereby, that they thought to kill him, <hi>John</hi> 5.16. And here
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30489:98"/>
he makes his defence, ſhewing how unjuſtly and partially they dealt with him. They do not <hi>ſtick</hi> to do thoſe things on the Sabbath day which <hi>Moſes</hi> commanded, he having given them the command of Circumciſion, <hi>Levit.</hi> 12.3. though he was not the firſt Inſtitutor of it; and if it happened that the Sabbath day was the eighth day after the birth of the childe, they circumciſed it on that day, which would have been a prophanation of the ſabbath <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.3. had not <hi>Moſes</hi> given ſuch a command concerning it. Hereupon our Saviour concludes his Apology with a wiſe and holy admonition, which might be of uſe to them in the whole courſe of their lives, and that was to <hi>judg righteous judgment:</hi> and to that end he warns them of one thing that doth moſt ordinarily pervert the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that is, <hi>judging according to appearance,</hi> or the face and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30489:98"/>
outward ſhew of things. And herein Chriſt may have reſpect either to his perſon, or to his action; if to his perſon, then it is as if he had ſaid, You think the authority of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſufficient to diſpenſe with the duties of the Sabbath, and never ſcruple any thing that he enjoynes, becauſe you think God ſpake to him, <hi>John</hi> 9.28, 29. but if you would make an impartiall judgement, and not ſuffer your ſelves to be deceived with the externall apearance of things; you might know, that though I come in the forme of a ſervant, and not of a King, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did, <hi>Deuter.</hi> 33.5. yet I have as ſufficient authority from God, for what I do, as <hi>Moſes</hi> had, <hi>John</hi> 5.36. yea I have the teſtimony of <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf, <hi>John</hi> 5.46. compared with <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.15. If it have reſpect to Chriſts action, then his Argument is thus, You paſſe ſentence upon actions according to the appearance
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30489:99" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and firſt view of them, without examining the grounds of them, or conſiderings in what caſes the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God are diſpenſible, when you ſee, according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſome things were done on the Sabbath-day, which had not been lawfull but for ſuch a particular command concerning them; and you do not obſerve how commands that are but Ritual, and of poſitive right, may yield to works of juſtice and mercy, elſe you would not have condemned the innocent, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.7.</p>
            <p>For the right underſtanding of the words of the Text, we muſt know, that both the Verb and the Nown verbal (which are ordinarily joyned together in Scripture) beſides many tropical and improper acceptions which they have, are for the moſt part taken either more largely, for an act of the minde, whereby we diſcern or determine
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30489:99" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of any thing, as in thoſe places, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.57. <hi>Why of your ſelves judg ye not what is right? Acts</hi> 4.19. <hi>Whether it be right in the ſight of God to hearken unto you more than unto God, judge ye.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.15. <hi>I ſpeak as to wiſe men judge ye what I ſay.</hi> The ſence of the words in theſe places is obvious to every one that reads them: Or elſe it is taken more ſtrictly, for judging evil, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.1, 2. both theſe ſignifications of the word we have in that elegant <hi>Antanaclaſis</hi> of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.13. <hi>Let us not judge one another, but judge this rather, that no man put a ſtumbling block, or an occaſion to fall, in his brothers way:</hi> that is, let us not condemn one another, but rather determine this in our own mindes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> here it is evident, that our Saviour underſtands it in the more large and proper ſence. Now, this judgement is either a private
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30489:100"/>
judgement of <hi>diſcretion,</hi> which belongs to every man; in this reſpect thoughts are free, ſo men think aright; or elſe a more publick judgement of <hi>Authority,</hi> which belongs only to thoſe who are appointed thereto; of this diſtinction ſee <hi>Aquin.</hi> 12 <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> q.</hi> 93. <hi>art.</hi> 2. 3 <hi>m.</hi> This command of judging righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly was firſt given in reſpect to this latter judgement of Authority, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.16. but it is here by our Saviour applied to the former judgement of diſcretion, it being neceſſary indeed in all caſes, that men ſhould judge righteous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is, according to truth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.2. as the thing is, as the matter requires. The judgment is the guide of our lives, and all our actions and affections are regulated thereby, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.22, 23. The eye enlightens the whole man, as a candle doth a room: And as the reſt of the members would not do
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30489:100" rendition="simple:additions"/>
their work aright, were it not for the eye that guides them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo neither can man do any thing aright, unleſs he be guided by a right judgment, which will make all that proceeds from him to be full of light, as with the light of a candle, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.36. See Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> on the former place, and on this latter, <hi>Eraſmus, Maldonate,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Hammond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The will indeed ſits as Queen regent in the ſoul, and the chief exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutive power belongs thereto; but as the King doth what he doth with the advice of his Councel, ſo the will followes the directions of the underſtanding; and when the will ſeems to be refractory, refuſing to follow the guidance of the judgement, it is becauſe the judgement doth not repreſent to the will the object which it ſhould chuſe, as <hi>omni modo bonum,</hi> as <hi>Camero</hi> ſpeaks, not as good or beſt in every reſpect; but though it do in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30489:101"/>
               <hi>theſi</hi> judge this or that to be beſt in general; yet <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc</hi> as we ſay, at this time, and as the caſe ſtands, it may judge the contrary more elegible: as a Drunkard may judge temperance to be better than exceſs, but having an opportunity to ſatisfie his appetite, and a ſtrong deſire thereto, and thinking for this once he may take liberty ſo to do, and eaſily obtain the pardon of it, he thinks it beſt at preſent to be drunk. Or elſe the minde is as a Maſter that is much from home, or is careleſs and negligent, and doth not look to his ſervants, to keep every one to his task, and ſo they grow idle and diſſolute. In like manner do the inferiour faculties uſurp authority, when the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding doth not clearly and actually repreſent things to the will; whence it comes to paſſe, that there are as well <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, luſts or wills
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30489:101" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of the fleſh, as of the minde, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3. ſee <hi>Amyrald. de lib. arbitr.</hi> 110. As it is not every feeble wiſh, or faint velleity of the will that can command the appetites, but an earneſt and reſolute purpoſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>tantum quiſque poteſt, quantum ſeriò &amp; vehementer vult, Camero</hi> 243. ſee <hi>Aug<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Confeſs. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 9. and <hi>Meſtrezat, in Heb. vol.</hi> 2. 134. So it is not any habitual knowledg of the minde, (which indeed the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> would not account knowledg) nor the weak and faint rayes thereof that can determine the will, but the expreſs clear actual dictates of it.</p>
            <p>But for the more diſtinct and full handling of this matter, I ſhall ſhew particularly wherein we are to judge righteous judgment: for though Chriſt here ſpeak, either concerning his perſon or actions, yet we may extend it further, and it is neceſſary in reſpect of
<list>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:30489:102"/>
                  <item>1. Opinions;</item>
                  <item>2. Actions;</item>
                  <item>3. Perſons;</item>
                  <item>4. Things:</item>
               </list>
In all which reſpects I ſhall ſhew you, how neceſſary a right judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, and how we may make ſuch a judgment.</p>
            <p>Firſt, We muſt judg aright of Opinions, or Doctrines. Every Chriſtian hath a judgement of diſcretion allowed him, and as we are not to act ecſtatically, like the <hi>Energumeni,</hi> which were acted of the devil, but upon rational grounds, knowing why we do what we do: So neither muſt we believe irrationally, but muſt judge for our ſelves. It is not enough for us to follow the judgment of others; for if the leader be blinde, not only himſelf, but he that follows him, ſhall fall into the ditch, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.14. wherefore we had need have our ſpiritual ſenſes exerciſed to diſcern
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:30489:102" rendition="simple:additions"/>
good and evil, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5.14. A Chriſtian indeed is not bound to determine every queſtion that is diſputed in the Schooles; there are many hundred queſtions I believe in <hi>Aquinas,</hi> and <hi>Scotus,</hi> which many good Chriſtians never heard of. But yet it is neceſſary that all fundamental truths ſhould be believed with an explicite faith, and next to neceſſary, that a Chriſtian be able to make a right judgement of other Doctrines that are not fundamental.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe Error in judgement is ſo deſtructive to godlineſſe, corrupt Opinions being like vapours, which being conde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed in the head by the coldneſſe of the brain, as in a ſtill, drop down upon the vitalls, and corrupt them: ſo they corrupt mens practiſes: Yea, as ſome humours, when they abound in the brain, do ſo obſtruct the paſſage of the animal ſpirits, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30489:103" rendition="simple:additions"/>
they cauſe an Apoplexie, which deprives a man of all ſenſe and motion: So ſome Errours do ſo obſtruct the workings of the Spirit of God, that they deprive a man of all ſpiritual motion. I will preſs that Caution of <hi>Auſtin, Epiſt.</hi> 107. but tenderly, where he bids us take heed, leſt while we plead for freewill amongſt men, we do not loſe the benefit of our prayers; for I do not think all that hold freewill to be of <hi>Seneca</hi>'s minde, <hi>Ep.</hi> 31. that we need not weary God with our prayers, but may make our ſelves happy. Yet there are many corrupt principles which have a more malignant influence upon mens practiſes than they are aware of. Some mens words eat as a gangrene, deſtroying the very life of godlineſſe, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.17, 18. They it ſeems, as ſome of later times, turned the Doctrine of the Reſurrection into an Allegory,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30489:103"/>
interpreting it myſtically; and the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.33. ſpeaking of this very thing, bids them take heed of being deceived, they could not think how ſoon ſuch Doctrine would corrupt their manners: he that thinks he ſhall die like a beaſt, will ſoon be perſwaded to live like a beaſt: wherefore <hi>Tertullian</hi> complains, that corruption in Doctrine was worſe than Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for Perſecution made Martyrs, but Hereſie Apoſtates, <hi>Praeſcript. adv. Haer. c.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Corrupt Opinions do ordinarily diſturb the peace of the Church. It is commonly ſaid indeed, that <hi>opinionum varietas, &amp; opinantium unitas non ſunt</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Difference of judgment ſhould not breed diſcord:</hi> but we too oft finde it otherwiſe: The Apoſtle could eaſily believe, that there were diviſions amongſt the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> becauſe he knew there muſt be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30489:104"/>
Hereſies amongſt them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.18, 19. men, in maintaining their own Opinions againſt others, proceeding for the moſt part to ſtrife of words, and ſo to envy, railings, evil ſurmiſings, perverſe diſputings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.4, 5.</p>
            <p>Now, that we may be able to make a right judgment in this caſe, I ſhall firſt lay down ſome Cautions, then give ſome Directions; and I ſhall begin with the Caution which our Saviour gives us here in the Text, <hi>Judge not according to the appearance.</hi> There was a ſort of Philoſophers indeed of old, which made appearance of the eſſence of truth, but that was becauſe they made man the meaſure of all things, and every thing was true which appeared to any man ſo to be, and ſo there were as many truths as men of different Opinions.</p>
            <p>But moſt men are ready to judge
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:30489:104"/>
that to be only <hi>true,</hi> which ſeems ſo to them: and let a man ſet off any Opinion with a few plauſible words, and many think preſently, it is as a King, againſt whom there is no riſing up, <hi>Prover.</hi> 30.31. It is with Opinions as with men, that which is firſt in its own cauſe is juſt, till another come and finde it out, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.17. Hence it is that moſt men are of the opinion of thoſe that they converſe moſt with, and wonder that any ſhould believe the contrary, or not riſe up to what they ſay; they ordinarily hear their own Opinions urged home, and the Opinions of their adverſaries have but a partial hearing; when, on the other hand, their adverſaries having their own Opinions repreſented to the beſt advantage, wonder as much that every body ſhould not be of their minde. The Papiſts are ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to conceal from the people the Arguments of the Proteſtants, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30489:105" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Sr. <hi>Edwin Sands</hi> tells us, in his <hi>Europae ſpeculum,</hi> that he could not ſet his eye on <hi>Bellarmine</hi>'s Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, or <hi>Gregory de Valentia,</hi> in any ſhop in <hi>Italy,</hi> becauſe theſe men do fairly lay down the Arguments of their Adverſaries.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Vergerius,</hi> he that we read ſo much of in the Story of <hi>Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> came to read the Writings of the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> with an intent to confute them, that he might vindicate himſelf from the ſuſpicion of favouring their cauſe, which had hindered his preferment, he was ſo borne down with the force of truth in them, that he became a <hi>Lutheran</hi> indeed, which he was only ſuſpected to be before. The like is reported concerning <hi>Pighius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some have obſerved, that the ſame word in the Hebrew ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ears, and a pair of ballances, Implying, that we ſhould weigh things with both ears, before we
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:30489:105" rendition="simple:additions"/>
judge. Yet I would not here per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade any to the <hi>Sceptick</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to ſuſpend their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment till they hear every thing which can be ſaid on both ſides, or rather becauſe they think when matters ſeem to be caſt one way, ſomething may poſſibly be ſaid on the other ſide to praeponderate; Neither do I think it neceſſary or poſſible for every one to examine whatever is ſaid or written <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi> in every point. We may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve many truths which we cannot anſwer all objections againſt, and there are many opinions which, are not fit to be <hi>candidates</hi> or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bationers to ſtand for a place in mens minds; only that which I would perſwade men to, is a due pondering of ſuch things as have a probability of truth, according to their capacities, or opportunities and advantages, that what they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they may believe upon good
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:30489:106" rendition="simple:additions"/>
grounds, and with due moderation towards others, that ſo they may not change their opinion as they change their company, and be of the ſame mind with every one which they hear or read maintain any thing with a few fair plauſible words: And that they may not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ail, or at leaſt wonder at every one that is not of their judgement, thinking they muſt needs be either ſtupidly ignorant, or ſelf-condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. It is obvious to every conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring man, that thoſe that are moſt ignorant and unſtudied are moſt confident and cenſorious; <hi>qui pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca conſiderat facilè pronunciat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When thoſe that hear what both ſides have to ſay, though their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are not born down with the force of their adverſaries argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yet they may ſee ſo much in them as may induce them to think that they differ conſcientiouſly, and are not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully blind.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:30489:106" rendition="simple:additions"/>Secondly, Let us take heed upon what grounds we judge any thing to be either true or falſe; becauſe many things ſtand upon the ſame foundation; and upon the ſame ground that we admit or refuſe one thing, we may admit or refuſe many others, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.2. The Apoſtle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeches the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> that they be not ſoon ſhaken in their mind, or troubled either by Word, or Spirit, or Letter, as from them; the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular thing whereof he warns them, had no great evill in it, but he was afraid of the means whereby they went about to ſeduce them, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. <hi>Let no man deceive you by any means.</hi> If they did by theſe means perſwade them to this, they might by the ſame means perſwade them to things of more dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence; if any ſhould endeavour to impoſe upon us ſome harmeleſs opinion, and to perſwade hereto, tell us it was revealed to him, or gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:30489:107" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in to him of God, if we believe him upon this ground, he may as eaſily preſs upon us the fouleſt er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours; if we admit any thing upon Apoſtolical tradition, how do we know what may be obtruded upon us under that pretence. Many urge their opinions upon us becauſe they are in ſo many words in Scripture, if this be ſufficient to draw us to their beliefs, we may as well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that God hath hands, and eyes, and ears, and ſo turn <hi>Anthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pomorphites,</hi> or almoſt any thing: So others cry out when we would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend ſome truths to them as the <hi>Macedonians</hi> of old <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; where do you find any ſuch thing in the Scripture? Shew me it in ſo many words; tell not me of infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences and conſequences; when if they will reject any thing upon this ground, they may reject the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:30489:107" rendition="simple:additions"/>Doubtleſs, There are many among the <hi>Papiſts</hi> wiſer men than to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve many of the dotages of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> but that admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting things upon the Authority of the Church, whatever is recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to them thereby, that is, by the Pope or a Council, muſt be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, how repugnant ſoever it be either to ſenſe or reaſon.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let us take heed of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon the authority of men, however eminent for Learning and Godlineſs; theſe indeed have a great advantage for finding out Truth, and they may be of much uſe to us for informing us thereof; but it is one thing to <hi>teach,</hi> and another thing to <hi>dictate; Debetur conſulenti reverentia, cum non debetur fides affirmanti.</hi> If a man tell me what he believes, and upon what ground he believes it, if his ground be an in artificial Argument, or if it be a clear divine teſtimony, he
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:30489:108" rendition="simple:additions"/>
makes his own knowledge mine, and I know it as well as he; but if a man dictate a thing only to me, and tell me it is truth, I muſt not believe it preſently becauſe he ſaith it. And though we are to have a reverent eſteem of the judgment of thoſe that are learned and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet it is no ſin for us to ſuſpend our aſſent thereto, till we ſee more reaſon for it, than meerly becauſe it is their judgement; for God doth many times leave ſuch men for our trial, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.1, &amp;c. and the devill makes choice of ſuch Inſtruments for his own credit, <hi>quarit diabolus ab iis ornari,</hi> as one ſaith; and he could get even into <hi>Peter, Mat.</hi> 16.23. The Man of God, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 13.7. withſtood the offer of <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> but was ſeduced by the old Prophet, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. Thoſe that have not been prevailed with by all the Arguments of learned men, have been eaſily miſled by ſuch as have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:30489:108"/>
been of great eſteem for godlineſs. How much hurt was done by <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> and <hi>Origen,</hi> men famous for Learning and Piety, we may ſee in <hi>Vincentius Lerinenſis,</hi> c. 23, 24. So <hi>Priſcillian,</hi> being a man of quick parts, great reading, much fluency of ſpeech, of a noble family, free from covetouſneſs, yet as free from laviſh profuſeneſs, drew multitudes of all ſorts after him, <hi>Sulpitius Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verus, Lib.</hi> 2. And as for learned men, it is true which one obſerves of them, that they ordinarily judge of the truth and waies of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that kind of Learning which they moſt excell in, reducing every thing to the trial of that which they addict themſelves to the ſtudy of; like the Muſician, that being asked what the ſoul was, defined it <hi>Harmony:</hi> So amongſt thoſe that addict themſelves to the ſearch of <hi>Antiquity,</hi> many times that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of <hi>Tertullian</hi> is true, <hi>De
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:30489:109"/>
vetandis virgin.</hi> cap. 1. <hi>Conſuetudo adverſus veritatem defenditur;</hi> a Tradition, or ancient Cuſtome is of more account with them than a long neglected truth or duty; and if they bend their ſtudies to Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, or School Divinity, we may complain with the ſame Father, <hi>Haereſes à philoſophia ſuboruantur. praeſcrip. adv. haer. c.</hi> 7. and Divinity muſt be cramped to fit their School nicities, and philoſophical notions. Such as delight in the ſtudy of the Jewiſh or Oriental Learning, how do they accommodate their Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to their dull Rabinical notions, if not to the Fables of their <hi>Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mud;</hi> like the men that came from <hi>Judea, Act.</hi> 15.1. Doubtleſs, the converted Gentiles were glad they had ſuch to conſult with, to whom the Oracles of God had been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and with whom Chriſt and his Apoſtles had converſed, and they preſently call them to the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:30489:109"/>
obſervation of their Circumciſion, whereon they ſo much doated. Far be it from me to ſpeak this to the contempt of Learning, which I value much (though I poſſeſs but little) knowing how good an uſe may be made of it; yet it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to obſerve how ordinarily men do abound in their own ſence, and how prone they are, that they may beget an high eſteem in others of ſuch Learning as they are moſt in love with themſelves, to make it ſeem more ſerviceable and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry upon all occaſions than indeed it is.</p>
            <p>I will conclude this Caution with that of <hi>Tertullian de praeſcript. c.</hi> 3. <hi>Ex perſonis probamus fidem an ex fide perſonas?</hi> Shall we judge of opinions by men, or of men by opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Let us take heed our Judgement be not perverted by Paſſion or Intereſt; It is true, the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:30489:110" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Underſtanding moves the Will <hi>morally,</hi> as hath already been ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but the Will moves the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <hi>phyſically, Aquin.</hi> 1 <hi>a. q.</hi> 82. <hi>Art.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> As a King followeth the advice of his Council, but yet choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his Council himſelf, and it may be ſo regulates their Debates, that they ſhall not take into conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, or at leaſt not throughly diſcuſs, thoſe things which he hath no mind to hear: So the Will doth determine the Mind to the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration almoſt of what it pleaſeth. Hence the Scripture complains of ſuch as <hi>will</hi> not underſtand, but walk on in darkneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.5. and are <hi>willingly</hi> ignorant, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.5. For though the Underſtanding cannot refuſe its aſſent to ſuch truths as are evidently demonſtrated thereto, as <hi>Scotus</hi> hath obſerved, <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>dist.</hi> 7. <hi>q.</hi> 1. Yet the Will and corrupt affections ſo interpoſe to hinder the acceſs of thoſe things to the Underſtanding
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:30489:110"/>
which might rightly inform it, that it cannot make a true impartial Judgement; as <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour complained of it as the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs of great men, that they could not know the Truth, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſuch about them, as would let nothing come to their ears but what might make for themſelves and their Intereſt: So corrupt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections prevent thoſe reaſonings of the mind which might reſtrain them from that which they have a ſtrong propenſion to. Hence it is that Seducers and Impoſtors have prevailed ſo much by their cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly deviſed Fables, ſuited to mens corrupt luſts and carnal Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts: as <hi>Mahomet</hi> and the Papiſts, of whom we may ſay as <hi>Tully</hi> of <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> It is a wonder they can look upon one another without laughter to think of their abſurd ridiculous opinions, but that they know as one of them blaſphemouſly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:30489:111" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſaid how much ſuch Fables profit them; and ſo certainly many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile their underſtandings into a belief of them. The Apoſtle 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18. ſpeaks of ſome, who through the luſts of the fleſh allured thoſe who had eſcaped them that live in errour: That is, through the luſts of their hearers or followers, fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Doctrine ſo as it might give the largeſt indulgence to their luſts, an account of which we have in <hi>Irenaeus, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1. Men heaping up Teachers to themſelves after their own luſts, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Mic.</hi> 2.11. and even good mens judgements may be ſwayed ſometimes by Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt or Paſſion, I might give an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance hereof in ſome of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, in the matter of compulſion by the Magiſtrate in ſpiritual things, we find that thoſe who lived under heathen or <hi>Arian</hi> Emperours were utterly againſt it, becauſe then it was againſt their intereſt, as
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:30489:111" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Tertullian ad Scapulam, c.</hi> 2. <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Inſtit. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 20. Indeed he wrote his Inſtitutions in his old Age under <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> to whom he dedicates them, but he had known ſomething of the effects of force in matters of Religion in <hi>Diocle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> time, whoſe fury he had with much difficulty eſcaped. The like might be obſerved of <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> and <hi>Gregory Nazianzen:</hi> But <hi>Auſtin</hi> was of another mind after he had ſeen the inſolence of the <hi>Donatists,</hi> and the effect of the Magiſtrates power in reſtraining thereof, <hi>Retract. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5. I am apt to beleeve we ſhall find many amongſt our ſelves which will not continue long of the ſame mind in this very thing, but ſome will be for it which have formerly been againſt it, and others againſt it which have formerly been for it; and I am not ſo void of charity, as to think all thoſe whom I ſee ſo
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:30489:112" rendition="simple:additions"/>
quick at changing their judgements in many things as times change, to be ſelf-condemned, or to go againſt clear convictions, but their intereſt baffles their judgement, and change of times hath as great an influence upon their minds, as change of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath upon weak bodies. But Truth is the ſame in all Ages, and in all places, and is not like our <hi>Almanacks,</hi> to be changed every year, or calculated peculiarly for one <hi>Meridian.</hi> And how Paſſion perverts mens judgements is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from the difference that is betwixt mens Polemical or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſial writings, and their devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or ſuch as they write in cool bloud. <hi>Rivet</hi> ſhews how much <hi>Bellarmine</hi> differs from himſelf about the Scriptures, <hi>Iſagoge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad Script. cap.</hi> 25. Men when they deal with their Adverſaries, whet their Pens ſo ſharp that they prick their own fingers; or they are like
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:30489:112"/>
Phyſicians, that to cure their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients of one diſeaſe caſt them into a worſe; to recover them from an Ague caſt them into a Feaver, which they know not how to cure; or to cure a Feaver, take away ſo much bloud that they diſpoſe their Patients to a Conſumption, or Convulſions. Thus <hi>Auſtin</hi> in vindicating the liberty of Mans Will againſt the <hi>Manichees,</hi> gave advantage to <hi>Pelagius,</hi> with whom he was more troubled than with the former. Thus <hi>Dionyſius Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrinus,</hi> whileſt he zealouſly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the <hi>Sabbellians,</hi> gave advantage to the <hi>Arians.</hi> Whether did <hi>Illyricus</hi> run in the buſineſs of ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal ſin, while he oppoſed the Papiſts? And what advantage did <hi>Luther</hi> give to <hi>Iſlebius Agrioola</hi> in the buſineſs of Juſtification: and it is an ordinary obſervation of many, that the oppoſition of our firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers to the general aſſend
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:30489:113"/>
maintained by the Papiſts, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported them to another extreme in the buſineſs of Faith; though I do much approve of the opinion of a Learned man concerning this thing, that thoſe good men ſpake much their own experience, God ordinarily giving them aſſurance whom he employed in more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſervices, and who were to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter greater trialls, which he doth not ordinarily give to thoſe who are not put upon ſuch ſervice, it being his way to proportion his comforts to his Peoples trials and temptations, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. See <hi>Arrowſmiths Tactica ſacra, l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>ſ.</hi> 5. I could eaſily give many inſtances in the moſt Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men of former and latter times, of ſeveral opinions and perſwaſions, of the influence that mens Paſſions and Intereſts have upon their Judgements, hindering the ſight thereof, as a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:30489:113"/>
Cataract or ſuffuſion hinders the ſight of the eye.</p>
            <p>I come now to the directions which we muſt obſerve if we will make a right judgement of Opinions or Doctrines. And,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Let us labour <hi>to have the Word of God dwelling richly in us in all wiſdom, Col.</hi> 3.16. It is not enough to be acquainted with the Letter of the Scripture, but we muſt ſtudy the Sence of it, and be able to find out ſuch truths as are not in ſo many words therein ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. Ignorance of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures was the cauſe of the Saddu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces errour concerning the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, though the Doctrine of the Reſurrection was not ſo obvious to every one in the place which our Saviour cited for the proof of it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.29.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Let us dayly apply our ſelves unto God by Prayer; by humble addreſſes of our ſelves to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:30489:114"/>
him, therein we may get more than by reading, or ſtudy; our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings as well as our Wills dayly ſtand in need of aſſiſting Grace. <hi>Homer</hi> doth ſay, That men depend dayly upon God for the guiding of their minds. See <hi>Ludov<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Vives, in lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de civitat. Dei. c.</hi> 8. It is part of the Spirits work to guide us into all truth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.13. though it do not immediately dictate to us what is truth, nor by any extraordinary Revelation diſcover any new ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to us, yet he is a Spirit of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to make us quick of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the fear of the Lord, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.2, 3. and to enable us to judge of ſpiritual things, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2, 15. <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.40.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let us labour to be well acquainted with the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Truths of Religion, which will be as ſo many <hi>phari,</hi> or towers, to guide us ſafe betwixt the rocks of errour; and with ſome of which
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:30489:114"/>
moſt Errours are ſome way or other inconſiſtent.</p>
            <p>Four<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hly, Let us labour for a ſince<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e honeſt heart; this conduces more to the keeping men right in their judgments, than the learning of the Schooles, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.8. Though men have not ſo much cunning as others, yet, if their hearts be right toward God, they ſhall not ſo ſoon be miſled; if mens hearts be not ſincere, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing elſe will help them: as Chriſt came into the world, <hi>that thoſe that ſee might be made blinde, and that thoſe that ſee not might ſee,</hi> John 9.39. <hi>He was ſet, not only for the riſe, but for the fall alſo of many in Iſrael,</hi> Luke 2.34. So the Scriptures are <hi>a light to</hi> the <hi>feet, and a lanthorn to</hi> the <hi>pathes,</hi> of thoſe who in ſincerity make uſe of them for guiding their feet in the paths of uprightneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.105. But if we make uſe of them only for ſatisfying our curioſity, or to paſſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:30489:115"/>
our cenſure upon them, they will be rather a ſtumbling block, than a light to us. <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, He is not affraid to affirm, that the Scriptures are ſo ordered or diſpoſed by the will of God, that Hereticks may be miſled by them, <hi>adv. Haer.</hi> 39. And if we pray to God for further illumination, only that we may <hi>know,</hi> and take no care to <hi>practiſe</hi> what we know, God will not ſo far ſatisfie our curioſity. They are thoſe that <hi>do the will of God,</hi> that ſhall know what Doctrine is of God, and what of men, <hi>John</hi> 7.17. There were three things that did ſo much advance <hi>Davids</hi> knowledge, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9. 1. The Word of God was with him, that is, he had it by him to read on, and conſult with, according to the charge given. <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.19. <hi>verſ.</hi> 98. 2. He meditated thereon, <hi>ver.</hi> 99. 3. He kept it, or practiſed what he read, <hi>ver.</hi> 100.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:30489:115" rendition="simple:additions"/>I might now, as ſome do, lay down ſome Characters for the tryal of Doctrines, whereby men may know what comes neareſt the truth; as that which doth moſt promote Godlineſs, and that which doth moſt detract from the creature, and give to God, is moſt like to come neareſt the truth. But I will not much urge theſe, and otherlike, becauſe however theſe may be true Characters, yet they are not ſo evident, and there is as much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie what doth moſt advance Holineſs, and the Grace and power of Jeſus Chriſt, as about any other <hi>mediums</hi> for the clearing of truth, and all proof ſhould be made, <hi>per notiora,</hi> by thoſe things that are more evident than that which we would prove.</p>
            <p>Secondly, We ſhould judg aright of Actions: and that, <list>
                  <item>1. Our own Actions.</item>
                  <item>2. Other mens.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:30489:116"/>We ſhould judge aright of our Actions, 1. Beforehand in our intention; that we may know what our duty is, <hi>It is the wiſdome of the prudent, to underſtand his way,</hi> Prov. 14.8. It is not ſufficient, that we do things in the ſimplicity of our hearts, as thoſe followed <hi>Abſalom,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.11. the will of God being the rule of our actions, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.17. not our own erroneous conſciences. And our ignorance will not altogether excuſe us in what we do againſt the command of God, no not at all, if we be wholly ſupine, and careleſſe to informe our ſelves of the will of God. <hi>Paul thought verily</hi> he <hi>ought</hi> to do many things againſt the name of Jeſus, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.9. yet this miſtake of his made his ſin only pardonable, and he confeſſes himſelf the chief of ſinners for it, 1 <hi>Timoth.</hi> 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.2. <hi>poſt factum;</hi> or in the reflection on our actions, we muſt judge
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:30489:116"/>
righteous judgement: It was the ſin of the Jewes, that none did reflect upon their actions, and conſider what they had done, <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.7. which we are to underſtand, not only <hi>phyſically,</hi> what actions they had done, but <hi>morally,</hi> of what nature the actions were, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.13. the <hi>guilt</hi> of ſin is taken away by juſtification, the <hi>blot</hi> or ſtain of it by Sanctification, but the <hi>fault</hi> is not taken away till Repentance, and in a moral ſence a man perſiſts in the act of ſin till he repent of it. <hi>Primus felicitatis gradus eſt non delinquere, ſecundus delicta cognoſcere, Cyprian, Epiſt.</hi> 55. next to innocency Repentance is the greateſt happineſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We ſhould judge a right of other mens actions, not that we ſhould be buſie-bodies, in other mens matters, or ſevere <hi>Cato's,</hi> cenſuring every thing which belongs not to us. But ſometimes
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:30489:117" rendition="simple:additions"/>
we are concerned to make a right judgement of other mens actions, 1. That we may not partake of their ſin, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. by approving that which is evil, 2 <hi>John</hi> 10, 11.2. That we may not condemn them, and caſt them out of our charity without cauſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.3. I know there is nothing doth more trouble one that is partaker of the divine nature that <hi>dwells in love,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.16. than to know or hear any thing of another, that may hinder the exeriſe of their love. There remains indeed alwaies a love of <hi>benevolence</hi> towards them, but it abates of our love of <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency,</hi> when we apprehend them guilty of any thing that is evil; and it is in it ſelf a ſin to be angry with our brother without cauſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.22.</p>
            <p>Now, that we may judge aright of actions, I muſt proceed in the ſame method as in the former caſe: <list>
                  <item>1. Give you ſome Cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ions:</item>
                  <item>2. Some Directions.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:30489:117" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let us here again take heed of judging of actions accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the appearance, but examine the Principles &amp; ends of them, with other circumſtances. Many times, at firſt view, mens actions ſeem very unwarrantable, till the buſineſs be fully underſtood, and till we ſee for what ends, upon what grounds, by what neceſſity forced thereto, and upon what occaſions men undertake ſuch things. It was the caſe of the <hi>Reubonites, Joſh.</hi> 22.12. but when their brethren underſtood their grounds and intentions, they were very well ſatisfied, <hi>verſ.</hi> 30. So many men do oft make very fair pretences of ſuch things as are moſt remote from their intentions. <hi>Judas</hi> ſeemed to be of a very publique ſpirit, and one that aimed at doing good, <hi>John</hi> 12.6. but there was ſomewhat elſe at the bottome, which lay out of mans ſight. But though <hi>counſel in the heart of man, be
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:30489:118" rendition="simple:additions"/>
as deep water, a man of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding will draw it out,</hi> Prov. 20.5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let us not judge of Actions by mens Examples.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Not of moſt men, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.21 we muſt not follow a <hi>multitude</hi> to do evil. The broad way, wherein moſt walk, leads to deſtruction, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.13. Nor of <hi>great</hi> men, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.48. It is the Doctrine that Mr. <hi>Rob. Bolton</hi> inſiſts on in his aſſize Sermon, on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26. that <hi>great men are ſeldome good.</hi> No, nor alwayes of the <hi>best</hi> men; their examples, if evil, are moſt dangerous, becauſe we are moſt apt to follow them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.13. but they muſt be followed only ſo far as they follow Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. yea further, good actions of good men are not alwaies to be imitated, as it is a great error in <hi>Policy,</hi> for men to undertake things becauſe they have ſeen others do them before them; as <hi>Pompey</hi> would ſay, <hi>Scylla potuit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>go non potero?</hi> Scylla <hi>did ſuch i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:30489:118"/>
thing, and why may not I?</hi> never conſidering the advantage of parts and abilities, opportunity, popula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which one man may have more than another. So it is a great miſtake in <hi>Morality,</hi> that what was lawfull and juſtifiable in another, we may venture to do, when that which is lawfull in one may be ſinfull in another, when there is not the ſame principles, ends, occaſions. And hence it is that <hi>Precedents</hi> get ſo much credit and authority, that they paſs for a <hi>Law,</hi> and men argue <hi>à facto ad jus.</hi> The Diſciples, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.54. pleaded the example of <hi>Elias,</hi> for what they deſired, when our Saviour intimates by his anſwer, that they were of a quite different ſpirit from <hi>Elias,</hi> and deſired fire from Heaven upon farre lower principles than <hi>Elias;</hi> his was pure zeal, theirs mixed with the baſe alley of ambition, and revenge, ſo <hi>Amos</hi> 6.5. thoſe <hi>Epicures</hi> plead
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:30489:119" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the example of <hi>David</hi> for their juſtification, not conſidering that the end of <hi>David</hi> in the uſe of Muſick, and ſinging, was to lift up his heart in the ſervice of God, theirs only to pleaſe their own luſts. So many plead the example of good men for what they do, and for the liberty which in many things they take to themſelves, not conſidering that while they do the ſame things, not on the ſame grounds, nor for the ſame ends, they may ſin, in that which others do lawfully. Again, that is lawfull at one time which is not lawfull at another; as Firſt, In caſe of offence, compare <hi>Act.</hi> 16.3. with <hi>Galat.</hi> 2.3. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.27. with <hi>ver.</hi> 28. <hi>quod non expedit,</hi> &amp;c. that which is not expedient, ſo long as it is not expedient, is not lawfull. Secondly, Some things which are our duty, or elſe unlawfull for the moſt part, may at ſome time be diſpenſed with. What commands
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:30489:119" rendition="simple:additions"/>
are diſpenſible, and in what caſes, would be too great a task here to examine; but that ſome commands are ſo, and in ſome caſes, is evident from <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.2, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall object, That <hi>We muſt not do evil that good may come of it:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The beſt Anſwer which I have in readineſs hereto is, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the goodneſs of the end may legitimate the means, ſo as it may ceaſe to be evil, ſuppoſing it to be in ſuch things as are not <hi>intrinſically</hi> and in their own nature evill, and <hi>prohibita quia mala,</hi> as ſome diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh. Theſe things, though they are not to be denyed, are to be tenderly preſſed. He that deſires to ſee more of this may conſult <hi>Rivet</hi> on <hi>Geneſis, Exercitat.</hi> 108. and on the <hi>Fourth Commandment, S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de Legibus, lib.</hi> 2.14, 15. Mr. <hi>Baxter, of Infidelity, Advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, propoſ.</hi> 13, 14, 15. Thirdly, Take need of judging of actions
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:30489:120"/>
according to ſucceſſe. <hi>God may ſhine upon the counſel of the wicked,</hi> Job 10.3. <hi>The proud may be accounted the happy men, and thoſe that tempt God delivered,</hi> Mal. 3.15. God hath taught all amongſt us this Doctrine effectually. Men indeed are very apt to judge of love and hatred by what is before them, <hi>Luke.</hi> 13.1, &amp;c. <hi>John</hi> 9.2. <hi>Acts</hi> 28.4. <hi>Faelix ac prosperum ſcetus virtus vocatur,</hi> Sen. But the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had right on their ſides, againſt the <hi>Benjamites,</hi> and a great advantage of multitude, yet they fell twice before them, <hi>Judges</hi> 20. So God delivered <hi>Judah</hi> into the hands of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who ſlew them with a rage reaching up to heaven, yet there were among the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſins againſt the Lord, and the fierce wrath of God was upon them, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9, 10, 11. I muſt give the ſame Directions here that I gave in the former caſe, therefore,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us labour to acquaint our
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:30489:120"/>
ſelves with the Word of God: there are not only <hi>credenda,</hi> but <hi>agenda;</hi> as well what we ſhould <hi>do,</hi> as what we ſhould <hi>believe:</hi> This was <hi>David</hi>'s counſellor, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.24. beſides the expreſs rules which are there given us, for the directing of our wayes, we may (if we be well acquainted therewith) be able to inferre one thing from another, and argue <hi>à pari ratione,</hi> and ſo know what to do in like caſes, as we find in the Word of God, as our Saviour argues, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.3.7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us pray for the guidance and direction of the Spirit of God, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 25.12. <hi>What man is he that feareth the Lord, him ſhall he guide in the way that he ſhall chuſe:</hi> that is, in the way that he <hi>ſhould</hi> chooſe; that which is ſpoken <hi>de facto,</hi> or of what men do, being oft underſtood <hi>de debito,</hi> or what men ſhould do, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.8. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5.4. God leads us by his good ſpirit,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:30489:121" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.10. not by dictating to us, as to <hi>Philip, Acts</hi> 8.29. though I will not deny, but the Spirit may ſometimes powerfully determine a man to ſome particular act. We read in the life of Mr. <hi>Dod,</hi> that he was ſtrongly inclined one night to go to his neighbours houſe, and knew not why, but God thereby ſaved a mans life. So we read of one <hi>Aventroot,</hi> who, in very old age, againſt the perſwaſion of his friends, went from <hi>Utrect</hi> in the Low-Countreys, to <hi>Madrid</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> to tell the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> that the Pope was <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and to perſwade him to deſtroy him, for which he was burnt. Theſe are extraordinary caſes, and do not favour the ordinary pretences of <hi>Enthuſiaſme,</hi> eſpecially in things contrary to the Word of God, ſee <hi>Voetites, de probationibus ſpirituum, p.</hi> 2 <hi>ap.</hi> 1124. where you have the forementioned Story, and what we
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:30489:121" rendition="simple:additions"/>
are to judge in ſuch caſes. Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily the Spirit directs Chriſtians, by filling them with the knowledg of Gods will, in all wiſdome and ſpiritual underſtanding: though it may ſometimes awaken conſcience to be as a voice behinde us, ſaying, this is the way, walk in it, when we turn to the right hand, or to the left, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.21. or direct us to ſuch places of Scripture as may be for our turn, or beſt ſerve our purpoſe, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> to <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.13. <hi>Junius</hi> to <hi>John</hi> 1. ſee <hi>Auſtine</hi>'s Confeſſions, <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 11. and <hi>Junius</hi> his life written by himſelf. He that deſires to read more concerning divine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſes, or the voyce of Providence, may conſult <hi>Geo. Wither</hi>'s cordial Confection, <hi>p.</hi> 12. and <hi>Edw. Gee.</hi> of the Right and Original of Magiſtrates, <hi>cap.</hi> 3. to whom I had rather referre, than determine any thing in ſo nice a point.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let us here alſo labour for an
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:30489:122"/>
honeſt, ſincere heart, otherwiſe it is as hard to judge of Actions, as of Opinions. Corrupt affections will blinde the judgement, and turn <hi>deſire</hi> into <hi>opinion,</hi> ſo as a man ſhall believe that to be true which he deſires to be true. Hence it is, that <hi>every mans way is right in his own eyes,</hi> Prov. 16.2. Paſſions and Luſts endeavour to draw the judgement on their own ſide, that ſo they may not be controled or interrupted thereby, <hi>Reynolds, on the Paſſions, cap.</hi> 8. And for this cauſe, ſome <hi>Philoſophers</hi> have not thought young men, eſpecially ſuch as were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to youthfull luſts, to be fit for the ſtudy of <hi>Ethicks, Wendelini Philoſoph. Moral. l.</hi> 1.0.1.</p>
            <p>But further, when men come to enquire of God with their idols in their hearts, he will anſwer them according to their Idols, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.4, 7. that is, When men (like young people, who ask their friends
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:30489:122"/>
conſent in marriage, but are reſolved beforehand what to do, whether their friends will conſent or no) pretend to inquire the mind of God, and have beforehand fixed their deſires, if not their reſolutions: God will anſwer ſuch to their coſt. The Jews pretended a deſire and willingneſs to know the minde of God, and to be ruled thereby, but they had before reſolved to go down into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and he tells them what ſhould befall them, if they went thither, the ſword and famine which they fled from ſhould follow cloſe after them, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 42. read that Chapter throughout. So <hi>Ahab</hi> had a minde to go to <hi>Ramoth Gilead,</hi> yet he would enquire of God, whether he ſhould go; God ſuffers the Devil by his Prophets to ſeduce him to go thither, to his ruine, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22. If we enquire of God, it muſt be with an honeſt heart, and ſincere Reſolution to follow his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:30489:123" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Counſel; God will not be mocked, we muſt ſeek to God, <hi>an licet,</hi> not <hi>ut liceat,</hi> whether a thing be lawfull or no, not that it may be lawfull.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Let us take heed of raſhneſſe, and precipitancy. <hi>With the well adviſed is wiſdome,</hi> Proverb. 13.10. <hi>We muſt ponder the paths of our feet,</hi> Prov. 4.26. We are not of ſuch preſent and comprehenſive under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, as to make ſudden Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions. We ſee how oft we are put to change our Reſolutions, and make them give place to ſecond &amp; wiſer thoughts. Gods immutabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is an Argument of his perfection, and is founded in his omniſciency, his perfect underſtanding of all things by one ſingle view, directing him to ſuch purpoſes as are not capable of any perfective alteration; only <hi>conſideration</hi> muſt not take up the time that ſhould be ſpent in <hi>execution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Let us conſult with thoſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:30489:123"/>
who are wholly unconcerned in what we would judge of, ſuch are like to make the beſt judgment. How doth <hi>David</hi> paſs ſentence on himſelf, when a caſe was repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him, only in <hi>theſi,</hi> not as his own, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.5, 6. So the Jews, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.41. but change the perſons, and they are of <hi>Ploydon</hi>'s minde, That the caſe is alterred, fo doth Intereſt corrupt mens mindes: We ſee dayly proof of this; hence the common ſaying, That a good Arbitrator muſt diſpleaſe both parties, becauſe intereſt makes them both think their own caſe right, when a third perſon ſees, that both muſt yield. Hence ſo many complaints of Oppreſſion, Intereſt makes both Plaintiffe and Defendant think himſelf wronged. Hence is it ſo hard to finde a good <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> if he ſtand in the croud, affection to cauſes, or parties ſwayes him, if he ſtand too farre
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:30489:124" rendition="simple:additions"/>
off, he cannot ſee well what is done.</p>
            <p>Finally, Hence it comes to paſs, that the preſent age ſeldome judges right, but the ſucceeding age muſt judge of the actions of the age going before, moſt men being ſome way concerned in publick affairs. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.30.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, We muſt judge aright concerning <hi>perſons.</hi> I ſhall not here ſpeak of judging our ſelves, having elſewhere ſaid ſomething of it. Now I ſhall ſpeak only, of our judgement concerning others; we are not indeed raſhly to condemn others, this is the judgement which Chriſt forbids, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.1. Neither are we to uſurp a peremptory judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning mens final eſtate, yet there is a private judgement of Prudence that we may, yea, muſt paſs upon men.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That we may know how to carry our ſelves towards them; to ſome we owe only a common cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:30489:124" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to others brotherly kindneſs, or a more entire affection, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17. Some are to be carefully avoided, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. Some there are of whom we may hope well, yet are to carry our ſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them as if we had a ſuſpition of them, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.14, 15.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That we may <hi>beware of men, Mat.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Paul,</hi> amongſt other dangers that he was in, reckons up <hi>falſe brethren,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.4. Theſe indeed are the moſt wretched ſort of men, and an abhorring to all fleſh. <hi>Perditiſſimi hominis eſt illum fallere, qui nou deceptus eſſet niſi credidiſſet.</hi> Abundance of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances I could eaſily give, of thoſe who have very much ſuffered by their credulity, and putting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves too much into their power, who have proved perfidious to them. Chriſt would not truſt all that truſted him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.24. And ſome think it was <hi>Alexander</hi> that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:30489:125"/>
was like to loſe his life at <hi>Epheſus, Act.</hi> 19.33. that did <hi>Paul</hi> ſo much harm, that he warns <hi>Timothy</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of him, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14, 15.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That we may know how to eſteem them. The Saints ſhould be the moſt excellent perſons in our account, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.3. <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.26. There is indeed a civill reſpect due to men according to the place wherein God hath ſet them, to keep up the authority of their place, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Act.</hi> 23.5. that authority which is neceſſary for preſerving of Order in the Societies of men, may not be betrayed to contempt, <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. ad Traſimundum. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. But yet we ſhould have a more real re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to thoſe who are the children of God, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.4. <hi>Ingo,</hi> King of the <hi>Venedi</hi> in <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> made a great Feaſt, to which he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited many of his Nobles, who were then <hi>Pagans,</hi> and many alſo of his meaner Subjects who were
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:30489:125"/>
Chriſtians; the Nobles he fed without with the meaneſt and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt Diet, the Chriſtians, who were but mean men, he ſumptuouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained at his own Table. <hi>Magd. Cent.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 2. though theſe are not thought worthy of the World, <hi>the World is not worthy of them, Heb.</hi> 11.38.</p>
            <p>Now, that we may judge aright of Perſons,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Let us not judge by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port; It was foretold of Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.3. that he ſhould not judge according to the hearing of the ear. <hi>Fama mendax,</hi> Fame is a lyar; See how much <hi>David</hi> ſuffered hereby, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.9. and <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.27. and <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 21.24. <hi>Tertullian</hi> complains in his <hi>Apology</hi> how much the Chriſtians of old ſuffered hereby; and their Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries were willing to believe falſe reports of them, that ſo they might with the greater ſhow of reaſon
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:30489:126" rendition="simple:additions"/>
malign and perſecute them. <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt de nobis quae non probantur, &amp; nolunt inquiri ne probentur non eſſe quae malunt credidiſſe, cap.</hi> 2. becauſe it was againſt the Law to have Virgins ſtrangled, <hi>Tiberius</hi> would firſt have them defloured, that ſo they might according to Law be ſtrangled; it is too much to abuſe Chriſtians as <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but firſt Fame muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a rape upon their names, and then they may be dealt with as the vileſt perſons; let them but be made Schiſmaticks or ſedirious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and no puniſhment will be too much for them: The poor Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants at <hi>Paris</hi> muſt firſt be accuſed of a Conſpiracy againſt the King, and then butchered by thouſands without mercy. I have ſometimes wondered what the bloudy Papiſts could ſay in excuſe of that cruell Maſſacre, till I read their pretence for it in <hi>Eſtourneaus</hi> continuation of <hi>Surius,</hi> 4. 48. What ſtrange things
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:30489:126"/>
were reported concerning the meetings of the Chriſtians of old! How they put out their Candles when they had peformed their reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ſervices, and fell to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of all manner of abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Tert. Apol. c.</hi> 7. And have not the ſame reports paſſed for currant amongſt many concerning others of latter daies? But we may ſay as the ſame Father, <hi>Cap.</hi> 39. <hi>Cum probi cum boni coeunt: cum pii cum caſti congregantur: non eſt factio dicenda, ſed curia.</hi> I ſhould wiſh thoſe that entertain ſuch reports of others no worſe puniſhment of their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity than the <hi>Italian</hi> Friers, who having heard that <hi>Geneva</hi> was a place where any thing was tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, robbed their own Covents, and brought away their booty to <hi>Geneva,</hi> pretending a converſion to the reformed Religion, and think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereupon to find Sanctuary there: Who when they came there
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:30489:127"/>
were preſently advanced to the Gibbet, which made them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain pitifully of their wrong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, <hi>See Europae ſpeculum,</hi> 170. where you have alſo the Story of a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gallant that loſt his head there upon a like occaſion. What horrid reports have the Papiſts raiſed concerning this Nation for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly? Yea, what ſtrange Stories do <hi>Calixtus, Hoornbeeck, Mareſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, &amp;c.</hi> yet tell? What ſtrange pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices have many conceived againſt others? Of whom we may ſay as <hi>Tertullian, c.</hi> 1. <hi>Si ſciant odiſſe non poterant;</hi> If they knew them, they could not hate them. How many have by Fame been repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented as men of corrupt Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and proud and turbulent ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, to be avoided as thoſe that have the Plague or Leproſie? Whom we have found when we have come to converſe with them to be ſober, humble, conſcientious Chriſtians.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:30489:127"/>
               <hi>Nemo niſi per amicitiam cognoſcitur;</hi> And if any object, that we have not any other way to know many but by report. I anſwer, If we have no opportunity to converſe with them, we have the leſs occaſion to judge any thing of them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Do not for the faults of ſome condemn all; A learned man (Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> in his <hi>Religio me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dici,</hi>) complains of this piece of injuſtice, whereby whole Nations are accuſed of thoſe crimes which, ſome therein have been found guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of, many concluding from a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in ſome, an habit in all. Thus it falls out when men of quite different principles and practiſes fall under one common name or compellation, whatever is held or done by one is many times charged upon all that are diſtinguiſhed by the ſame name. Thus of old what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever <hi>Carpocrates</hi> and his followers did, was charged upon the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:30489:128"/>
in general, becauſe they went under the name of Chriſtians among the Heathens, <hi>Euſebius, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 8. What the Proteſtants have ſuffered from the Papiſts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account, becauſe ſo many Sects are included in the common notion of Proteſtants, I need not ſtand here to ſhew. I will only give one inſtance more: What abominable errours are charged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Independents</hi> of <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by a late Author? <hi>Alexander Roſſe</hi> is his <hi>view of the Religions of Europe, Sect.</hi> 12. as far remote from the judgement of the generality of thoſe who come within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of that Name, as <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is from <hi>Europe;</hi> their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings againſt the abettors of thoſe opinions, and the Writings of <hi>Hooker, Cotton, Norton, Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard,</hi> &amp;c. ſufficiently teſtifying their abhorrency of them. I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to give like inſtances nearer
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:30489:128"/>
home, and deſire only thoſe whom it may concern, to conſider how they ſhould reſent it, if a <hi>Papist</hi> ſhould charge upon them all the opinions of <hi>Anabaptiſts, Socinians, Weigelians, Arminians,</hi> becauſe they are <hi>Protestants,</hi> and have made a Seceſſion from the Church of <hi>Rome; And whatever ye would that men ſhould do unto you, do you even ſo unto them, for this is the Law and the Prophets, Mat.</hi> 7.12.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let us not judge of men according to a bare outward profeſſion, though there is a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of charity, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.7. to which men have as much right, as to any thing they call their own, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.7. yet this doth not deprive us of the uſe of reaſon or prudence; let a verbal profeſſion, <hi>valere quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum valere poteſt,</hi> go as far as it can, as one ſaies, If <hi>Gracchus</hi> be inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive againſt ſedition, I cenſure him by his actions, not by his words.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:30489:129"/>
And if <hi>Cato</hi> be accuſed of mutiny, I cenſure him by himſelf, not by his accuſers. <hi>Omnino enim nihil pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt nomen ſanctum habere ſine mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, quia vita à profeſſionè diſcordans abrogat illuſtris tituli honorem, per indignorum actuum vilitatem. Salvian de Gubernatione Dei, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>in fine.</hi> A profeſſion of Religion is cheap, eſpecially when it is the riſing ſide; and that is the reaſon why <hi>Salvian</hi> and others of the <hi>Fathers</hi> complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſo much of the corruption of the Church, after the Church was in proſperity Emperours being tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Chriſtians. See <hi>Lactant, lib.</hi> 2. 1. <hi>Uſſer. de ſucceſſione, Eccleſ. C.</hi> 1. <hi>ſ.</hi> 22, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It was not only becauſe <hi>Saevior armis luxuria incubuit, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctumque ulciſcitur orbem, Juvenal.</hi> becauſe the warm ſun-ſhine of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity made them caſt off thoſe Garments, or at leaſt wear them more looſe, which the bluſtering winds of perſecution had made
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:30489:129"/>
them keep cloſe to them: But alſo there were many hypocrites turned Chriſtians for advantage; and a verbal profeſſion in the time of the Churches proſperity will not ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie ſo much as it did when a bare profeſſion of Chriſt was enough to expoſe a mans life and eſtate to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard; as we may ſee many, who when they are abroad appear in a handſome garbe and attire, whom we ſhould not know if we met them as they go every day at home: So there are many who make a fair ſhew when they are amongſt thoſe with whom they ſeldom converſe, but go into their Families, or follow them to their Callings and they are quite other men.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Let us not judge of men by particular actions, but by their walking, or the courſe which they hold on in, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 1.1. and 119.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. otherwiſe, we may take the vileſt hypocrite for the moſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:30489:130"/>
eminent Saint, and the beſt Saints for the prophaneſt ſinners. What ſhould we have judged of <hi>Ahab,</hi> when we had ſeen how he humbled himſelf? 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.27. Or of <hi>Jehu,</hi> to have ſeen his zeal for the Lord of Hoſts? 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 10.16. Or of <hi>David,</hi> to have ſeen how he heaped his ſins one upon another, that (as they ſay of ill turns) it might not rain through? 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. Or what ſhould we have thought of <hi>Aſa?</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. who when he had ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſhut the Prophet in priſon that told him of it, and afterwards in his ſickneſs ſought to the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, and not to God.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Judge of men as God judgeth of them; his <hi>Judgement is according to truth, Rom.</hi> 2.2. <hi>He judgeth not as man judgeth, for man looketh on the outward appearance, but the Lord looketh on the heart,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7. <hi>Antiochus</hi> was called <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes,</hi> or the <hi>Illuſtrious,</hi> yet God
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:30489:130"/>
calls him a <hi>vile perſon, Dan.</hi> 11.21. And thoſe are accounted happy times when men are eſteemed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their real merit, and not honoured with gaudy Titles, which do no more become them than a Pearl in a Swines ſnout, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.5. <hi>Reddunt miſeri dignitatum pretia quas non emunt, commercium neſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt &amp; ſolitudinem faciunt, Salvian de Gubernat. Dei, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Quantus in Chriſtiano populo honor Chriſti eſt, ubi religio ignobilem facit? Statim enim ut quis melior eſſe tentaverit, deterior is abjectione calcatur: ac per hoc omnes quodammodo mali eſſe coguntur, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> viles habeantur, Idem. Ibid.</hi> What a ſhame is it that Votaries, and thoſe who make the greateſt proficiency in other Religions ſhould be had in higheſt eſteem amongſt thoſe who profeſs the ſame Religion with them, and amongſt Chriſtians only, thoſe ſhould be moſt contemned that are moſt ſtrict in obſerving the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:30489:131" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Rules of Chriſt; And that men ſhould be under ſuch a temptation amongſt them, as to be forced to be wicked leſt they ſhould be vile and expoſed to contempt? <hi>Si quis aliquid de ſpiritu dixerit, velut in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulſum atque inſipidum cum riſu &amp; ſubſannatione excipiunt, cum ſibilis exuflant, cum clamore &amp; contentione rejiciunt. Clemangis apud Voetium, p.</hi> 3. 65. Such men are as ridiculous and brutiſh to any whoſe wiſdom remains with them, as <hi>Gryllus</hi> in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> who when <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> pitied them, in that condition wherein they were, being tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into beaſts by <hi>Circe,</hi> and prevailed with <hi>Circe</hi> to reſtore them to their former condition again, <hi>Gryllus</hi> diſdains his offer, and tells him, they now deſpiſed him, and would not change their happy condition for the worſe, to be made men again, that is, the moſt wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed creatures in the World. <hi>Man
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:30489:131" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that is in honour and underſtands not,</hi> (that is, <hi>hath not a right underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.20.) <hi>is like the beaſts that periſh, Pſal.</hi> 49.20. Yet they think thoſe that would perſwade them to return to their former ſtate, and recover the Image of God which they have loſt, envy them the happineſs of their preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. <hi>Nobilitas ſola eſt unica vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Juvenal.</hi> The World bleſſeth the covetous man, he that will be rich, that is, a thriving man, that will not boggle at any thing which may ſtand in the way of his gain, <hi>but God abhors ſuch an one, Pſa.</hi> 10.3. That is, the truly noble and brave ſpirit that abhors to be the devils ſlave, and aimes at nothing lower than an incorruptible Crown, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13, 14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.25. <hi>Habet &amp; ſapientia ſui generis ſuperbiam,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion hath its ambition too. <hi>Bern. de amore Dei, cap.</hi> 8. God calls all wicked men fools in Scripture, and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:30489:132" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſo they are indeed. <hi>We ſpeak wiſdom among them that are perfect, yet not the wiſdom of this world, nor of the Princes of this World that come to nought,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. No marvel the Apoſtle diſclaims the wiſdom of the Princes of this World, when they come to nought with all their wiſdom. <hi>Sinite ſapientes hujus ſeculi de ſpiritu hujus mundi tumentes alta ſapientes, &amp; terram lingentes ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter in infernum deſcendere. Bern. de vita ſolitar.</hi> With all their wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome they do but go wiſely to hell; If they <hi>reject the Word of the Lord what wiſdom is in them? Jer.</hi> 8.9. He is the only wiſe man that is <hi>wiſe to Salvation,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Lactan. Inſtitut. lib.</hi> 3. 11. Who fixes on a right end, chooſes fit means for attaining that end, and vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly proſecutes that end in the uſe of thoſe means: and in ſome of theſe points of wiſdom every wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man fails. Indeed, godly men
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:30489:132"/>
may be defective in many points of particular wiſdom, wherein a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man may excel, and God doth not call <hi>many wiſe men after the fleſh,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26. But as Nature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending higher perfection is more negligent of lower things, ſo that Bruits do in many inferiour things excell men, who have a reaſonable ſoul beſtowed on them far ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all the excellencies of bruit Creatures: So God doth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies beſtow the greateſt natural endowments where he intends Grace, which is far better, as in his Church he oft beſtows the greateſt gifts where there is the leaſt grace, to adorn thoſe parts which have moſt need, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.23, 24.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, We muſt judge aright concerning things. <hi>Aquinas</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figns this as one cauſe of ſin, <hi>Falſa aeſtimatio de particulari elegibili.</hi> So <hi>Cebes Thebanus</hi> makes
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:30489:133"/>
a falſe opinion or wrong judgement of what is to be deſired and avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the cauſe of all vices and evils, when men have not judgement to approve the things that are more excellent, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.10. that ſo they may value every thing according to its reall worth. Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> makes thoſe words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.22. to be an anſwer to an objection which might ariſe from what went before; the reaſon why ſo few lay up a treaſure in heaven is, they want underſtanding to diſcern things that differ: As our eſteem is of any thing, ſo will our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be towards it, <hi>Our heart will be where our treaſure is, Mat.</hi> 6.21. that is, where the things which we account our treaſure or ſet greateſt ſtore by are. A very ingenuous Author, <hi>Monlin of a peace and contentment of mind,</hi> makes the right Government of Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to depend on right opinion.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:30489:133"/>
               <q>The great errour (ſaith he, <hi>pag.</hi> 207) of the underſtanding, which makes the paſſion to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it ſelf to an evill object, or to a good object, otherwiſe than it ſhould, is a miſtake in the true price and true inconvenience of things; which being once well known we ſhall abate much of our deſire and fear of moſt things which we ſeek or avoid with great earneſtneſs, and ſhall become earneſt to get other things vvhich vve neglect, and to avoid other things vvhich vve deſire.</q> And as our affections, ſo our endeavours are guided by the opinion vvhich vve have of things; The Merchant vvhen he hath found a treaſure or Pearl vvhich he ſets a great price upon, ſells all he hath to purchaſe it, and runs <hi>per mare per terras,</hi> by ſea and land to get it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.44, 46. So that it is a true obſervation of one, that there is no
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:30489:134"/>
errour more dangerous though it be common, than to think that true happineſs conſiſts in honour, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and riches. <hi>Ceriziers la conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation de la Theologie, l.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>Now, that we may judge aright of things:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Let us not judge according to the appearance; the ſhew of things for the moſt part deceives us, thoſe things that are of leaſt value being moſt taking, and thoſe things moſt affrighting which have little or no evill in them. How doth the pomp and ſplendour of the World, Riches, and Honours, and Pleaſures dazle the eyes, and attract the deſires of moſt men in the World? When they prove but va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and vexation of ſpirit, for the moſt part failing mens expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of worldly comfort and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, and often proving the ruine of their ſouls. And how do men abhor from that which is
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:30489:134"/>
diſpleaſing to Nature? Flying from it as from a Serpent, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did from his Rod while it lay on the ground, which when he had taken it up, proved that Rod whereby he wrought his miracles in <hi>Egypt,</hi> at the Red Sea, in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.3. So we flee from the Croſs when it lies before us, but if we take it up, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.24. it is of much uſe in overcoming our ſpiritual enemies; and it is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually true of every Believer which is ſpoken, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.18. <hi>They ſhall take up Serpents; and if they drink any deadly thing it ſhall not hurt them,</hi> but do them Good, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.11. <hi>Non hominibus tantum ſed &amp; rebus perſona demenda eſt, &amp; reddenda ſua facies, Seneca Ep.</hi> 24. Let us take off the vizards, not only from perſons, but from things, and they will not be ſo dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as they appear, <hi>vid. Lipſi. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:30489:135"/>Secondly, Let us be guided in our judgment of things by the judgment of God. Thoſe things that are highly eſteemed amongſt men are many times an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.15. We, in our folly many times rejoyce in a thing of nought, deſire that which would undo us, are afraid of our mercies. Methinks God ſtands by his children when he is giving them the cup of affliction to drink of, as a father by his childe, when he is giving him a bitter potion; oh (ſaith the childe) I cannot endure to drink it, it is ſo bitter, oh it will make me ſick! oh I ſhall ſaint! fear not, ſaith he, I will not leave thee, I will ſtand by thee, be not afraid, I will hold thee. How do we ſhrink at the thoughts of any affliction? and think we ſhall never be able to bear it, or to hold out under it. Fear not ſaith God, I will hold thy right hand, I will help
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:30489:135"/>
thee, thou art mine, I am with thee, I am thy God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.13, 14.43.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. And obſerve how on the other hand the Scripture vilifies the greateſt and moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable things of this world, making them next unto nothing, yea nothing, and appropriates reality, ſubſtance, truth, worth, and excellency, of being unto the things of the world to come, See <hi>J. Goodwins Catabaptiſme, Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. S.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let us follow the judgment of the wiſeſt men, and thoſe that are moſt fit to judge, as he to whom God gave wiſdome, ſo as there was none like him before, him, or after him, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.12. <hi>Eccleſiast.</hi> 12.8. having made his <hi>Demonſtration</hi> at large, he reſumes his <hi>Concluſion, quod erat demonſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, vanity of vanities all is vanity:</hi> conſult <hi>Paul,</hi> a man who had the ſpirit of God, and ſo was fit to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:30489:136"/>
judge, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.40. he accounts all things but dung in compariſon with the excellency of the knowledg of Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8. conſult the wiſeſt heathens, and the wiſer they were, the nearer they came to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, and the more they contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the things of the world. Conſult men on their ſick beds, or when they are bound in fetters, and held in the cords of affliction, <hi>Job</hi> 36.8. and ſo are brought to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.17. and become <hi>ſanae mentis,</hi> as mad men, that by hard uſage, and ſlender diet, and being kept bound are brought to their wits: theſe will judg other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of the world than they did before; yea, take dying men whoſe ſoules begin to peep out of this dark priſon, and ſee ſome light, how are their judgments alterr'd? how do they mourn at laſt, and bewail their own former fooliſh choice? <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.11, 12.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:30489:136"/>Laſtly, Let us judge according to reaſon, quitting our ſelves like <hi>men,</hi> 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 16.13. and not like beaſts, that minde only what ſenſe gives them notice of. That is the uſe which we ordinarily make of reaſon, to correct the errors of ſenſe, elſe we ſhould never ſowe, to bury our ſeed under a clod: We ſhould never take Phyſick, nor do many other things which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon amongſt men. Let us examine what conduces moſt to our chief end; this made the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> run into ſo many Opinions about the <hi>Summum bonum,</hi> or, <hi>Mans chief happineſſe;</hi> this fell firſt under their conſideration, becauſe <hi>Finis dat bonitatem, &amp; amabilitatem mediis,</hi> they could judge nothing concerning other things till they had determined ſomething con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the chief end of man; every thing elſe being to be judged according to the tendency that it
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:30489:137"/>
hath thereto: Reaſon tels us, <hi>quod diuturnius praeſtantius,</hi> that is beſt which is moſt durable, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.18. things that are not ſeen are <hi>eternal,</hi> theſe things that are ſeen but <hi>temporal.</hi> Reaſon tels us, that the more comprehenſive any good is, the better it is: and God is an <hi>all ſufficient good,</hi> Gen. 17.1. <hi>Cur ergo per multa vagamur, quarendo bona corporis &amp; animae?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Aug. Med. cap.</hi> 18. We weary our ſelves in ſeeking ſeveral pieces of happineſſe, as they are ſcattered among the creatures, when we might in God finde them altogether. And it is a matter of greateſt aſtoniſhment, that men ſhould be ſo farre forſaken of reaſon, as to preferre <hi>broken cisterns which will hold no water before the fountain of living waters,</hi> Jer. 2.12, 13. and, that (when in other things we are impatient of being deceived by others) we willingly permit Satan, for the pleaſures of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:30489:137"/>
ſin, which are but for a moment, to cheat us of thoſe pleaſures which are at Gods right hand for evermore.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:30489:138"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 71. line 7. read <hi>perceptio.</hi> l. 8. r <hi>lectione.</hi> l. 9. r. <hi>quacunque.</hi> p. 107. r. <hi>on ſome</hi> p. 160 l. 6. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> p. 167. l. 24. r. <hi>pabulo.</hi> p. 43. l. 24. r. <hi>allay.</hi> p. 67. l. 7. blot out <hi>in</hi> l. 10. r. <hi>ſolutionem.</hi> There are ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther literal faults and miſpointings, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch as will not much hinder the Reader<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:30489:138"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
